<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>De morbis fœmineis, the womans counsellour: or, The feminine physitian. Modestly treating of such occult accidents, and secret diseases, as are incident to that sex, which their too much modesty, too often to their sorrow, causes them to conceal from others, for a remedy whereof, they are here taught to be their own helpers; especially in these particulars: of barrenness and abortion: of natural, and unnatural births: of the suppression of the termes, the immoderate flux thereof, and other infirmities. Dicereque puduit, scribere jussit. With a brief appendix, touching the kindes, causes, and cures of dropsies, and tympanies of all sorts. / Translated out of Massarius de morbis mulier. By R.T. philomathēs.</title>
            <title>Praelectiones de morbis mulierum. English</title>
            <author>Massaria, Alessandro, 1510-1598.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1657</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 210 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 115 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A88902</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M1028</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1650_3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R209118</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99868016</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99868016</idno>
            <idno type="VID">170219</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A88902)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 170219)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 207:E1650[3])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>De morbis fœmineis, the womans counsellour: or, The feminine physitian. Modestly treating of such occult accidents, and secret diseases, as are incident to that sex, which their too much modesty, too often to their sorrow, causes them to conceal from others, for a remedy whereof, they are here taught to be their own helpers; especially in these particulars: of barrenness and abortion: of natural, and unnatural births: of the suppression of the termes, the immoderate flux thereof, and other infirmities. Dicereque puduit, scribere jussit. With a brief appendix, touching the kindes, causes, and cures of dropsies, and tympanies of all sorts. / Translated out of Massarius de morbis mulier. By R.T. philomathēs.</title>
                  <title>Praelectiones de morbis mulierum. English</title>
                  <author>Massaria, Alessandro, 1510-1598.</author>
                  <author>Turner, Robert, fl. 1654-1665.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 192, 19, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Streater, and are to be sold by the booksellers in London,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1657.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"An appendix touching the dropsy" has caption title and separate pagination; register is continuous.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "June 27".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
                  <note>R.T. = Robert Turner.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Medicine --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Women --  Diseases --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Women --  Diagnosis --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:170219:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>De Morbis Foemineis,</hi> THE Womans Counſellour: OR, <hi>The Feminine Phyſitian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>MODESTLY Treating of ſuch occult accidents, and ſecret Diſeaſes, as are incident to that Sex, which their too much modeſty, too often to their ſorrow, cauſes them to conceal from others; for a Remedy whereof, they are here taught to be their own helpers; eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in theſe particulars: Of barrenneſs and Aborti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: of natural, and unnatural Births: of the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of the Termes, the immoderate Flux there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of and other infirmities.</p>
            <q>Dicere quae puduit, Scribere juſsit.</q>
            <p>With a brief <hi>Appendix,</hi> touching the Kindes, Cauſes, and Cures of Dropſies, and Tympanies of all ſorts.</p>
            <p>Tranſlated out of <hi>Maſſarius de morbis Mulier.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>R. T.</hi> φιλομαθης.<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>John Streater,</hi> and are to be ſold by the Bookſellers in <hi>London,</hi> 1657.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:170219:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:170219:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Courteous Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Am now to write to two Sexes, both Maſculine, and Feminine: This Treatiſe is compoſed uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful for both Men and Women; for men who are <hi>Engliſh</hi> Students, in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent works of nature, the knowledge of Phyſick, who want ſome <hi>Engliſh</hi> ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of this nature, there being nothing of it yet extant. And this Authour com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to my hands, almoſt worn out with the Canker of Time, I have beſtowed the pains to new dreſſe, and revive with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny additions; there being no ſubject more uſeful.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:170219:3"/>
            <p>To the Feminine Gender, Women of all ſorts, be they Maids, Wives, or Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows, what private and occult infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties they are ſubject to, are here deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed, with their cauſes and Cures, Thoſe that are, or intend to take on them the honourable practice of Midwives, may be inſtructed in ſome difficulties that will happen in their Offices, whereby they may be helpful to thoſe they undertake; I mean not the Theorical part of a Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wives Office and Duty: what appertains to that they are ſufficiently, and excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently directed, by that late deceaſed, and yet living <hi>Engliſh Apollo,</hi> Mr. <hi>Cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pepper,</hi> in his Midwives Directory; and here followes the practical part directing what means is to be uſed in any accident there, or that followes, or precedes Child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>birth.</p>
            <p>I have beſtowed the pains plainly to Engliſh the Receipt of every Medicine, in words at length, and not in figures, that every one may underſtand them; and thereby over modeſt Maids and VVo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men may help themſelves in many pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate infirmities, which oftentimes they
<pb facs="tcp:170219:3"/>languiſt under, and will not diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver. Then make uſe hereby, as you have occaſion; and as you finde the Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, give God the prayſe, who hath given power to his weak Creatures, the Herbs of the Field to be your helpers, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervers, which is the deſire of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>R. T. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:170219:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:170219:4"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A</hi> TABLE <hi>OF THE</hi> Contents <hi>of the</hi> Chapters.</head>
            <list>
               <item>OF Womens Diſeaſes in general: The Introduction. Chap. <hi>1.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of the Menſtrue or Termes. C. <hi>2.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of the ſuppreſsion, or ſtopping of the Termes. Chap. <hi>3.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of the immoderate Flux of the Termes. Chap. <hi>4.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of the Flux of the Womb, or the Whites. Chap. <hi>5.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of the Fits of the Mother, or ſuffocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and drawing up of the Matrix. Chap. <hi>6.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of the falling down of the Womb. Chap. <hi>7.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of natural Conceptions. Chap. <hi>8.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of Barrenneſs. Chap. <hi>9.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of monſtrous and unnatural births. C. <hi>10.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of the unnatural fleſhy Conception in the Womb, called Mola. Chap. <hi>11.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of weakneſs of Children in the Womb. Chap. <hi>12.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of Miſchances, and to prevent the ſame. Chap. <hi>13.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:170219:5"/>
               <item>To expel and drive forth a dead Child out of the womb. Chap. <hi>14.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of hard Labour find meanes to procure eaſie Delivery. Chap. <hi>15.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of ſuperfluity of milk, and other acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents happening after the Birth, as ſore breaſts. Chap. <hi>16.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Meanes and Remedies for Nurſes that want milk. Chap. <hi>17.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of Dropſies and Tympanies, an Appendix.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:170219:5"/>
            <head>THE WOMANS COUNSELLOUR.</head>
            <head type="sub">The Introduction.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Chap. I.</hi> Of Womens diſeaſes in generall.</head>
               <p>THis being a Subiect, which too much modeſty, or indeed as it is, ſimple folly of many of the female Sex, hath hindred them from attaining to; and others, to fill their purſes, have, and do ſtill endeavour to conceale; But the want thereof being much, and the benefit great to ſave the health, and ſometimes the lives of many poor women, <hi>whom God made</hi> as like himſelf, as he did the greateſt Queen in the world; is the cauſe of bringing this ſo much neceſſary work to eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:170219:6"/>ones capacity. And to treate peculiarly of the Diſeaſes, and Infirmities incident to women, which as they want a particular Treatiſe, ſo they require a peculiar and proper Cure,<note place="margin">Hipp. <hi>I.</hi> de morbis mul. <hi>331.</hi>
                  </note> as <hi>Hippocrates</hi> at large teacheth: For the women do much differ from the men, from their beginning, and therefore do labour under, and ſuffer many Diſeaſes peculiar and proper only to that Sex; which men can never ſurfer, neither are they incident to them. Wherefore, Is it not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite to call ſuch infirmities wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens diſeaſes, and for them to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtittute not only a proper Treatiſe, but a ſpecial Cure? Nevertheleſſe, it hath been, (and perhaps ſtill is) contended againſt by ſome learned and famous men, who would ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count this Treatiſe needleſſe, and ſeem to averre, that there is no ſuch vaſt diſtinction to be uſed between the Male and Female; but their Diſeaſes having only reſpect to the Sex, may be cured by one and the ſame general method. And this
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:170219:6"/>indeed may be true in ſome common and generall Diſeaſes uſual to both ſexes; but in ſuch infirmities aſ ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertain only to the women, and are not at all contingent to the men, their falſity plainly appears. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Galen, Hippocrates,</hi> &amp; <hi>Dioſcorides,</hi> and many others, have taken the pains to write whole Commentaries meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon the Diſeaſes of women; but yet their works are much incuſed by the corruption of time, though full of much variety of ſpeech, gravity, and excellency of Learning.</p>
               <p>This Treatiſe of the Diſeaſes of wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, is ſo occult, intricate and diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult to perform, that there is nothing to be found in all the Cabinets of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, or ſecrets of the medicinal Art, more abſtruſe and difficult. The cauſes of this are many, as <hi>Hippocrates</hi> numbers them in his Book,<note place="margin">Hipp. de morbis mul. pag. <hi>331.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>De morbis mul. pag.</hi> 131. The firſt cauſe is, that women carry Diſeaſes a long time a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout them, and root it in them, and yet are either voluntarily, or fooliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ignorant thereof; either they do not know, or elſe are ſo ſuperfluouſly
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:170219:7"/>modeſt as they will not diſcover the ſame, until time and neceſſity, too late to their pain, teaches them to know them by experience. And from hence it followes, that their Cure is not onely difficult, but oftentimes their Diſeaſes are incurable.</p>
               <p>The ſecond cauſe <hi>Hippocrates</hi> num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>breth to be this; That a great many women that are troubled with ſome ſecret Diſeaſe, and do well know the ſame, yet are ſo ſhamefac't and modeſt as rather to ſuffer under the ſame, than to communicate their minds to the Phyſician. Whereas he that wears the ſhoo beſt knows where it wrings; and amongſt other Cauſes, the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation of the Patient, diſcovers to the Phyſician the knowledge, and ſo conſequently, the Cure of the Diſeaſe may be the eaſier effected. Now the Phyſician being deſtitute of that help, by reaſon of the ſilence of the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, the knowledge of the Diſeaſe is the more hard to find out, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently the Cure more difficult.</p>
               <p>This alſo may be added for a third cauſe, the too much verecundity or ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midity
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:170219:7"/>of the Phyſicians, dealing too careleſly with the women, being too ſhamefac'd, or baſhful to deal plainly with them, and to inquire of them diligently and perfectly, the cauſes of their infirmities, and alſo <hi>abſconditos locos ſuos attingere &amp; tractare,</hi> which is neceſſary and needfully required. Of which negligence, <hi>Hippocrates</hi> doth much reprove and reprehend many Phyſicians, who do not accurately and carefully ſtudy to ſearch out, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the true Cauſes of womens Diſeaſes, without the knowledge whereof, their going about to Cure them, is raſh and indiſcreet.</p>
               <p>But to paſſe by theſe Cauſes, which, are of no ſmall moment, it will not be amiſs to add another, that the ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance of Midwives, not knowing the internal ſecret parts of nature, nor how to exhibite in word or outward remedies, may cauſe to the women difficult and hard labours.</p>
               <p>From all which, is conſequently gathered, that the Cauſes finding out, the matter and knowledge of womens Diſeaſes, containeth in it many ſecrets and great difficulties.</p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:170219:8"/>
               <p>But theſe difficulties carry with them, and comprehend in themſelves a recompence of jucundity and profit; For what is more delightful to man than to underſtand ſo great ſecrets and myſteries of Nature? And what can be more profitable to a Phyſician than to finde out and know the way and manner of curing, and helping the infirmities and diſeaſes of women? For ſince that the infirmities which do moſt frequently afflict miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable women, are very many moſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute and grievous, in ſo much that their complaints may be heard almoſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually from the very Womb; cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly Phyſicians in the ſtudy of their Cure ſhall not only gain great eſteem and honour, but much profit. This therefore induceth me to render this Treatiſe plainly in the <hi>Engliſh</hi> tongue, that the women themſelves may be their own Phyſicians.</p>
               <p>The firſt thing therefore here inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to be handled is of the Concepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of man; and therein the firſt thing to be noted, is the diſtinction and difference of the Sexes of man and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:170219:8"/>without which no Conception can be had, nor the Courſe of nature maintained; of which that it may be fully and perfectly underſtood by you, we ſhall ſpeak plainly; I ſay therefore as the Philoſophers teach, that all things whatſoever that are, have a two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold <hi>ens</hi> or being, ſome ingenerative incorruptible, eternal as Intelligen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Heaven: others generative corruptible and momentary, as theſe inferiour Elements, and thoſe things which conſiſt of the Elements.</p>
               <p>Although the Elements, as to the whole, are ingenerative and incorrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible, nevertheleſſe, according to the parts they are generated, and corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and are ſubject to continual tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutation. But the Cauſe thereof is the <hi>materia prima,</hi> or firſt matter, which alwaies deſires new forms as the Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers in their Phyſicks every where teach. But to let paſſe all other circumſtances,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gal.</hi> 14. cap. 11.</note> 
                  <hi>Galen</hi> tells you, there was a man ſo ſtudious in the ſecrets of Nature, as to ſeek if it were poſſible to be immortal, and bring immortality upon the Body. But the <hi>materia pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma,</hi>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:170219:9"/>or which, if you will, call it God himſelf, knew this to be unlawful, and this <hi>Galen</hi> ſufficiently declareth;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gal.</hi> 1: cap. 1.</note> For that which conſiſteth of <hi>Arteries,</hi> Veins, Nerves, Bones and Fleſh, is the compound of Nature, and therefore is ſubject to corruption, for the <hi>Fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bricatum</hi> or building of Nature, is a plain way, yet impoſſible to bring a man to immortality, his ſtructures are ſubject to fall. The greateſt of Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and the wiſeſt of men be their Counſels never ſo great, or their peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple never ſo many, and their wiſdom and their providence never ſo much, time will bring them all to nothing. Therefore the workes of Nature are wonderful, as, that as one dies, another lives, and inſtead of one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſucceeds; and by that Rule you may call nature to be immortal, but this is no other but the continual Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration of mankind:<note place="margin">Gal. <hi>6.7.14. 3</hi> De uſu part.</note> ſo teacheth Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy, and ſo the learned write. There is no part of the Body, but is neceſſary to be uſed, and competent to the protection of life, as the Brain, the Heart, the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:170219:9"/>Liver, the Eyes, the Noſe, the Ears, but if we ſhould particularly inſtance the <hi>primum mobile</hi> of Nature, we muſt then ſpeak of the four principal parts which carry a diſtinction between the Male and the Female, and are the preſervers and continuers of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind.</p>
               <p>I'le preſume ſo much modeſty as to give you theſe tearms in the old tongue,<note place="margin">Turner.</note> my meaning cannot be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known, 'twas lawfull for <hi>Ovid</hi> to write what he would not ſpeak, and you may know my meaning; the parts following which we muſt treat of, are the maintainers and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues of the World before the confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of <hi>Babel,</hi> called <hi>pudenda, teſtes, utert.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You know my mind, if you do not his, in <hi>Engliſh,</hi> ſuch things as have the beſt ſenſe of feeling.</p>
               <p>Of this which we ſaid before, we in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend only to diſcriminate the Sexes, without which no Generation can be had in any Creature whatſoever, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the perfect mixture of Male and Female.</p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:170219:10"/>
               <p>And therefore <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> in all his works,<note place="margin">Arist. de gen. <hi>c. 2</hi>
                  </note> counted the Earth to be the Mother of all Creatures, the Sun the Father and begetter of them: ſo ſaith likewiſe <hi>Plato,</hi> and all others, that the Man and the Woman conſiſt of two Elements of the Sun and Moon; the Father and begetter to be the Fire or Sun, the woman or conceiver to be the Earth or Moon, of which the whole World is built and conſiſts.</p>
               <p>As the Macrocoſmus or great world conſiſts,<note place="margin">Turner.</note> and is properly ſupported by the Sun and Moon, which are the male and female of the ſame great World. ſo the Microcoſmus Man, by the woman which is the Moon of the man, and the Earth of the Microcoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, and the field of his generation, products the continual generation of mankind. To ſpeak of the differences of Sects and parts between man and woman, would take up a Volume in Philoſophy, beyond our preſent inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which intends only the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities incident to the Moon of the man, or that Creature which we call a woman; Something may be ſaid how
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:170219:10"/>the Sun and Moon of the Microcoſme, or the man and the woman differ in parts and nature, Philoſophy largely teacheth it, but we ſay no more but only they differ in Faculty. For the Man or the Sun of the Microcoſme, hath a power or faculty to ingender in another, that is, in the Moon, but the woman hath alſo a faculty in po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of generating, or bringing forth in her ſelf, by the help of the Sun her husband, without which mutual con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction no Generation can be had.</p>
               <p>I hope you have wit enough to know what I mean by the Sun and the Moon, that I may not be forc'd to Engliſh one thing twice: and if you be Men or Women, then know that by the Sun I mean the Man, and by the Moon the Woman; <hi>which if ſhe be a whore, I cannot help it.</hi> That's an Eclipſe to the microcoſmical Sun; And as theſe two differ in Sex, ſo they differ in Nature, and in the ſeveral Faculties of Nature, and Members belonging to procreation, and Generation of Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures accomodated the one to the other; but if you will take the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:170219:11"/>
                  <hi>Aristotle</hi> he calleth them in Women <hi>Pudenda</hi> and <hi>uterus,</hi> and in Men <hi>Teſtes</hi> and <hi>Membrum virile. Teſtes</hi> ſignifies properly, witneſſes; and a man without ſuch witneſſes will have bad ſucceſs in his cauſe,<note place="margin">Turner.</note> if women be of the Jury. And therefore the firſt Mover and Maker of all things knew it neceſſary, to have a procreati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Mankind, for the continual ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply of the World, which ſhould be as well Male as Female; and therefore he made the Woman, and fitted her anſwerably to be accomodated to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Inſtrument of the Microcoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mical Sun the Man, neceſſarily fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting one to the other for the Act of ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration, and this was the cauſe why 'twas thought not fit, the Man ſhould be alone, for if he had been ſo, the World had ceaſed in him: and 'twas not only ſufficient to make a Man and a Woman ſo, and furniſh them with Inſtruments proper to conjunction and copulation; but alſo, that as well in the Man as in the Woman, there ſhould be a deſire, and magnetical attraction to the Act of copulation,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:170219:11"/>by a ſympathy between themſelves; or elſe, the very Act it ſelf would be ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horred, and the ſpecies of humane Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration fruſtrate, and come to no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, by an abhorrency of the Act it ſelf naturally as it is, whereby the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention of Nature would have fallen to the ground, and one Man, and one Woman onely, been made in vain. Therefore the ſagacity of Nature, to cauſe propenſity in both Sexes, to the Act of Generation for procreation ſake, endued both with a reciprocal pleaſure, and delight in the Act of Coition it ſelf.</p>
               <p>And this propenſity and pleaſure, is not ordained in men and women on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but in all other Animals, to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain a continual ſucceſſion of genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions amongſt them: as appears by the great fierceneſs, and earneſt deſire of all Creatures to this Act, of which the Philoſophers largely write; but we paſſe, it as not pertinent to our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent intent, and come to ſpeak of the menſtrual or monethly Courſes, by the natural conſtitution whereof, all women are more or leſſe weak or
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:170219:12"/>ſtrong, diſeaſed or ſound, more or leſſe able and meet for Conception accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the ſpecies or degrees thereof.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Chap. II.</hi> Of the <hi>Menſtrua</hi> or Terms.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>ARiſtotle</hi> delivers,<note place="margin">Ariſt. <hi>1.</hi> de gen. Anim. <hi>cap. 19.</hi>
                  </note> that the <hi>Men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrua</hi> is an Excrement, and in proportion as the Seed of man; and that they happen to Women at the ſame age as the men begin to have Seed; And that the humours of the Terms are purged forth by Nature, as ſuperfluous and unprofitable: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they may be comprehended un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the general notion of an Excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the principal uſe thereof is, for generation ſake, which is the firſt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution thereof, the Birth deſiring a copious matter for nutriment.</p>
               <p>The Terms generally begin in all Women,<note place="margin">The time</note> about the fourteenth year of their age, about which time alſo Men begin to have Seed, and both
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:170219:12"/>men and women change their voice, and are ſubject to many other muta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in their Bodies. And they ceaſe, as the ſame Philoſopher writes, about the 50th. year, ſeldome longer conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuing.</p>
               <p>The time of their flowing, is not in all alike, for ſome have theſe purgati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons but one day, others two, three, and four dayes, according to the age and temperament of the Woman. For ſometimes they flow more, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times leſſe: ſometimes longer, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſhorter. In women that are ſound of body; they moderately flow two or three dayes, if any longer or ſhorter time, that Woman is ſickly, or barren.</p>
               <p>And ſo much for the Terms in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, we will proceed now to ſpeak of the ſuppreſſion or ſtopping there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:170219:13"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Chap. III.</hi> Of the ſtopping, or ſuppreſſion of the Terms.</head>
               <p>WHereas by the inſtitution of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, it is neceſſarily provided, that all Women ſhould ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e their monethly natural purgations, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the temperature of this Sex, and many other cauſes: but if they be ſuppreſt or ſtopt, there followes to that Woman much peril and many ſickneſſes, but on the other ſide, if they have their purgations according to the law of Nature, it keeps them in health, and preſerves them from many Diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes.</note>The Cauſes of the ſuppreſſion of the Terms, or diminiſhing of them are principally four,
<list>
                     <item>The firſt is, the vitiouſneſs of the Womb, and of the Veſſels pertaining thereunto.</item>
                     <item>The ſecond is, the vice, or corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the blood.</item>
                     <item>The third, the viciouſneſſe of the whole Body.</item>
                     <pb n="17" facs="tcp:170219:13"/>
                     <item>The fourth and the laſt are, the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſneſs and the Faculties of the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, to which all other cauſes may be referred.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt therefore, the Terms are ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt, or diminiſht by reaſon of the Womb, and the Veſſels belonging thereunto, by which the Terms ought to be purged; if therefore the Womb labour under any Diſeaſe, which may be many, as that if the ſubſtance of the womb be too hard or too thick, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe then is agreeable to Nature, that cauſes a ſtopping of the Terms, that muſt be brought to a better habit, with fit medicaments, and uſed in time for a convenient remedy.</p>
               <p>Secondly, there doth happen Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſes of intemperateneſs, which are various, ſimple and compound, ſome with matter, and ſome without mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, under all which the Womb may labour, partly by Nature, and from the Birth, and partly growing in time againſt Nature, as hardneſſe and thickneſſe, of which we have ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken.</p>
               <p>Of theſe Cauſes, the Simple are
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:170219:14"/>cold and dry, the Compound hot and dry; both which, may ſtop the Terms, cauſe the Womb to grow thick and hard, deſtroy the blood and impedite the natural purgation.</p>
               <p>Then there are Diſeaſes of intem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perateneſſe with matter, as Inflamma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Swellings, Tumours, and Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers againſt Nature.</p>
               <p>Then there are other Diſeaſes, as Ulcers, Fiſtulaes, Impoſthums, and the like, which the Womb is ſubject to, which alſo impedite the Terms.</p>
               <p>The ſecond cauſe of the ſuppreſſion of the Terms, is corruption of blood, which may be either too thick, or too glutinous, by reaſon of the vicious thickneſs of the humours, the Diet and many other cauſes frequently hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pening.</p>
               <p>The third Cauſe, which cauſes Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men many times, not to have their Purgations at all, is the viciouſneſſe of the whole Body, that it ſends not blood ſufficient to the Womb for this matter to be digeſted of; the humour inclining to other parts of the Body, either cauſed by ill Diet, or too much
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:170219:14"/>exerciſe, as often happens in ſome ruſtick Women; whereby their tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perament becomes too hot and dry, almoſt inclining to the nature of men.</p>
               <p>Another Cauſe of the ſuppreſſion of the Terms, is the weakneſs of the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men in general, whereby the blood wanting power for Concoction runs to ſome other parts of the Body; and ſo long as the Woman labours under that weakneſs, the purgations are hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, if not altogether ſtopped. But thus much may ſuffice for the Cauſes, we ſhall now proceed to the Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptoms, Prognoſticks, and Remedies to be uſed in the helping this infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity.</p>
               <p>Though outwardly no viſible ſign may appear, but only the meer relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the party afflicted; yet the differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences thereof, may be judged by the Cauſes, and Accidents attending it, and the part of the Body thereby af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted. Whether the whole Body be vitiated and diſeaſed, or the defect be in the Womb, or Veſſels, as that the Mouth of the Womb be diſtorted
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:170219:15"/>and turned aſide out of its due place, or ſome other impediment there a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout; or if there be a perpetual ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of the Terms, then it plainly ſhows ſuch a Woman to be abſolutely barren.</p>
               <p>If the Obſtruction come by weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Veſſels, and expulſive po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer then that is perceived by immode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate heat, great thirſt, a ſwift and ſtrong pulſe, head-ach, and many other ſigns of heat.</p>
               <p>But if the cauſe thereof happen to be from cold, then the Woman is dull, drowſy, and much given to ſleepineſs, but without any thirſt: the pulſe beats very ſlow, and the Urine is of a loath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome colour.</p>
               <p>If the Diſeaſe proceed from ſome inward cauſe, it is diſcovered by the fatneſs or leanneſs of the party.</p>
               <p>This Obſtruction uſually brings to the party afflicted, not only barren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, but oftentimes the Falling-ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Suffocation, Swellings and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtumes of the Womb, and the other parts appertaining thereunto, much dulneſs and drowſineſs over all the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:170219:15"/>Body, Coughing, difficulty of brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, the Dropſy, detention of the Urine, coſtiveneſs, heavineſs of mind, pain in the Head, and many other in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities.</p>
               <p>Now therefore, to proceed to the Remedies to be adminiſtred for Cure of this infirmity, it will be very fit and neceſſary in the firſt place, to looſen the Belly; which may be done by Gliſters, which diſſolve wind, and gently looſe as thus:</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>A Gliſter for the ſtopping the Terms.</head>
                  <p>Take flowers of Camomile and Mugwort of each one handful; Anni-ſeeds and Fennel-ſeeds, each an ounce, and make a Decoction thereof.</p>
                  <p>Then, take of this Decoction a pound, or a pint, which you pleaſe: three drams of oyl of Camomile and brown Sugar to make it a Gliſter; ſo give it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Hiera Piera,</hi> is much co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mended in theſe caſes, to purge the Excrements of the Veſicles, and remove thoſe groſſe humours.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:170219:16"/>
                  <head>A proper Receipt thereof may be thus, to provoke the Terms.</head>
                  <p>Take the Species of <hi>Hiera,</hi> or (if it be lawful for me to ſpeak <hi>Engliſh;</hi> and that 'tis a hard matter to do of ſuch ugly unſignificant words, as purblind Phyſicians have deviſed)</p>
                  <p>Take four ounces of the powder of <hi>Hiera pi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ra,</hi> and mix it with honey of Roſes, or ſyrup of Roſes, a ſufficient quantity to make it into a <hi>Bolus.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Alſo, take of the ſame ſimple Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, or plain powder of <hi>Hyera,</hi> two drams, that is, a quarter of an ounce; and mix it with a ſufficient quantity of ſyrup of Betony, that it may be made a <hi>Bolus.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take three drams of ſolutive ſyrup of Roſes; and a ſufficient quantity of the Decoction of Citron-ſeeds; make it into a Potion or drink, which you pleaſe, &amp; take it immediatly after the <hi>Hiera Bolus</hi> before directed.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:170219:16"/>
                  <head>Another excellent, is this.</head>
                  <p>Take of the powder of <hi>Hiera picra</hi> three drams; of the Electuary called <hi>Lenitivum,</hi> and <hi>Caſſia</hi> newly drawn, three drams; mix it into a <hi>Bolus</hi> with fine Sugar.</p>
                  <p>Be pleaſed to give me leave to tell you what a <hi>Bolus</hi> is;<note place="margin">Turner.</note> for It is a tearm Phyſicians have caught by the end, without ſenſe or reaſon, to fright you with. <hi>Bolus,</hi> is a Latin word, and ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies as much in <hi>Engliſh</hi> as to ſay, a mouthful or morſel, or as much as one can ſwallow at once, ſo that you may make it a Pill or Electuary, which you pleaſe: for you know both are to be ſwallowed.</p>
                  <p>Some do refuſe the uſe of <hi>Caſſia</hi> to be adminiſtred in ſuch caſes, and condemn it; but being well admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred with <hi>Hiera piera,</hi> it is very com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modious for this diſeaſe.</p>
                  <p>The opening of a Vein, or letting of bloud, is very proper for this Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſe, if it appears that there be a ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitude, or corruption thereof; it is
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:170219:17"/>properly to be drawn from the lower parts of the Body,<note place="margin">Give me leave to be ſo mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt as conceale that.</note> as the Foot; ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times from the Thighs and <hi>Venis Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biti, et ab utero;</hi> you may imagine my meaning though I ſpeak Latine: but I ſay, the ſuperfluous blood muſt be drawn out, and that downwards, or elſe it will endanger to ſpoil the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy.<note place="margin">Sub ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trice.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>Ligature and binding of the Thighs, is alſo requiſite in this caſe, and to keep the ſame bound to draw down the blood.</p>
                  <p>Alſo, if the Veins in the Matrix be obſtructed and ſtopt, and the humour of blood abounds, it is requiſite that there be a Vein opened, to take away the blood, and that there be other means uſed to diminiſh the ſame, as laxative and opening Medicines, uſing abſtinence and exerciſe, as need re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires; but where no order nor abſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence is uſed, never expect a good re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy.</p>
                  <p>But take it for a general Rule, that at firſt you begin to provoke the Terms, with gentle and lenitive mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Medicines, afterwards, if that
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:170219:17"/>do not the work, proceed to ſtronger by degrees, alwaies having due reſpect to the age and ſtrength of the perſon.</p>
                  <p>For young and tender perſons ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally, this is a gentle mover of the Terms; ſyrup of Betony, of Mugwort, of honey of Roſes , the decoction of Betony, and Hyſop, Ceterach.</p>
                  <p>Simples gently provoking and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the Terms: which are warm by nature, are accounted theſe;</p>
                  <p>Smallage roots, Fennel roots, roots of Butchers broom, of Parſly, Madder, Aſarabacca, Valerian and Elecam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pane;</p>
                  <p>The ſeeds of Lupines, Sperage, Parſly, Smallage, Annis, Fennel, Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min.</p>
                  <p>Of herbs theſe, Cinquefoile, Mug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wort, wild Mints, Harts-tongne, Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jerom, Fetherfew, Wormwood, Juni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, wild Time, Lovage, Maidenhair, Southernwood, and waſht Turpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine.</p>
                  <p>Stronger Simples to provoke the Terms, are; Hemlock, Rue, Cento<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, Savin, Euphorbium, Sagapenum, Ammoniacum, Mirrh, Aſſa foetida,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:170219:18"/>Muſtard-ſeed, Celandine roots, Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quint, Pepper, black Hellebore, Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras.</p>
                  <p>Theſe with the former, are to be uſed in powder, Syrrup, Juyce or De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coction, but beware you be not too buſie in medling with ſome of the laſt mentioned, leſt you repent it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>A Syrup to Concoct, and prepare the humours, to provoke the Terms.</head>
                  <p>Take Syrup of of Betony, of Mug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wort, and Elecampane, of each half an ounce; of the Decoction of Hyſop, and Betony, of each four ounces; mix them together, and ſo take it when you pleaſe.</p>
                  <p>Odoriferous things which provoke the Terms are, Cynamon, Caſſia Lig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nea, Coſtus roots, Muſcus, Spica Indiae, Spica Romana, Gallia muſcata, and ſuch like.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Fumes to be burnt to move the Terms are,</head>
                  <p>Oppoponacum, Soponoria, Frankin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe, Lignum Aloes, and red Storax.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:170219:18"/>
                  <head>Things by nature cool, which move the Terms, are,</head>
                  <p>The ſeeds of ſmall Endive, of Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lons, of Gourds, of Pompeons, Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbers and Lettice; of which Peſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries may be made, to uſe in the Womb; but have a care you put a ſtring to them, to get them out again when you pleaſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>A Syrup to take away the Obſtructions in the Body, which hinder the Terms.</head>
                  <p>Take Madder, two ounces; of the roots of Lovage, Sperage, Cypers, and graſſe, each an ounce and a half; Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Mountaine and Balm, of each two ounces, Spica Indiae, half a dram; Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corice, Currans, Roſemary flowers, and Stecados, of each an ounce; ſix ounces of Honey, and nine ounces of Sugar; boyl it into a ſyrup, and take thereof two ounces at a time.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:170219:19"/>
                  <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
                  <p>Take two ounces of Madder, Sperage roots, Cypers roots, and the roots of Butchers broom, of each an ounce, Valerian Sabine, white water Mints, and Penny-royal, of each a handful; Baulm two handfuls; of Melon ſeed, one ounce; Licorice and Currans, each half an ounce; Honey and Sugar, of each ſix ounces; ſo make it into a ſyrup, and take thereof about an ounce and a half at a time.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>To provoke the Terms strongly.</head>
                  <p>Take the water of Smallage, of Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pins, Sperage, and Fennel, of each ſix ounces; a dram of Cinamon, a quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of an ounce of Spica Indiae; Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniacum and Oppopanacum, of each a dram and a half; Parſly ſeed, Fennel ſeed, wild yellow Rape ſeed, and Carraway, of each a quarter of an ounce; Gromell ſeed and Agrimony, of each a handful; Galingale and Saffron, of each half a dram, the ker<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nels
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:170219:19"/>of Quinces and Mallow ſeeds, of each half an ounce; Syrup of Violers, two ounces; boyl them all, except the ſyrup in two quarts of Gourds water, till the third part be waſted; then ſtrain it, and mix it with the ſyrup of Violets, and boil it with ſo much Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney as you ſee convenient; then ſtrew a little powder of Cinamon into it, and Vinegar of Squils, enough to make it ſowriſh; then take of it in quantity as the former.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Common Sirups whith remove obſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Terms, are,</head>
                  <p>Syrup of Mugwort, of Maiden-hair, of Chicory with Rubarb, and the ſyrup of the five roots; theſe you may have ready made at the Apothecaries.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>A Laxative to open the Body, and purge ſuperfluous humours.</head>
                  <p>Take Sene leaves, Penny-royal and Madder, of each a like quantity; boyl them in white Wine, take thereof about three ounces at a time faſting.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:170219:20"/>
                  <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
                  <p>Take Penny-royal, Nep, Southern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood, Rue, Centory and Hyſop, of each one handful; Savin and Fether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>few, of each one handful and an half; Galingale, a dram: Cinamon and Madder, of each one handful; Mirrh, a quarter of an ounce; boyl them toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in a quart of fair water till the third part be waſted, take thereof two or three ounces faſting at a time.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take Sperage, Smallage, Fennel and Parſly roots, <hi>Carduus benedictus</hi> and Butchers broom, of each an ounce and a half; Annis, Fennel and Carraway ſeeds, of each a dram and a half; Mug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wort, Penny-royal, Mints, Horehound, Aſſarabacca, and Fetherfew, of each half a handful; ſeeth them altogether in two quarts of water till half be wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted; then ſtrain it, and mix there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with the ſyrup of the five roots of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamint and Mugwort, of each a like
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:170219:20"/>quantity, and drink thereof in the morning and afternoon, about two ounces.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Another to move the Terms.</head>
                  <p>Take Mints, Balm, Penny-royal, Marjerom and Southernwood, of each an handful; Anni-ſeeds, Fennel and Carraway ſeeds, of each an ounce; Polipody, an ounce and an half; Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cory roots, an ounce; cut the roots and herbs very ſmall, and boyl them all together in a quart of water till a third part be conſumed; then ſtrain it, and ſweeten it with Sugar to your own likeing, and take thereof as you pleaſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>A Syrup to provoke the Terms.</head>
                  <p>Take four handfuls of Cicory roots, take out the pith, and cut them ſmall, and boyl them a good ſpace in two quarts of White wine; ſtrain it, and then boyl the decoction unto a ſyrup with Sugar, and take thereof about two ſpoonfuls, evening and morning.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:170219:21"/>
                  <head>A Trochis to move the Terms.</head>
                  <p>Take a dram and a half of Mirrh, two drams and an half of Lupines, Rue, water Mints, Comin, Madder, Elecampane roots, Sagapenum, Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>popanacum, of each a dram; make it into Trochis, with the juyce of Mug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wort and give half an ounce thereof in the decoction of Juniper berries, made with water.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Wines good to provoke the Terms.</head>
                  <p>Wine of Elecampane roots, of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jerom gentle, of the herb Rennet, of Betony, of Gellow-flowers, and of Roſemary; theſe are very good if the Patients Body be fitting to drink Wine, otherwiſe diſcretion may di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect you not to uſe it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Confections good for this Diſeaſe are,</head>
                  <p>The Confection of Elecampane roots, the Confection of Eringo roots, Conſerves of Pioney, and Mirrh roa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted in an Apple.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:170219:21"/>
                  <head>Pills to move the Terms.</head>
                  <p>Take the Pill Alephargine, half a dram; Aloes, two ſcruples; Savin in powder, one ſcruple make in into Pills with the water of Mugwort, and take half thereof at once; theſe provoke the Terms, and are ſafe without any danger.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Others for the ſame.</head>
                  <p>Take-Pill Alephargine, half a dram; pill Cochiae, one ſcrupſe, mix them into five Pills, and take them at once.</p>
                  <p>By the way, heed is to be taken that theſe Medicines are not to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited at ſuch time as the Flowers do uſe to come, or nature uſeth to ſend forth the menſtrual purgations; for at that time they may draw and turn the humors from the womb, where nature would yent and purge it, to ſome other parts of the Body, to the impediting of nature, and dammage of the Body: but the whole Body being purged and cleanſed, then 'tis a fit time to apply
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:170219:22"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="33" facs="tcp:170219:22"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="34" facs="tcp:170219:23"/>theſe Medicaments, which may take away the intemperatneſs, and remove the vices and obſtructions of the Womb and Veſſels; purifie the craſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſious and corrupted bloud, and extenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate the ſame out of the Veſſels; and briefly provoke the Terms: To do which, you ſee the ways and means are manifold, partly ſimple, partly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound, partly internal, and partly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal, to be adminiſtred and exhibited ſundry wayes, and for ſundry reaſons, as the cauſe and neceſſity ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, to which we further proceed.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Pills to procure the Terms.</head>
                  <p>Take Musk and Mirrh, of each four ſcruples, Sterhas, Madder, Penny-roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, Citron pills, long Pepper, Caſſia wood, Caſſia pills, Pioney ſeeds and Calmus, of each three quarters of an ounce; Spica Indiae, half a dram: make Pills thereof with the juyce of Mugwort; whereof take a dram at once.</p>
                  <p>Thus far of inward Medicines, to procure the Terms; there are alſo
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:170219:23"/>many outward Medicines to be uſed if need require, the firſt part whereof are Baths and Lotions, which are part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly natural, as of the natural water of hot Baths; and partly artificial, which are prepared of congruent and fitting Medicaments.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>A Bath or Lotion for the Terms.</head>
                  <p>Take of Camomile flowers, of Mugwort, Calamint, Dictamnus of Crete, Briony, Savin, of each one handful; of Anniſeeds, Fennel ſeeds, yellow Carrot ſeeds, and Ameos, of each an ounce; mix them altogether and therewith make a Decoction in water.</p>
                  <p>The uſe of theſe Lotions and Baths, is twofold; Firſt, to waſh and Bathe the Thighs and lower parts of the Woman, with the water decocted; and ſecondly, for the woman to ſit in a Bath up to her middle.</p>
                  <p>The ſecond ſort of external mede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines are injections, or medecines to be injected into the Womb; and Peſſaries, or Suppoſitories to be put
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:170219:24"/>into the Womb, and remain there a ſpace. Suppoſitories are made of me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>decines wrapt up in wooll or bom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſt, or ſome ſuch like thing; and ſo put up into the Womb, and there a great while to be detained.</p>
                  <p>But alwaies remember that you tie a ſtring thereunto, put about the Thigh, that it may again be taken out when you pleaſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>A Peſſary for the Terms.</head>
                  <p>Take the leaves, roots, and juyce of Mercury, and make thereof a Peſſary, and apply it alone; it may alſo be mixed with other Medicaments.</p>
                  <p>Peſſaries of odoriferous things, and Aromaticks are very good.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>An Aromatick Peſſary to draw down the Flowers.</head>
                  <p>Take of Gum Ladanum the beſt, two parts; of Belzoine and Mirrh, of each one part; of Musk, one part: mix the Aromaticks with oyl of white Lillies, a ſufficient quantity, to make it into a fit form, and ſo put it up.</p>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:170219:24"/>
                  <p>Peſſaries more ſtrong in operation, are ſuch as are made of Coloquintida, Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ony, Scammony, and the like, an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample whereof take following.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>A Peſſary to move the Terms.</head>
                  <p>Take of Ox gall, the juyce of Brio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, of each one ounce; Pulp of Golo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quintida, two drams; of Mirrh one dram; make this into a Peſſary as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is directed, and ſo apply it.</p>
                  <p>In the third place outward means to be uſed, are, fumes and ſuffumigati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and they are beſt to be made of odoriferous Aromatick things, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of take this example.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>A Fumigation to procure the Terms.</head>
                  <p>Take Belzoinum, Storax, Calamint, Mirrh, Bdellium, of each a dram;<note place="margin">Theſe you may have at the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potheca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries.</note> Gallia Muſcata Meſ: half a dram; Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bethum, half a ſcruple; Storax liquid, or oyl of Spike perfumed, a ſufficient quantity, to make it into Pills or Trochis.</p>
                  <p>This is to be put on a moderate
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:170219:25"/>fire, that the fume may aſcend, and the Woman is to be ſo comodiouſly pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, that ſhe may receive the fume up into the Matrix, through a veſſel or funnel fit for that purpoſe, which is to be made broad at that end next the fire, that it may receive all the ſmoke, and with a narrow neck like a funnel, to inject the fume into the Matrix.</p>
                  <p>But theſe Fumigations as <hi>Hippocra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes</hi> teacheth,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Hipp.</hi> 5. <hi>Apho.</hi> 28.</note> uſe to cauſe the Headach. Therefore, the Woman ought to be well covered &amp; fortified with clothes, that the vapours may be kept from aſcending to the Head.</p>
                  <p>In the fourth place, amongſt the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Medicines, unguents and plai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters are to be uſed, and applyed to the <hi>Abdomina</hi> or ſecret places.</p>
                  <p>Letting of blood is alſo to be uſed in the Foot, or elſe where, as need re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires us.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>An Oyl good to bring down the Flowers.</head>
                  <p>Take oyl of ſweet Almonds; two ounces; of white Lillies, one ounce;
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:170219:25"/>Oyl of Anniſeed, two drams; Mixe them, and therewith anoint &amp;c. it is very effectual for infirmities in thoſe parts.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>A Plaiſter to apply, to move the Terms.</head>
                  <p>Take of Penny-royal, Calamint, Ditanny, Mugwort, of each one hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful; Cinamon, Cloves, Mirth, Balſom, of each a dam; meal of Peaſe, a pound; mixe them with White-wine upon the fire, and make thereof a plaiſter, and apply it to the <hi>pundenda.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>An Ointment for the ſame.</head>
                  <p>Take Muſſilage of Fleawort, and Linſeed, of each an ounce; Butter Unſalted, two ounces; Hens greaſe, Ducks greaſe, Gooſe greaſe, Marrow of Calves bones, of each half an ounce; Ammoniacum, a quarter of an ounce; oyl of Seſanum, oyl of ſweet Almonds, of each five drams; Wax ſufficient to make it into a ſalve. With this Oint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, anoint the Body behind and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, from the Navel downwards; but
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:170219:26"/>not before you have uſed all other in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward means, and outward of Bathing, letting blood, Fumes, Peſſaries, &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>A Plaister for the ſame.</head>
                  <p>Take <hi>Confectio benedicta,</hi> half an ounce; Turbith, a quarter of an ounce; Nigella ſeed, three drams; clarified Honey, enough to make it into a Plai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter.</p>
                  <p>This Plaiſter, is to be applyed over the Privities, as before is directed.</p>
                  <p>If you perceive the Courſes begin to appear, then take this drink follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
                  <p>Take Mugwort, Sene leaves and Penny-royal, of each half a handful; Cinamon, half an ounce; Mace, three drams; boil theſe altogether in three pints of good Wine, until the fourth part be waſted: boil it in a pot ſtopt cloſe in boiling water, otherwiſe cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Balneo Mariae.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In the laſt place, is to be uſed fricti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, or often rubbing of the Thighs; and inferiour parts, to draw the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour downwards, Ligatures or bin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:170219:26"/>the Thigh hard with a ſtring, Cupping glaſſes to be applyed to the Hips and Thighs, and the inferiour parts, both with ſcarification and without.</p>
                  <p>Let the ſick party beware of all ſlimy meat, and hard meat, and from all ſalt, cold binding things, as are hard of digeſtion: omit ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, ſorrow, and melancholineſſe; and alwaies in theſe caſes, begin with the mildeſt Medicines firſt: of which you have ſufficient before directed. And thus far, for the ſuppreſſion or ſtopping of the Terms, we proceed to the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Flux (an evil alſo incident to Women) and the remedies there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Chap. IIII.</hi> Of the immoderate Flux of the Terms.</head>
               <p>HAving hitherto fully declared the Symptomes Cauſes and Cure of that great Feminine infirmity the
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:170219:27"/>ſtopping or obſtruction of the termes' we provide now in order to treat of the immoderate Flux, or overflowing of Womens courſes, which often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times brings to the party afflicted there with many other infirmities, and great weakneſs, and ſickneſs, pains in the back and ſtomack, loſſe of ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite, ill digeſtion, and many other diſeaſes, as Dropſie, Conſumption, and others.</p>
               <p>This infirmity may, and often times is cauſed by ſome fall, blow, thruſt, over-ſtraining, too much exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe, over-heating the body, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by making the blood thin and flux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ible.</p>
               <p>It is alſo cauſed by ſome unnatural, and untimely birth, breaking of a vein, or ſome bruiſings in the womb, ſome vein there being broken, or through ſome weakneſs in the reten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive faculty, and too much ſtrength of the expulſive; too much moyſture and ſlipperineſs in the Matrix.</p>
               <p>Many ſuppoſe the immoderate Flux of the termes, and the continual Iſſue of women to be one and the
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:170219:27"/>ſame diſeaſe; but they are beſides the Cuſſion; for they are 2 ſeveral &amp; diſtinct diſeaſes, as <hi>Galen</hi> plainly teacheth, for in the ſuperfluous Flux of the termes, blood only iſſueth, as it uſeth to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear in the natural monthly purgati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; but only it flowes immoderately; but in the iſſue or Flux of Women, not only blood, but various excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, ſometimes watry, and of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſubſtance, are evacuated.</p>
               <p>The Termes or courſes are ſaid to flow immoderately, after a twofold manner.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>Firſt, when they flow exceſſive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and beyond meaſure in a ſmall time.</item>
                  <item>Secondly, When this evacuation continues many dayes beyond its na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural courſe and time.</item>
               </list>
               <p>And to this purpoſe, writes <hi>Galen,</hi> when he ſaith, Men are wont to call that much rain, or a great rain, which continues a long time, though it fall but ſlowly, and leaſurely; or elſe if it ſuddenly fall upon the earth in great ſhowers.</p>
               <p>If any one ſhall be ſo curious,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:170219:28"/>as to ask what is the proper quantity and meaſure of the menſtrual blood, which nature ought duly to evacuate, <hi>Hippocrates</hi> anſwers them, That in a ſound Woman,<note place="margin">Hip. <hi>1.</hi> Lib. de morb. mulier. Pag. <hi>313.</hi>
                  </note> and one perfect in health, the moderate monethly Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations ought to be about 20. ounces, a very little more or leſſe, if they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed very much that proportion, or are much leſſe, then are the Courſes diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſed, and diſaffected.</p>
               <p>But the certain quantity of the monethly natural purgations, cannot ſo ſtrictly be defined in all bodies, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the difference of the tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rature, the dyet, habit, conſtitution, age and ſtrength of Womens bodies: it muſt neceſſarily be, that ſome muſt have them more copiouſly then o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; but this definition might be taken to be of a Woman in perfect health; but if the Flux of natural pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation be immoderate, the party muſt needs be much afflicted therewith, and thereby incur many other Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes; of ſome whereof mention is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready made, and partly of the cauſes thereof.</p>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:170219:28"/>
               <p>But we deſire to be a little more copious,<note place="margin">Cauſes.</note> in diſcovering the cauſes of this diſtemper, before we proceed to the method of the cure thereof.</p>
               <p>The cauſes of this immoderate Flux,<note place="margin">Gal. <hi>3.</hi> de Sym. Cauſis Cap. <hi>2.5.</hi> Aph. Com. <hi>58.</hi>
                  </note> are diſtinctly and accurately handled by <hi>Galen,</hi> That</p>
               <p>The Termes (as other Fluxes of blood) do flow immoderatly for three cauſes.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>Firſt, By reaſon of the faculty that recludeth the Veſſel containing the blood; as in the Flux of blood at the noſe.</item>
                  <item>The ſecond, Becauſe of the evil affection, and ill diſpoſition of the blood.</item>
                  <item>And the third, By reaſon of ſome vitiouſneſs, or detriment in the Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels themſelves.</item>
               </list>
               <p>The firſt cauſe is, by reaſon of the natural faculties which are foure. The faculty attractive, retentive, alterative, and the faculty expulſive.</p>
               <p>All which faculties perform their operations,<note place="margin">Gal. <hi>1.</hi> de fac. Nat.</note> according to their proper temperatures, as <hi>Galen</hi> largely teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth.</p>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:170219:29"/>
               <p>Therefore they are the cauſe of the menſtrual Fluxes immoderation, when theſe fuculties do not properly, and duly exerciſe their functions and Offices.</p>
               <p>As chiefly, If the retentive facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty be too weak, that it cannot retain the blood ſo much, and ſo long as it ſhould, until its due time: this is a ſpecial cauſe of the ſuperfluous Flux, which many times happens, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of ſome ill diſtemper in the womb or Veſſels, either too much cold, or moyſture, or both.</p>
               <p>In like manner, it comes to paſſe, when the expulſive faculty too power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully ſends forth the blood, in ſuch quantity, and at ſuch times, when by the Lawes of nature it ſhould not; and this alſo chiefly happens, by reaſon of ſome ill diſtempers, either in the Womb or Veſſels, proceeding of too much heat, and dryneſs, or both.</p>
               <p>Another cauſe of the immoderate Flux of the Termes, is the ill diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or corruption of the blood, and that after a twofold manner.</p>
               <p>The firſt, when the blood is ſo viti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:170219:29"/>that it corrodeth and corrupteth the Veſſels wherein it is contained, which is done, when the blood is too thin, hot, or ſharp, and that by reaſon the temperature, or ill dyer, is mixed with ſuperfluity of Flegme, Choler, or Melancholy, which are of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſive to nature, and do provoke her to expel them.</p>
               <p>A ſecond cauſe is ſuperfluity of blood diſtempered,<note place="margin">4 <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod.</hi> 2.</note> ſo that the Veſſels cannot contain it, but it breaks out, and forces a purgation, by reaſon of the abounding acrimonious humor thereof, as <hi>Galen</hi> alſo makes mention. Having now ſpoken of two cauſes of the immoderate Flux of the Termes, we proceed to the third, which is, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the viriouſneſs of the Veſſels, and that conſiſteth in the too much hardneſs, ſoftneſs, or ſmallneſs there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: And happens to come, in youth, in their firſt beginning; and to others afterwards, in progreſs of time. And this happens to come thus to paſſe. Too much ſoftneſs of ſuperfluity of moyſture, hardneſs of too much dry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and ſmallneſs of too much hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:170219:30"/>or want of ſuſtenance.</p>
               <p>If this ſuperfluous Flux proceed of too much blood,<note place="margin">Colour.</note> then the colour of the Termes will be pale and whitiſh, if they come of Choler, then the Flowers will incline to a yellow Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour.</p>
               <p>If Melancholy be the abounding humour, then are the Flowers of a blewiſh, black, or dark colour.</p>
               <p>By which Colours you may judge of the abounding humour, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide a remedy accordingly, to ſtop the exceſſive Flux thereof; for which pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe we now come to preſcribe many, both internal and external meanes.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Firſt, Obſerve theſe Rules.</head>
                  <p>Beware of hot things. If the Body be groſſe, and full of blood and hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours, that nature ſeems to expulſe it this way, ſtop it not ſuddenly, unleſs there be danger of much weakneſs by it; but gently purge and prepare the body firſt.</p>
                  <p>If the Body be very full of blood, you may open the <hi>Baſilica</hi> vein; and
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:170219:30"/>ſeek to reverſe it that way, if it appear to come of Choler; or, if any other peccant humour abounds, purge that humour with proper moderate Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines, mixing aſtringent and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable things amongſt it.</p>
                  <p>Let the Woman abſtain from all hard labour, and all kind of ſlimey, thin, and wateriſh meat.</p>
                  <p>Vomits are good to ſtay the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, and turn their courſe, that they flow not downwards.</p>
                  <p>Inwardly may be given Sirrups, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectuaries, decoctions, Confections, and the like.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>A Sirrup to ſtay the immoderate Flux of the Termes.</head>
                  <p>Take Sirrup of Endive, one ounce; Sirrup of Purſlain, half an ounce; the decoction of Egrimony, and of Plantain 4 Ounces: mix them toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and make them into a Sirrup, and ſo take it as you pleaſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>An Electuary for the ſame.</head>
                  <p>Take conſerve of Roſes 2 Ounces,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:170219:31"/>of water Lillies, one ounce of Pearl prepared, and burnt Harts-horn, each half an ounce: Bole Armonick, Terra Lemnia each half a ſcruple: mix them together with ſyrrup of Plantain, a quantity ſufficient to make it into an Electuary.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>A Bolus for the ſame.</head>
                  <p>Take Conſerce of Roſes, half an ounce; Philonium, or Requies Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholai, two Scruples: Mix them toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and make a Bolus thereof. This is not to be given, but when extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty urges.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Avicenna</hi> amongſt many other Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicaments of this nature, commendeth the uſe of Vinegar, which to ſome may ſeem ſtrange, it being the vulgar opinion, that Vinegar is of a great opening quality.</p>
                  <p>Nevertheleſs, <hi>Galen</hi> agrees with <hi>Avicen,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Gal. <hi>1.</hi> de ſim. med. cap. <hi>18.19.</hi>
                     </note> who writeth of Vinegar, that it is of an aſtringent quality, and doth ſuppreſſe and ſtop fluxes of the blood.</p>
                  <p>Others contradict the ſame, not approving of it in this caſe, as hurtful
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:170219:31"/>to the Womb. And there being ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other Medicines here readily pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed, it may very well be let alone.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>A Powder to ſtay the immoderate Flux of the Terms.</head>
                  <p>Take Species tria ſantali, Diarrhodon Abbatis, each a dram: Coriander, two ſcruples and a half: (Blood-ſtone wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, one dram: Shepherds purſe, two ſcruples: fine Bolus, half a dram: Roſes, Corral, of each half a dram: Cinamon, a quarter of an ounce: make them all into a fine powder, and mix them with Sugar, as much as you pleaſe, and take it in broth, or ſtrewed on meat,</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Another Powder for the ſame.</head>
                  <p>Take fine Bolus, one dram: Terra ſigillata, two ſcruples; Tormentil, half a dram; Shepherds purſe; a ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: Pearl prepared one dram; Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies de gemmis frigidis one dram and a half: Pomgranates, half a ſcruple: Roſes, Saunders, red Coral, of each a
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:170219:32"/>ſcruple: Sugar, three ounces. <hi>Mix</hi> them all together, and make them a fine powder, and give it as the other in broth or ſtewed meat.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>An Electuary for the ſame.</head>
                  <p>Take Conſerve of Roſes, ſix oun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; Conſerve of Burrage, Buglas, Balm, of each an ounce; Bolus pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared, a dram: Pearl prepared, a quarter of an ounce: of Rubies, Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinths, Saphir, each a Scruple; Cina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, a dram; mix theſe together, and make an Electuary thereof.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Another Electuary to ſtay the Flowers.</head>
                  <p>Take Conſerve of Roſes, three ounces: Marmalade, two ounces and half: red Corral, a dram: Bolus pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared, half a dram: Blood-ſtone pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared, two drams; mix them all toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the ſyrup of Myrtles, and make an Electuary thereof, and take it as you pleaſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:170219:32"/>
                  <head>A Confection for the ſame.</head>
                  <p>Take Conſerve of Roſes three oun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; Marmalade, two ounces and a half; Conſerves of Burrage, Buglas, each one ounce; Bolus prepared, a dram and a half: Pearl, two drams and a half: Tormentil, two ſcruples; red Saunders, one dram; mix them all together, and make a Confection thereof, with the Syrup of Myrtles.</p>
                  <p>The Confection of black Cherries, and preſerved Barberries, are alſo very good for this uſe.</p>
                  <p>A toſt of bread ſteeped in red Wine, and Nutmegs in powder, ſtrewed thereon, is very good.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
                  <p>Take Tormentil and Nutmegs, of each a like quantity, Plaintain ſeeds, half as much; beat them all to pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and give it evening and morning, with ſtale beer.</p>
                  <p>Red Corral, taken every day before meales in Plantain water, is alſo very good to ſtay the Flux.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:170219:33"/>
                  <head>For the ſame.</head>
                  <p>Take burnt Harts-horn, and Nettle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeds, of each a like quantity: and beat them to powder, and take thereof a dram at a time in Plantain water, and about a ſpoonful of the juyce of Yar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row.</p>
                  <p>Galingal chewed in the Mouth, is alſo good.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>A Clyſter to ſtay the immoderate Flux of the Terms.</head>
                  <p>Take Fetherfew, Balm, Rue, Scabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, Roſemary flowers, Southern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood, Comin, Bay-berries, Caſſia wood, Caſſia ſiſtula, of each a dram and an half: Dill ſeed, Anniſeed, each a handful and a half: ſhaven Ivory, two handfuls; boyl them altogether by a mild fire in two quarts of water, till half be conſumed, and then ſtrain it out, and take of this Decoction, 12. ounces: oyl of Seſanum; Rue and Pep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, of each half an ounce; Indian Salt, one dram: Diacaſtore; Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:170219:33"/>of Bay-berries and Benedicta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of each three drams; temper them all very well together, and adminiſter it very warm.</p>
                  <p>Thus far of ſuch Medecines as are to be given inwardly; we now pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to external or outward applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, of which there are divers, but all ought to be of an aſtringent ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping quality: ſuch are Peſſaries, Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guents, and Plaiſters, &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>A Peſſary, to ſtop the exceſſive Courſe of the Terms.</head>
                  <p>Take Bauluſtes, bark of Pomgra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nates, Mirtles, each half a dram; mix them with a ſufficient quantity of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, and make thereof a Peſſary, and put it up into the Matrix.</p>
                  <p>There are alſo more liquid Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>decines, which may very commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly be injected with a fit Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment like Clyſters.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:170219:34"/>
                  <head>An Injection to stay the Flux of the Terms.</head>
                  <p>Take Bauluſtes, Pomgranate Pill, Tragant, of each a dram: Comfrey, four drams; make a decoction thereof, and mix it with four drams of the Juyce of Plantane, and make an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection thereof.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>A Peſſary for the ſame.</head>
                  <p>Take juyce of Plantane, juice of Sloes, and juyce of Pimpernel, and make a Peſſary thereof with Cotton.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>A Cataplaſme for the ſame, or a Pultis, which you pleaſe to call it.</head>
                  <p>Take Wormwood, Knot-graſſe, Nights-ſhade, of each a like quantity: pound them together, and ſtrain out the juyce; then temper with it Rye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meal, a ſufficient quantity, to make it into the thickneſs of a Pultis, and lay it all over the Belly from the Navel to the Matrix.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:170219:34"/>
                  <head>A precious ſalve to ſtay the immoderate Flux of Womens Courſes.</head>
                  <p>Take Comin, Carraway, Rueſeed, Ameos, Seſeli and Gallia Moſcata, of each a dram and a half: Roſin, three drams: oyl of Dill, two ounces: oyl Olive, one ounce: Lignum Aloes, Cloves, of each half a dram; melt the Roſin in the oyl, and temper the other things with it, being beaten ſmall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to fine powder, and incorporate them together, by ſtirring until it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a thick ſalve.</p>
                  <p>Herewith anoint the Hips and Reins, it is excellent to ſtop the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluous flux of the Terms: It is alſo good againſt vomiting and perbrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, and to expel wind, being apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the Navel and Stomach.</p>
                  <p>Be ſure to obſerve, whether the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man abound with heat or cold, and frame your Medicines accordingly; if cold be predominant, uſe ſuch things as cauſe heat, and are good to ſtop blood; ſuch are,</p>
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:170219:35"/>
                  <p>Frankincenſe, Maſtick, Cipreſs nuts, Sandaraca, Laudanum, Mirrh, Storax, Annis, and the like.</p>
                  <p>If heat abound, ſuch things are to be prepared as are cold and aſtringent, as cool and bind, and ſuch is the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of theſe following.</p>
                  <p>Camphire, the juyce of Sloes, burnt Ivory, Coriander, Dragons blood, Saunders, Blood-ſtone, fine Bolus, Hypociſtis, the ſeeds of Kneeholm, or Butchers broom, call it which you will; theſe ſeeds and alſo the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coction of the root, are very effectual; if you would know where to find the ſeeds, look into the inſide of the red berries thereof, and there you ſhall be ſure to find them; but not before you have found the hearb, for they grow together, and the Kneeholme hearb is a common companion almoſt with every holly buſh.</p>
                  <p>Theſe are alſo cooling and aſtrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent; Mirtle ſeeds, Galls, Pomgra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nates, flowers called Balauſtes, the ſeeds of Plantane of Melons, Cucum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber gourds, and of Pompeons and the roots of Pimpernel.</p>
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:170219:35"/>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Some are glad to eat what they can get, yet ye muſt as near as ye can avoid what is hurtful.</note>Let the manner of dier, be ſuch as is nouriſhing and breedeth good juyce, and is eaſily digeſted, eſpecially ſuch as thicken the blood, and hinder the fluxibility thereof, as Birds, thoſe eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially of the Mountains, are highly commended, if you can catch them.</p>
                  <p>Let their drink be aſtringent Wine, or, uſe to quench Steel in their drink, or boyl therein the ſeeds, leaves, and roots of Plantane. And thus much of the Flux of the Terms.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Chap. V.</hi> Of the Flux of the Womb, or the Whites in Women.</head>
               <p>WEe have already declared, that the immoderate Flux of the monethly Courſes, and the Flux of the Womb, or the white Menſtrue,<note place="margin">Gal. 6. loc. affe. ad finem.</note> are two ſeveral Diſeaſes, as <hi>Galen</hi> plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly teacheth.</p>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:170219:36"/>
               <p>We proceed now to ſpeak of the Whites, or white Flux in women, called by the Phyſicians,<note place="margin">Gal. lib. <hi>3</hi> de ſym. cauſ. cap. <hi>4.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Menſtrua al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ba &amp; profluvium uteri,</hi> as <hi>Galen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Diſeaſe hath great affinity with the <hi>Gonorrhea,</hi> or the involunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry iſſue of natural ſeed, called the run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Reins.</p>
               <p>And this Flux alſo proceeds from two Cauſes, either too much cold, or unatural heat; and the differences of this Iſſue are very many, as may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear by the colour of the Excrements which flow or iſſue, which are ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times red, ſometimes pale, ſometimes yellow, ſometimes black, ſometimes white, and ſometimes green, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times thick, and ſometimes watery; from Species may be gathered the qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of the peccant humour, as for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample; If the Flux be of a red colour, it declares, that the iſſue flowes from the blood, and is thereby cauſed; If it be pale or yellow, it denotes, black Choler is the cauſe thereof; if white, it proceeds from flegm; if it be thin and watery, ſuperfluous humours do abound in the Body.</p>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:170219:36"/>
               <p>But above all things, be ſure to know whether this Flux, be a Gonorrhea, that is an involuntary iſſue of the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Sperm, which is the running of the Reins, the ſelf ſame Diſeaſe being alſo incident to men, as well as wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and proceedeth in both Sexes, from one and the ſame cauſe, and that women as well as men do labour un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſame Symptom; But is general among women to call this diſeaſe the Whites; though it be a Gonorrhea, or the running of the Reins, under which infirmitie many do a long time labour to the great waſting and Conſumption of their Bodies; the principal cauſe thereof proceeding either from immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate, exceſſive, or unlawful Venery.</p>
               <p>It is generally agreed, that the law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and proper cauſe of the Whites, is too much ſuperfluity of Excrements; but as touching the place and manner, where and how theſe Excrements are ingendered, Authors diſagree.</p>
               <p>Some ſay, the cauſe is a daily beget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of corrupt humours in the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal parts.</p>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:170219:37"/>
               <p>Others, that it proceeds only from the Womb, and Spermatick Veſſels.</p>
               <p>Others, that it flows only from the Reins, the Womb being not at all af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted thereby.</p>
               <p>But <hi>Galen</hi> plainly demonſtrates,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>6.</hi> de locis affect. loc. <hi>5.</hi>
                  </note> that the whole Body is affected with this Iſſue, although it purge through the Womb, and evacuate it ſelf from the Reins; and that this Diſeaſe is moſt incident to flegmatick and weak women.</p>
               <p>It remaineth before we come to ſpeak of the method of the cure of this infirmity, that diligence be uſed (as we ſaid before) to find out whether it proceed from a Gonorrhea, that is, a Running of the Reins, or Flux of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane ſeed, or not: the knowledge whereof muſt be rather conjectural, then to be demonſtrated from any certain ſign, other then the Patients own relation.</p>
               <p>But the flowing of the Seed, is more thick, and floweth in leſſe quantity, and is not ſo corrupt, and of a whiter colour.</p>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:170219:37"/>
               <p>On the contrary, the other Excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are more thin, do flow more abundantly, are more filthy and putri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, and are not alwayes of the ſame colour.</p>
               <p>But to proceed to the manner of the Cure of this Diſeaſe: Reſpect in the firſt place is to be had to the purging and cleanſing of the whole Body; and if the Diſeaſe be a Gonor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thea, and proceed of heat unlawfully, or however gotten; the Body muſt firſt be purged with Medicines appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priate to the Reins, before you at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt in any wiſe to ſtop the ſame; for which, this following is very good.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>An Electuary to purge the Reins.</head>
                  <p>Take Caſſia newly extracted, one ounce; Rheubarb in powder, one dram: mix them together with ſyrup of white water Lillies, a ſufficient quantity to make it into an Electuary; put this into a penny pot of White-wine, or a little poſſet drink, which comes firſt to hand; ſtir it well toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:170219:38"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="61" facs="tcp:170219:38"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="64" facs="tcp:170219:39"/>till it be all diſſolved in the drink, and ſo take it in the morning faſting, and go about your buſineſs (if you have any thing to do) about two hours after, take ſome broth or poſſet drink.</p>
                  <p>This Medecine you may take twice or thrice, as you ſee occaſion, reſting alwaies a day between.</p>
                  <p>Afterwards, you may take every other day, a dram of Trochis de Carabe in Plantane water.</p>
                  <p>You may alſo give the Patient, every ſecond or third day, a dram of the filings of Ivory in Plantane water; it is very good.</p>
                  <p>Sweating is alſo much commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in this caſe, which may be thus done.</p>
                  <p>Take Barley water, three ounces; ſtrong Wine, two ounces: give it the Patient very warm, and ſo let her ſweat.</p>
                  <p>Afterwards, prepare a Clyſter in this manner.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="65" facs="tcp:170219:39"/>
                  <head>A Clyster for the Whites, through heat, or running of the Reyns.</head>
                  <p>Take Beets, Violet-leaves, and Night-ſhade, of each one handful, ſeeth them well together, and take 12 Ounces of the decoction, or boyled liquor; which you pleaſe to call it, and to it add, Sugar 1 Ounce and a half, Yolks of Eggs, Oyl of Water-Lillies, Oyl of Roſes, of each 2 Ounces, Salt a dram and a half: give this Clyſter in the afternoon, a little before meat.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>A Confection for the ſame.</head>
                  <p>Take Comfrey-roots 3 Ounces, Pom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peon-ſeed, Water-Lillies, of each a dram, Juyce of Liquorice 2 ſcruples, Coral prepared, Bolus, Mirtle-ſeed, Roſes of each 10 grains, Gun Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganth half a dram, Syrup, the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phrey Roots; cleave and ſlice them ſmall, and ſeeth them in Red Wine, until they be ſo tender, that you may beat them to grout or pap, then pill the Pompeon-ſeeds, and beat them
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:170219:40"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="65" facs="tcp:170219:40"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="66" facs="tcp:170219:41"/>together with the other things to fine Powder; then incorporate them with the pap or grout, made of Camphrey-Roots; and then put to them Sirrup of Citron Pills, and of Orenges, as much as you pleaſe, and then boyl them together to a Confection. And take every morning a ſpoonful there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, before break-faſt.</p>
                  <p>Conſerves of Roſes, and Marma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lade, are exceeding good for this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, either to be taken alone, or mixt together, with prepared Bolus, and take thereof a dram at a time.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>An excellent Sirrup for the ſame.</head>
                  <p>Take the Seeds of Purſlain, Lettice, and Water-Lillies, of each an Ounce, prepared Coriander, Water Lilly-Roots, Dandelion, Night-ſhade, of each half an Ounce, Camphire half a dram, Dates chopt ſmall 2 Ounces, Rue-Seeds, Mountain Mints, parched Gomin, of each 1 dram. Steep the Dates 8 dayes in Vinegar, then ſeeth them together in 2 quarts of water, till half be waſted, ſtrain it, and put to
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:170219:41"/>it 12 Ounces of the juyce of Quinces, Sugar 36 Ounces, and boyl them all together to a Sirrup, and ſo clarifie them.</p>
                  <p>Of this Sirrup, take 2 Ounces, with 3 Ounces of Plantain water, or Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlain-water: This is an excellent pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Sirrup for this purpoſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Drinks and Waters good for this Diſeaſe.</head>
                  <p>Take Comphrey Roots, and boyl them in water, and drink thereof 3. of 4. Ounces at a time with Sugar.</p>
                  <p>Alſo water wherein the filings of Steel have been ſteeped, and then Myrtle-ſeeds boyled therein, is very good to drink for the ſame:</p>
                  <p>Simple waters good for this infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, are the waters of Plantain, Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel, Purſlain, and Cithorie.</p>
                  <p>The decoction of Mallows, and the Roots of Hollyhockles, is alſo very good to drink for this Diſeaſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="68" facs="tcp:170219:42"/>
                  <head>An Oyntment for the ſame, called, Unguentum ſandalinum.</head>
                  <p>Take red Sanders 2 drams and a half, yellow Sanders 1 dram and a half, Roſes 3 drams, Fine Bolus a quarter of an Ounce, burnt Ivory a dram, Camphire half a dram, white Wax an Ounce, Oyl of Roſes 3 Oun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. Melt the Wax firſt amongſt the Oyl, then temper the other things a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them, and make them into an Oyntment.</p>
                  <p>This Oyntment is not only good to annoint the ſecret parts for this Diſeaſe, but alſo to cool the inflam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations of the Kidnies, Liver, and Stomack, and all other parts, being annointed with it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>A Salve for the ſame Diſeaſe.</head>
                  <p>Take Oyl of Roſes, Oyl of Mirtles, Maſtick, of each half a dram, ſhaven Ivory a ſcruple, Camphire 2 grains, pound that which is to be powned, and with a little Wax, make them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:170219:42"/>a Salve; with this annoint the Reins and Kidnies, it is excellent good for the whites.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Another Confection, very good for the ſame.</head>
                  <p>Take ripe Black berries, or bramble berries, which you will call them, and boyl them unto a Confection, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with Honey or Sugar; and take there of every day as much as you pleaſe: this you may make, when the Black-berries be ripe, and keep it in a readineſs by you all the year; it is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo good for any ſoreneſs, or ſwelling in the throat, and for inflammations in the mouth.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>A Powder alſo excellent for the ſame.</head>
                  <p>Take the young buds of the Black<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berry Buſh, and the Berries thereof dryed; pound them, and drink a dram thereof twice a day in red wine.</p>
                  <p>You may gather the green buds, when the branches firſt ſpring; and keep them dry by you, and gather the
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:170219:43"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="69" facs="tcp:170219:43"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="70" facs="tcp:170219:44"/>Berries too when they be ripe (if you be not afraid to prick your fingers) &amp; keep them dry by you; and when you have occaſion, beat them to powder, and take them in red Wine, as before is directed.</p>
                  <p>You that will not regard this Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine, becauſe it is too cheap, may let it alone for them that will; there be Medicines enough to be had, to fit your turns, if you think the vertue conſiſts in their dearneſs; and I do not deſire to hinder thoſe that can furniſh you with them; but thoſe that will make uſe of this, will finde it worthy their acceptance.</p>
                  <p>But if in caſe this Diſeaſe iſſue from ſome cold cauſe, it will not be then amiſs to uſe this Medicine follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>For the Whites.</head>
                  <p>Take the Seeds of Arch Angel, or dead Nettles in powder, about a dram at a time in red Wine.</p>
                  <p>Confected Aniſeeds is alſo very good for this Diſeaſe, and not impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:170219:44"/>may be given in either caſe, this following.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Another for the ſame, or Reds.</head>
                  <p>Take 4 ſpoonfuls of red Roſe-wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, a new-laid Egge, a peny worth of white Sugar Candy in powder, and a Nutmeg grated, incorporate all theſe, and beat them well together, and drink it laſt at night going to bed.</p>
                  <p>You may alſo if the Iſſue be ſharp, ſo as to cauſe pain and ſoreneſs, uſe an Injection or Peſſary.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>A Peſſary for the whites in Women.</head>
                  <p>Take ſome Whites of Eggs, and beat them well in red Roſe-water, and make it into a Peſſary, with ſome Cot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten or linnen Cloaths wet in it, and ſo put it up into the Matrix, alwayes remembring to tie a ſtring to it, to pull it out again, when you pleaſe.</p>
                  <p>If the Whites flow from the abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of ſuperfluous humours, it will not be unneceſſary to endeavour to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vacuate the ſame through the skin, by
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:170219:45"/>uſing often frictions or rubbing of the whole body; firſt gently, and then more hard, by which means the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours may be purged through the skin.</p>
                  <p>And to uſe unctions is alſo very good, if neceſſity urge, of Oyl of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>momile, of ſweet Almonds, or the like; ſo that of all ſorts of reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies you have here your choyce, and therefore we ſhall proceed to another Chapter.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Chap. VI.</hi> Of the fits of the Mother, or ſuffo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, or drawing up of the Matrix.</head>
               <p>MAny Women ſorely labour un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der this Diſeaſe, it hath great af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finity with the Syncope paſſion, and the Diſeaſe called Epilepſia, or the Falling Sickneſs; and that becauſe of the Sympathy, that is, between the heart and the brain, and the Matrix.</p>
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:170219:45"/>
               <p>This happens to Women, through ſeveral cauſes.</p>
               <p>Oftentimes when there is an ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, or ſtoppage of the Termes, which do burthen the Brain and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trix with bad humors.</p>
               <p>Sometimes by reaſon of the reten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their natural Seed, as in Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows, and old Maids; for this reten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion cauſeth wind to aſcend, and ill vapors from the Matrix, to the Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phragma or Midrif, and there ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth the paſſage of the breath: it of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten therefore troubleth ſuch as have been uſed to have carnal Copulation, and afterwards are conſtrained to want it; and therefore, ſaith <hi>Galen,</hi> it doth moſt frequently trouble Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows.</p>
               <p>Likewiſe the overmuch retention of the Seed, cauſeth it to putrifie, and ſend up ill vapours to the head, cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing many troubleſome accidents, as drouſineſs, dulneſs, giddineſs, &amp; pains in the head; ſometimes madneſs it ſelf, ſhortneſs of breath, and panting of the heart.</p>
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:170219:46"/>
               <p>The Complexion alters into a ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy colour, ſwarthy or yellow, pale, and ſometimes redneſs of the face or eyes.</p>
               <p>When they are thus taken with this evil diſtemper; they begin to gnaſh their teeth, and immediately loſe their ſpeech, by reaſon their breath is ſtopt; and ſometimes it is ſo violent, that neither breath, nor pulſe, nor life, can be diſcerned; but lie as if they were dead, which is the worſt condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all; for the breath cannot be retained, but death will enſue; for breath is the life of the body, without which no Creature can live.</p>
               <p>This accident alſo happens through ſome ſudden fright, and ſome ſorrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful newes or ſad accident ſuddenly happening; or ſome ſorrow or grief, whereby melancholy prevails, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vercomes the body.</p>
               <p>It may likewiſe be cauſed, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of ſome ſtrong and violent Cold, which may ſo draw the breath and pulſe inwardly, that no feeling, or ſenſe thereof outwardly appears; but
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:170219:46"/>this caſe is not ſo dangerous as the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
               <p>But to proceed to Remedies, when this Diſeaſe commeth ſuddenly, ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily caſt cold water on her face, and give her cold water to drink.</p>
               <p>Let another Woman dip her finger in ſome ſweet ſmelling odoriferous Oyl, as Oyl of Lillies, of Cloves, or of ſweet Almonds mixed together, and gently rub the neck of the womb and Matrix, and that will draw the Matrix downwards;</p>
               <p>If it be a married Woman, her Husband may give her a preſent re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy, which leſt it offend the Maids <hi>pudoris gratia,</hi> I leave it in my Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thours own Language.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Si maritus ungat penem ſuum cum o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leo gariophillorum admixto parum olei. Amygdal: dulc: ad Caliditatem pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oris temperandum, &amp; Cum uxore coeat; Matrix ſubito deſcendet,</hi> it is a ſpeedy Remedy.</p>
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:170219:47"/>
               <p>You muſt have a care to keep away all ſweet and pleaſant things from the Patients noſe, and apply ſtinking things thereunto; and on the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, anoyne, foment, and fume the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trix with ſweet Aromatick things.</p>
               <p>For the Matrix is drawn and at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted to ſweet things, and naturally flies from ſtinking ſmells: therefore as in the aſcention, or riſing of the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, you are to uſe ſtinking things to the noſe, and ſweet to the Womb; ſo contrariwiſe, in the falling down, or diſcention of the Mother, you are to apply ſweet perfumes to the Noſe, and ſtinking to the Matrix: to the end, the ſame may thereby be drawn up again into its due place.</p>
               <p>For this Diſeaſe, it is good to hold to the Noſe, <hi>Aſſa foetida, galbanum,</hi> old Woollen Clouts, or Shooes burnt, Hair, or Feathers, or ſuch ſtinking things that may be gotten ſpeedily.</p>
               <p>And apply ſweet odoriferous things to the Matrix beneath; for which pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe this Powder following is very good.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="77" facs="tcp:170219:47"/>
                  <head>A Powder to be uſed in the nature of a Peſſary, againſt the ſuffocation of the Matrix, or fits of the Mother.</head>
                  <p>Take red Storax, Lignum Aloes, Cloves, of each a dram, Musk, Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of each half a dram: Make them altogether into a Powder, and then bind it up in a Cloth, in the form of a Peſſary, and put it up into the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trix.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
                  <p>Take an Ounce of Oyl of Lillies, Musk, Saffron, of each 3 grains; bruiſe all well together, and make a Peſſary thereof with Wooll, or Cotton, and put it up into the place.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>A Fumigation for this Diſeaſe.</head>
                  <p>Take Gallia Moſcata, Caſſia wood, Cynamon, Time, of each a like quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity; mix theſe together, and make a perfume thereof, and let the ſmoke be
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:170219:48"/>received up into the Matrix, through a tumel for that purpoſe.</p>
                  <p>If the Patient be a Maid, a Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band is the beſt Medicine, if ſhe can get one; but in caſe that cannot be, then let her abſtain from ſtrong Wines, and fleſh meat, and all ſuch things as increaſe natural ſperme.</p>
                  <p>And uſe letting blood, ſuch meats and drinks as are cooling; and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the reſt, this Confection fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing is very good.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>A Confection againſt the fits of the Mother.</head>
                  <p>Take Polipody Roots 6 Ounces, Sene, Violets, Prunes, Sebaſtins, Dates, Currans, of each an Ounce and a half, ſeeth theſe altogether in two quarts of water, till half be conſumed away, then ſtrain it out hard, and infuſe in the decoction, while it is hot, 6. Oun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the Seeds of Fleawort, till the Muſcilage be drawn out of them, then put to this decoction 24 Ounces of fine Sugar, and take thereof, once in 2 or 3 dayes, and faſt after it 6 hours.</p>
                  <pb n="79" facs="tcp:170219:48"/>
                  <p>Take ſilver Mountain, Madder Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyroyal, the innermoſt rinds of Caſſia Pipes, Pomegranat Kernels, Piony Roots, Calamy, of each 3 drams, Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus and Spica Indie, of each, half a dram: make all theſe together into Pills, with the juyce of Mugwort; of theſe ſhe may take a dram every day before Supper, if ſhe take not the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection the ſame day.</p>
                  <p>It is alſo good for this Diſeaſe, to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen the Saphea vein in the foot, and afterwards give the Patient a dtam of the Powder of Betony, in Featherfew-water. It is alſo good to anoint the Belly with the Oyl of Maſtick: and ſo much for this affliction of the ſuffoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or aſcention of the Matrix; we come next to ſpeak of the diſcention, or falling down of the ſame.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Chap. VII.</hi> Of the falling down of the Womb.</head>
               <p>This is another great evil, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with many poor Women labour, and
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:170219:49"/>is of no ſmall conſequence and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger; for as in ſome caſes, and for ſome cauſes, the Matrix in ſome Women is drawn up and aſcendeth out of its due place; ſo on the contrary, it ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times deſcends downwards, out of the Body.</p>
               <p>This accident is cauſed ſometimes by hard labour, and heavy births falls, bruiſes, too much aſtringency in the body, taking great cold, violent ſnee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, overmuch ſtirring, and the like.</p>
               <p>It may likewiſe be cauſed by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of ill humours, predominant in the Body, which fall down to the Womb, forcing it out of its natural place; and many times brings with it the Palſie and Falling Sickneſs: as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo Ulcers and Impoſthumes in the Womb.</p>
               <p>If this Diſeaſe happen by means of any outward accident, the Patient her ſelf can beſt diſcover the cauſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</p>
               <p>If it come from ſome inward cauſe, then reſpect is to be had to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of the party, whether ſhe be lean or fat, moyſtor dry, and to the
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:170219:49"/>Symptomes the diſeaſe, which cauſeth pain in the lower part of the Back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bone, and alſo about the ſecret parts; ſometimes an Ague with it, the Urine ſtaies, and the Body is aſtringent.</p>
               <p>If the paſſage of the neck of the Womb bee ſmooth and open, then it is not moved downwards; but if it be ſtopped, then be ſure it is deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, although it appear not out of the Body; and if it do continue diſplaced any long time, it will be very difficult, if not impoſſible to reduce the ſame to its natural place again.</p>
               <p>Now to ſeek Remedies for this Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſe, you muſt, inſtead of applying ſweet things to the Matrix, as you were directted in the aſcenſion of the Matrix, or the fits of the Mother, to draw it down, you muſt now apply ſtinking things to the Matrix, and ſweet ſmells to the Noſe, to draw it up againe.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>A Fume for the falling down of the womb.</head>
                  <p>Take Tormentil, Biſtort, juyce of Sloes,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:170219:50"/>of each 3 drams: Pomgranate pills, the bloſſoms thereof, of each a quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of an ounce; Aſſa foetida, an ounce; Maſtick, Frankincenſe, Galbanum, of each 2 drams and a half: Cypreſs Nuts, Galls, Mirtle ſeed, of each five drams: ſtamp &amp; mix all theſe together, &amp; ſtrew thereof upon a red hot brick, &amp; let the patient receive the fume thereof be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath.</p>
                  <p>Let it not come at her Noſe, but in the mean time, let her ſmell to Musk, Amber, Violets, and ſuch ſweet ſmells which draw up the Mother, and cauſe it to aſcend again.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
                  <p>Take a ſtinking rotten addle Egg, that a Hen hath ſat on, and dip Cot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton in it, and lay it upon the neck of the Matrix, it cauſeth it to aſcend again.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>A Fume for the ſame by a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coction.</head>
                  <p>Take Camomile, Marjoram, Carra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, of each one handful; Linſeed,
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:170219:50"/>one handful and a half: boyl theſe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together in water, and receive the Fume thereof into the Matrix.</p>
                  <p>The vapour of Houſleek bruiſed and laid on a hot brick, is good for the ſame, if there be heat, or inflamma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the Matrix.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>A Fomentation for the ſame.</head>
                  <p>Take Roſes, three ounces: Mirtle ſeed, Violet leaves, Marigolds, Fether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>few, of each one handful: Aſſa feetida, five drachms: bruiſe them together, and tie them up in a bag, and ſeeth them in red Wine, and lay it upon the place after the vapour is received.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>An Oyntment for the falling down of the VVomb.</head>
                  <p>Take the Ointment of Hollyhocks, which is called at the Apothecaries unguent de Althea: mix therewith ſome marrow of an Ox, or other beaſt, the greaſe of a Hen or Capon, and ſome oyl, and herewith annoint the neck of the Matrix, and all the
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:170219:51"/>parts about it, when you go to bed; you may alſo make a plaiſter hereof, and apply it all night as before.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Another Ointment for the ſame.</head>
                  <p>Take oyl of Myrtles, of Lillies, of Maſtick, of each two ounces and an half; Aſſa foetida, Biſtorta, Tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til, of each three drams; melt the Gums, and then pound them altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and make an ointment thereof; and with this annoint the Kidnies, and lower parts of the Body.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>A Peſſary for the ſame.</head>
                  <p>Take Aſſa foetida, one ounce: Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick, Frankinſenſe, Myrtle ſeed, Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingale, Cypreſs nuts, of each a dram; beat them together very ſmall, and mix it with the oyl of Mirtles, and make a Peſſary thereof, and put it up into the Matrix.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="85" facs="tcp:170219:51"/>
                  <head>A Plaiſter for the deſcenſion of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trix, to keep it from going any further out of the Body.</head>
                  <p>Take Rozen, two ounces: Frankin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe, Maſtick, Cypres gum, of each half an ounce: mix and melt them all together, and put to it ſome oyl of Maſtick, ſo make it into a Plaiſter, and apply it to the privities, and wear it thereon.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Another Plaister for the ſame.</head>
                  <p>Take Maſtick, one ounce; Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kincenſe, half a dram; Cypreſs nuts, Galls, Mirtle ſeeds, of each one dram; Pomgranate pills, the bloſſoms there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, Turpentine, of each one quarter of an ounce: pound all that is to be pounded, and mix them all together, with turpentine and oyl of Maſtick, enough to make it into a plaiſter, and ſpread it on a cloth, to cover from the Navel to the privities, and there wear it alwaies.</p>
                  <pb n="86" facs="tcp:170219:52"/>
                  <p>For the deſcention of the Matrix, it is alſo good to take Date ſtones, and beat them to powder, and ſtrew there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of on the place.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>A Bath for the falling down of the Matrix.</head>
                  <p>Take Oken buds, Medlar leaves, Service leaves, Cypreſs leaves, topps of Ladies thiſtles, each one handfull: Sprigs of Mirtle, Valerian, wild Mints, of each two handfuls; bruiſe or chop them all ſmall; then put them in a bag, and boyl it well in water and fit thereon, in a Bath up to the Navel a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout an hour.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>For pain in the Matrix, through wind.</head>
                  <p>Take Turbith, four ſcruples: Gin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, one ſcruple: give it in Mug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wort water, or in the Decoction of Mugwort.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="87" facs="tcp:170219:52"/>
                  <head>For the ſame, and to prevent Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carriages.</head>
                  <p>Take Carraway ſeed, one dram: Ameos, Ginger, Beaver cod, of each one ſcruple: ſteep the Carraway ſeed in Vinegar, and dry it again, and beat it to powder; then mix it with the reſt, and give a dram thereof in Wine, every morning for certain dayes toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>For the ſame.</head>
                  <p>Annoint the Belly with oyl of Lil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, and oyl of Wall flowers.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>For an Impoſtume in the Maetrix, a Peſſary.</head>
                  <p>Take Wax, oyl of Violets, of each half an ounce: melt them together, and then put to it juyce of Plantane, Nightſhade, of each an ounce: Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phire, half a dram: mix them all well together, and dip a tent of Cotton in it, and put it up into the Matrix.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="88" facs="tcp:170219:53"/>
                  <head>An Injection to cleanſe the Matrix.</head>
                  <p>Take Galls, Lentils, Pomgranate flowers, Kneeholm ſeeds, Roſes, Saun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, of each a like quantity: boyl them all together in water, and ſtrain it, and inject the decoction into the Matrix with a Syringe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>For the ſame.</head>
                  <p>Take Hyſop, Wormwood, and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney of Roſes, and ſeeth the ſame in white Wine and milk, and inject the decoction thereof.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>A Bath to incarnate the fleſh in the Matrix, after it is clean ſed from all uncleanneſſe.</head>
                  <p>Take Centory, ſix ounces; Ireos, Comphrey, Caſſia roots, Egrimony, of each three handfuls: Sarcocolla, Gum dragon, Dragons blood, Mum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my Hypociſtis, Frankincenſe, of each one dram: boyl them all together in a ſufficient quantity of water, till half
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:170219:53"/>be conſumed,; and then, put to it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe of Iron prepared, an ounce and a quartet: then boil it a little longer, and uſe this for a Bath.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Another for the ſame uſe.</head>
                  <p>Take Mallows, Violet leaves, Meli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lot, Plantaine, Lentils, Fenegreeke, Colewort buds, of each three hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulls: boyl them all in water unto the half, and make a Bath of it, as of the former.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>A Peſſary, to mollifie the hardneſs and pain between the Navel and the Matrix.</head>
                  <p>Take Ducks greaſe, marrow of Harts bones, or Oxes, marrow if you cannot get the other, Neats feet oyl, Bdeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, yolks of roſted Eggs, of each a like quantity; Saffron, two drams: diſſolve them together in Wine, and temper therewith oyl of Lillies; then dip a tent of linnen or Cotton therein, and put it up into the place; uſe it often, this will aſſwage the pain, and take it away.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="90" facs="tcp:170219:54"/>
                  <head>For Cankers, and Ulcers of the Womb, a purging Potion.</head>
                  <p>Take Benedicta laxativa, half an ounce; Agarins one ſcruple: Ginger, Grains, one ſcruple; juyce of Fetherfew, two ounces and a half: mix them well together, and give it the Patient two mornings together, and then let let her govern her ſelf, as after purging.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Another Potion for the ſame, to be uſed many dayes together to cleanſe the Matrix.</head>
                  <p>Take Oxymel of Squils, half an ounce: <hi>Syrupus de Byſantijs,</hi> Syrup of Vinegar, of each three quarters of an ounce; Lovage water, Egremony wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, of each an ounce: Cicory water, 2 ounces; Let the Patient drink this in the morning early, and ſleep upon it, &amp; faſt four hours after it; uſe it many daies together, till the Urine become of a good colour, and appear clean.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="91" facs="tcp:170219:54"/>
                  <head>A Peſſary for Ulcers in the Womb.</head>
                  <p>Take oyl of Fetherfew flowers, Saf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fron, of each half an ounce: oyl of Wall-flowers, two ounces: Sarcolla, Mittha, Opopanacum, of each a dram; Turpentine, three quarters of an ounce; Musk, one graine; White wax, one ounce: boyl them all toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in four ounces of the juyce of Smallage, till all the juyce be conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med; then annoint a Peſſary of Cot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton therewith, and put it up into the grieved place, and refreſh it often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times.</p>
                  <p>Cleanſe the Body inwardly with Honey water, and make afterwards this Peſſary following, renewing it four or five times a day.</p>
                  <p>Take Smallage, Fetherfew, Mug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wort: ſtamp them together, and make a Peſſary thereof, and annoint it with <hi>Hierapicra.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Take alſo the juyce of the aforeſaid herbs, and wet a cloth therewith, and lay it on the Back and Hips, and low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er parts of the Back bones.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="92" facs="tcp:170219:55"/>
                  <head>An Injection for Ulcers in the Womb.</head>
                  <p>Take Egrimony, and ſeeth it in Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley water: and mix with it clarified Honey, or Honey of Roſes, and ſo uſe it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Another more ſtrong for the ſame.</head>
                  <p>Take Wine, ſix ounces: burnt Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum, Verdigreaſe, of each half a dram; temper them together, and let them ſtand infuſed in the Wine five hours, and then inject it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Another to dry the Ulcers.</head>
                  <p>Take Galls, Pomgranate pills, Pom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>granate flowers, Allom, Egrimony, of each a like quantity: ſeeth them all together, and ſtrain out the decoction, and inject it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>For a Vein broken in the Ulcer.</head>
                  <p>If there be any Vein broken in the Ulcer, then mix ſome of theſe things
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:170219:55"/>with the former decoction, as Dragon blood, Mirrh, Frankincenſe, fine Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus, Saffron, Hartwort, Roſe water or Plantane water.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>A Bath for the Reins, very good for Ul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers or Cankers therein.</head>
                  <p>Take Yarrow roots, Valerian roots, Smallage roots, of each four handfuls; Mirrh, Oppopannacum, of each one quarter of an ounce: boyl them alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in a ſufficient quantity of fair water until a good part thereof be conſumed, then let the Patient ſit therein up to the Navel.</p>
                  <p>Let the Patient in this Diſeaſe, uſe ſuch meats and drinks as cleanſe the Body, and make good blood, beware of fiſh, and ſuch moiſt meats, and abſtain from much motion of the Body.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="94" facs="tcp:170219:56"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Chap. VIII.</hi> Of natural Conceptions.</head>
               <p>HAving thus far treated of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſes, accidents and infirmities incident to the Menſtrue, and genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive parts of Women; we proceed to diſcourſe of thoſe things which per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain to the Conception and Birth of man; in which thing the conſervation and continuance of all mankind con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts.</p>
               <p>That to the generation of every man there is a neceſſity of a diſtinction of both ſexes Male and Female; and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo of Conjunction of them both, we have already declared.</p>
               <p>But in what manner this admirable operation of nature is effected, and brought to perfection, <hi>Galen</hi> declareth; who ſaith,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gal.</hi> 1. <hi>ſem.</hi> 4.</note> That in time of Copulation of the Male and Female, the Seed of the Male, is attracted into the Womb of the Female, and is extended, and dilated through all the parts thereof; and is there, by the natural heat, and
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:170219:56"/>moiſture of the Womb, Coagulated into a maſſy ſubſtance, before any of the Members be formed, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards nature, as with an inſtrument forms and faſhions the Veins, Arte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, Bones and other Members bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching them all over the body, &amp; then ſafely wrappeth them all up together in a Coat, preſerving them to the time of the perfect Birth, if no miſchance, or accident intervene to the hinderance thereof; which muſt be diligently en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to prevent. And to further the Conception for the procreation ſake of mankind, take theſe directions.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>A Confection, to cauſe fruitfulneſſe in Man or Woman.</head>
                  <p>Take Rapes, Ivory ſhaven, Aſhkeys, Seſely, Behen red and white, of each one dram; Cinamon, Doronicum, Mace Cloves; Galingale, long Pepper, Roſemary flowers, Balſom wood, Blatiis Byzantiae Marjoram gentle, Penny-royal, of each two ſcruples; Balm, Buglas, Citron pieces, of each one ſcruple, Spica Indiae, Amber, Pearles, of each half ſcruple; Sugar a
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:170219:57"/>pound: decoct the Sugar in Malmſey, and the other things; and make them into a Confection, uſe of it a little at a time.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>A Powder for the ſame, to be ſtrewed on meat.</head>
                  <p>Take Nurmegs, Cubebbes, Ginger, of each half a dram; long Pepper, Maſtick, Cinamon, red Behen; white Behen, of each a Scruple: mix them all together, and make them into fine powder, and ſtrew of it a little upon the parties meat.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Another Confection for the ſame.</head>
                  <p>Take Honey; three ounces: Linſeed, Grains, Ivory ſhaven, of each one ounce: Borrage three ounces; Sugar, 24 ounces: Musk, Amber, of each half a ſcruple: Cinamon, two grains: Cloves, Mace, of each one graine; clarifie the Honey, then incorporate the other things with it, to make a Confection thereof, and take of it as you pleaſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="97" facs="tcp:170219:57"/>
                  <head>A Porionto further Conception in a Woman.</head>
                  <p>Take Wormwood, Mugwort, of each a handful. Boyl them together in a quart of Goats milk, till almoſt half be waſted, and let the Woman drink thereof firſt and laſt, every morning and evening a good draught.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>A Bath for the ſame.</head>
                  <p>Take Penyroyal, Mugwort, Rue, of each a handful: Put them into a Bag, and boyl them in Rain-water, a ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient quantity to make a Bath, boyl it well, &amp; bathe therein twice a day, and renew the Bath every third day, uſe this for a good ſpace.</p>
                  <p>You muſt underſtand, as I ſaid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that without the mutual con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juction of male and female, the natural reception and coagulation of both their Seeds in the Field of gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration the Womb, there can be no natural conception, and ſo conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently no birth; ſo that if the impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diment
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:170219:58"/>lie in either of the Veſſels re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving, or inſtruments giving, then theſe Medicines preſcribed, do not work their effect till the obſtructive cauſes be removed, and of them you ſhall be ſufficiently directed, in the ſubſequent Chapter of barrenneſs, and the cauſes thereof; but if the Womb be clean, and the Maſculine Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment proportioned thereunto, ſo that the defect lie in ſome debility of nature, let both parties make uſe of this Confection following; and take of it in the mornings faſting, and they ſhall ſeldom fail of their deſires.</p>
                  <p>But take notice by the way, I do not preſcribe this to Maids, nor Batche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lors, they have no uſe for it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>A Confection to further fruitfulneſs in Men, and Conception in Women.</head>
                  <p>Take a Bores Stones, Stags Piſſel ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven ſmall, I ounce, (Bulls Piſſel, if you cannot get the other, will do as well) Sparrows Brains, 50. or 60. yellow Rape, Eringo Root, and Satyrion con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected,
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:170219:58"/>Ivory ſhaven, of each 3 Oun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and a half; Cynamon, Dates, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, Nut Kernels, of each 2 Ounces; Long Pepper, Ginger, Roſemary Flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, of each half an Ounce; Seſeli 1 dram, Nettle-ſeed, Cloves, Safron, Mace, Galingale, Cypreſs Roots, Nut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>megs, Caſſia wood, Cucubes, Doro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicum, Field Mints, Peny Royal, Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca Indiae, Musk, Amber of each one dram. Make all theſe into a Confecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, with 4 pounds &amp; an half of white Sugar, refined in Mint-water, and take of it as before is directed; and if you cannot eaſily get all the things, yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe not the Medicine, but make it with as many as you can come by.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Chap. IX.</hi> Of Barrenneſs.</head>
               <p>IT is granted amongſt all men, that the Generation of man-kind, and alſo of all other Creatures, is the
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:170219:59"/>moſt perfect work, and the moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent and moſt exquiſite natural o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration of all the works of nature;<note place="margin">Ariſtotle 2 Gen. A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>mal. Galen de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> part. <hi>14.2.</hi>
                  </note> which <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> moſt elegantly ſets forth, and demonſtrates, That where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as it is impoſſible by the decree of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, that any animal or Creature ſhould live alwayes, or have an eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Eſſence and being: therefore for the continuance of the kinds of all Creatures, as well bruit as rational, that a continual Generation might be had, and maintained, the Sexes of male and female, fitted to the act of procreation, were ordained.</p>
               <p>And from hence, ſaith <hi>Galen,</hi> it comes to paſſe, that all Creatures are furniſhed with Inſtruments of genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, fitting the quality of their Sexe, and are indued with natural inſtincts, prompting them to the uſe thereof.</p>
               <p>Therefore we here take liberty, to ſpeak of this wonderful Operation of nature. And to ſeek out the cauſes that hinder, and preſcribe meanes to fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Operation of the ſame; part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for Dame Natures ſake, whoſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent in hindred, where this work is
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:170219:55"/>obſtructed, and partly for thoſe Ladies ſakes, who are ſometimes diſconſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late, being amongſt the number of thoſe that are accounted barren.</p>
               <p>We intend not here to enter into the Philoſophers Inquiſitions, nor the Phyſitians Lectures; what is the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming matter which cauſes the birth in the Womb; in what order, how, and in what time, or how many dayes the ſeveral parts and members of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy are framed; at what time God the Authour of all things, and nature it ſelf infuſeth the living ſoul into the Conception, or conceived body; but our intention only is to ſpeak of what belongs to Phyſick, and not only to Philoſophy; &amp; to treat of thoſe things which do impedite, or hinder the perfection of conception.</p>
               <p>For as the conception hath ſome contingency with every part of the body, ſo the ſame may be taken quite away, hindred or impedited, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praved, as it happens in all other acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and motions of the body.</p>
               <p>If Conception be quite taken away in a Woman, ſo that ſhe can never
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:170219:60"/>conceive, this affection is called bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renneſs; or this may be called a bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren Woman, which you pleaſe.</p>
               <p>But if a Woman do conceive ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, though rarely and ſeldom, this is a weak and diminutive conception, or the conceiving faculty is feeble, and diminutive.</p>
               <p>And to this kind of debility and weakneſs, may be referred abortive, and untimely Births; when the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man doth conceive, but through weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs cannot bring the conception to the due time of the birth.</p>
               <p>There is alſo a depraved concepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, when in the Womans Womb is contained ſome unnatural concepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as Monſters, <hi>Mola,</hi> or ſuperfluous unſhapen fleſh, water, wind, or the like, filling up the Womb, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving the form of a conceived ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance: the cauſes and Remedies of theſe, we ſhall proceed to declare.</p>
               <p>The holy Scripture makes mention what reproach, and how odious and deteſtable a thing barrenneſs was ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted in the antient times: there was hardly any greater defamation to
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:170219:60"/>a woman, ſo that <hi>Rachel</hi> could cry out to her Husband for Children, or elſe her life lay on it, rather then bear the reproach of barrenneſs; and ſome Women have preferred their <hi>Maids</hi> to their Husbands, ſo that the Child might be reputed theirs, to take away their blemiſh of barrenneſs; but you will find few Women of that mind now a dayes.</p>
               <p>Therefore we come to ſpeak of the cauſes of this grief, which the Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians do account many and divers.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hippocrates</hi> accounteth the principal cauſes of barrenneſs to be theſe,<note place="margin">Hippoc. lib. de ſterili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate.</note> if the mouth of the Womb be diſterred, and turned aſide out of its place, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary from the <hi>pudenda</hi> if the mouth of the Womb appear too big, or more wide then is convenient; or if the mouth of the Womb be fallen down, or hang out below the <hi>pudenda;</hi> then is ſuch a Woman unfit for concepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; theſe are therefore great cauſes of barrenneſs.</p>
               <p>Many other are the cauſes of bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renneſs, ſometimes more, ſometimes leſſe, as <hi>Galen</hi> excellently teacheth.</p>
               <pb n="104" facs="tcp:170219:61"/>
               <p>The head and principal beginning of the invention,<note place="margin">Gal. <hi>3.</hi> de Symp. Cauſ.</note> and finding out of all cauſes, which bring hurt, or are ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noxious to the faculties of the body, is no other but the knowledge of the meanes; whereby theſe faculties per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form their actions in the time of health and ſoundneſs of body.</p>
               <p>And whereas it hath been already declared, that to produce any natural conception, there is a neceſſity of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction, and carnal copulation, both of the man and woman: therefore it ought, firſt, to be made manifeſt, that the cauſe of barrenneſs, may be through ſome defect in the man, or in the woman, and ſometimes in both.</p>
               <p>Although at this time our intent is only to treat of ſuch Diſeaſes, as are incident to Women: yet neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, ſince the Women have in this caſe a great intereſt, and a dammage too if the fault be in the man; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they may help their Husbands defect, and in ſo doing, pleaſure them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, if they finde the imperfection to lie in him, we ſhall not praetermit it.</p>
               <pb n="105" facs="tcp:170219:61"/>
               <p>And again, ſince there is a neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Copulation of man and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, or elſe there can be no generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: and that they be both furniſhed with fit Inſtruments for that purpoſe, as the man with the yard, ſtones, and ſeed; the woman with <hi>Pudenda, teſtes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">You may eaſily know what I mean.</note> the womb, ſeed, and menſtruous blood.</p>
               <p>Then all reaſon tells you, that if there be any diſaffection, or defect in nature, in any of theſe members or parts, belonging to this work, the fruitfulneſs and conception muſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily be, either impedited, dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, or quite taken away.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Barren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in men. Few Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men do complain of this fault.</note>One cauſe of barrenneſs on the mans part, which is of all Authours condemned, is, <hi>penis longus,</hi> or the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vermuch length of the yard; by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon whereof, the ſeed is refrigerated, and taketh cold in the paſſage of the yard, before it can be injected from the ſtones, into the womb.</p>
               <pb n="106" facs="tcp:170219:62"/>
               <p>But although this be a general re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived reaſon,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Avicen. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>tract.</hi> 1.8.</note> amongſt almoſt all Philoſophers, yet it may ſeem vain, and ſuffer contradiction; for the ſeed paſſing through the Conduit, or chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel of the yard, is cheriſhed, and kept hot, by the <hi>pudenda</hi> of the woman, ſo that it ſeems impoſſible, that it ſhould take cold in the paſſage; but rather the contrary, that the long <hi>penis</hi> is moſt fit and commodious, to further and perfect the Conception, by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecting the ſeed into the inner parts of the womb, which is done without any interval, or ſpace of time.</p>
               <p>And alſo contradictive to this O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, is the relation of <hi>Averroes,</hi> which is credited by <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther good Philoſophers, That a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Maid conceived with Child, by ſtanding in a Bath, where ſome ſeed of man had been caſt, the Womb drawing the ſame into it, by its natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral magnetick attractive faculty, which draweth and attracteth to it ſelf the ſeed of man, as the Loadſtone draweth Iron.</p>
               <p>But whereas many will have it, that
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:170219:62"/>the too long yard is unfit for concep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;<note place="margin">This is the worſt fault in womens account.</note> ſo there are others on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, that affirm the ſhort <hi>penis</hi> to render men unfruitful, and that to be as bad, if not a greater fault then the other.</p>
               <p>And this is the more probable rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, that the ſhort <hi>penis</hi> may be more defective then the long one, becauſe it cannot ſo well inject the ſeed into the inner parts of the womb.</p>
               <p>But to ſpeak freely, neither of theſe cauſes, either of the length or ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the yard, can be firm reaſons of the barrenneſs, or fruitfulneſs of man, or to cauſe barrenneſs in the man, ſince it is confirmed by experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of both parts, that have had plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Children.</p>
               <p>But a greater reaſon of barrenneſs in the man, may be ſome vitiouſneſs, or defect in the yard, as if the ſame be oblique or crooked, if any of the liga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments thereof be diſtorred, or broken, whereby the wayes and paſſages, through which the ſeed ſhould flow, be corrupt, ſtopped, or vitiated; or ſome Diſeaſe or imperfection, be ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:170219:63"/>in the proper, or in the vicious parts thereof.</p>
               <p>Another cauſe of barrenneſs, by the defect of the yard, is too much weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and tenderneſs thereof, ſo that it is not ſtrongly enough erected, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject the ſeed into the womb; for the ſtrength and ſtifneſs of the yard, very much conduces to conception, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the forcible injection of the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane ſeed into the womb.</p>
               <p>A ſecond cauſe of barrenneſs of men, may be ſome natural vice, or lae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion in the ſtones;<note place="margin">Gal. <hi>14.</hi> uſu part. <hi>1.</hi> de ſem. <hi>11, 16.</hi>
                  </note> if they are ſo made by nature, that they cannot exerciſe their gift properly, in producing ſeed.</p>
               <p>The ſtones may be the cauſe of barrenneſs, by reaſon of their evil compoſition, or accidents and diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, or continual ſolution.</p>
               <p>The ſtones may labour under di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtempers, either ſimple or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound, either with, or without mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
               <p>As if the ſtones be oppreſſed with any inflammation or tumour, wound
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:170219:63"/>or Ulcer, or drawn up within the bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, not appearing outwardly, all ſuch cauſes of the ſtones, may be the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of barrenneſs in the man.</p>
               <p>Alſo the man may be barren, by reaſon of the defect of the ſeed, and that may come from a twofold cauſe.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>The firſt, If he ingender and caſt forth no ſeed at all, or in leſſe ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance then is needful.</item>
                  <item>And ſecondly, If the ſeed genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and caſt forth, be vitious, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit for generation.</item>
               </list>
               <p>The ſeed is hindred from generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in thoſe bodies, which are groſſe and fat, the matter of it being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fective.</p>
               <p>And on the other ſide too much leaneſs, or a continual waſting or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption of the body, deſtroyes the ſeed; nature turning all the matter and ſubſtance thereof, into nutriment for the body.</p>
               <p>The ſeed may alſo be corrupt, and vitious, by reaſon of many internal, and external cauſes.</p>
               <p>If the Inſtruments and Veſſels of
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:170219:64"/>ſeed be intemperate, or diſaffected, or in any wayes corrupted, that they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not attract the matter of the fruitful ſeed, and ſo that they cannot concoct the attracted matter, and retain the ſame ſo long, until it can receive its whole and perfect abſolution; as for examples ſake, it frequently happens to thoſe, who have a long time laboured with the Gonorrhea, or running of the Reins; or if the principal parts of the body be ſo ill affected, that they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit ill nutriment, that cauſeth viti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſeed to be generated, unfit for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception.</p>
               <p>Likewiſe many outward cauſes may ſo alter, and diſaffect our bodies, as that they may cauſe the ſeed to be vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious, and unfruitful.</p>
               <p>Too frequent carnal Copulation,<note place="margin">Gal. <hi>1.</hi> de ſem. Cap. <hi>16.</hi>
                  </note> is one great cauſe of barrenneſs of men, which attracteth the ſeminal moi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture from the ſtones, before it is ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently prepared, and concocted, as all other members of the body, by the inſtitution of nature, do uſe to draw their accuſtomed juyce to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
               <pb n="111" facs="tcp:170219:64"/>
               <p>So if any one by daily Copulation, do exhauſt and draw out all the moy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture of his ſeed, then do the ſtones draw the moyſt humours from the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perior veins, unto themſelves; and ſo having but a little blood in them, they are forced of neceſſity, to caſt it out raw, and unconcocted; and thus the ſtones be violently deprived of the moyſture of their veins, attract the ſame from the other ſuperior veins, and the ſuperior veins, from all the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther parts of the body, for their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per nutriment, to the great violating of the body, depriving the ſame of the vital ſpirits.</p>
               <p>It is therefore no wonder, if thoſe that uſe immoderate Copulation, are very weak in their bodies, ſeeing the whole body is thereby deprived of its beſt &amp; pureſt blood, &amp; of the vital ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits: inſomuch, that many who have bin too much addicted to the pleaſure, have killed themſelves in the act.</p>
               <p>But chiefly, It is no wonder, if ſuch ſeed not well concocted and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſted, be unfit for generation.</p>
               <pb n="112" facs="tcp:170219:65"/>
               <p>Gluttony and drunkenneſs, do alſo much hinder men from fruitfulneſs, and maketh them unfit for generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
               <p>But amongſt other cauſes of bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renneſs in men, this alſo is one that maketh them barren, and of the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of Eunuchs, the inciſion, or cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of their veins behinde their ears, which for a Diſeaſe many times is done.</p>
               <p>This ſaith <hi>Hippocrates,</hi> cauſeth barrenneſs in them,<note place="margin">Gal. Lib. de geni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur.</note> whoſe veins be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde their eares are cut, to which <hi>Galen</hi> agrees; for he ſaith, that eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially more then from any other parts of the body, the ſeed flowes from the brain by thoſe veins behinde the eares, which alſo <hi>Aristotle</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firms.</p>
               <p>From whence it probably appears, that the tranſmiſſion of the ſeed is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedited by the Section of the Veins behinde the eares, ſo that it cannot at all deſcend to the lower parts of the body, or elſe very crude and raw.</p>
               <pb n="113" facs="tcp:170219:65"/>
               <p>And thus have we ſhown the cauſes of barrenneſſe in men. Now we come to ſpeak of barrenneſſe in women.</p>
               <p>Although there are many cauſes of the barrenneſs of women; yet the chief and principal are internal, and they may be all referred to the privy parts of the Body, the Seed, or the menſtruous blood.</p>
               <p>Therefore <hi>Hippocrates</hi> ſpeaking of the eaſy and difficult Conception of Women, ſaith thus; The firſt conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration is to be had of their Species; for little Women are more apt to conceive then great; ſlender, then groſſe; white and fair, then ruddy and high coloured; black, then pale and wan.</p>
               <p>Thoſe which have their Veins con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicuous, are more apt then others; but to be very fleſhy is evil, to have great ſwelling Breaſts good.</p>
               <p>The next thing to be conſidered is, their Courſes or monethly purgations, whether they have them duty every Moneth, if they flow plentifully and are of a good colour; whether they
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:170219:66"/>have them equal every moneth, at their certain daies and times; for ſo their purgations ought to be.</p>
               <p>Then the Womb, or place of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception is to be conſidered, it ought to be clean and ſound, dry and ſoft, the Womb not retracted nor drawn up, nor prone or deſcended down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, and the mouth thereof ought not to be turned awry, nor everſt, nor too cloſe ſhut.</p>
               <p>But to come to conſider of theſe Cauſes more diſtinctly, and particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly.</p>
               <p>The firſt parts therefore to be ſpoken of, are the <hi>pudenda,</hi> that is, the privie member, and the Womb, which parts are ſhut &amp; encloſed, either by nature, or againſt nature; &amp; from hence ſuch women are called inperforate; For in ſome Women the mouth of their Womb continueth compreſſed &amp; clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed up, from the time of their Birth, until the time of the ripeneſs of their Courſes; and then on a ſudden when their Terms provoke forwards to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, they are moleſted with great pain and ſickneſs: ſome break, of their
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:170219:66"/>own accord, others are diſſected and opened by Phyſitians, to ſome it brings death, or elſe they are forced to break, or never break at all.</p>
               <p>And this <hi>Aetius</hi> diſtinctly handles, who writeth, that the Wombs of wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men are ſhut three manner of waies, which hinders Conception.</p>
               <p>The firſt is, When the lips of the <hi>Pudenda</hi> do grow or cleave toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Although the lips ſeem open, yet there are certain Membrances growing in the middle part of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trix within.</p>
               <p>The third, Though the lips and boſome of the <hi>Pudenda</hi> may appear fair and open, yet the Mouth of the Womb may be quite ſhut up; all which three kinds of Cloſures are im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pediments to the Conceptions of wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
               <p>They do hinder in the firſt place, the performance of three offices; the uſe of man, their purgations, and their Conception.</p>
               <p>In the ſecond place, they are two impediments, the communication
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:170219:67"/>with men, and Conception there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by.</p>
               <p>And thirdly, two other impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to themſelves, Purgation and Conception, there might alſo fall in by the way, a diſcourſe of the Hymen, or that Membrane which is ſo called; but that only ſerves for the teſtimony of true virginity to them that know it, which lock the loſſe of a Maidenhead opens: but that ſeems a digreſſion from this intention.</p>
               <p>But amongſt all cauſes of barrenneſs in a Woman, in the inſtruments of generation, it is certain, that the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt is in the Womb, for the Wombe is the field of generation; and if this field be corrupt, and not well diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, it is in vain to expect any fruit, let it be never ſo well tilled and ſown, for the Womb is ſubject to many di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſes, and thence it followes, that it may be often unfit for generation, diſtempers many are ſubject to it, as over much heat, and over much cold. Women whoſe Wombs are too thick and cold, cannot in any wiſe conceive,
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:170219:67"/>becauſe coldneſs extinguiſheth the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural heat of the humane Seed.</p>
               <p>Another cauſe of barrenneſs may be, immoderate moiſture of the Womb, which deſtroys the Seed of the man, as Corn ſown in ponds and marſhes.</p>
               <p>A third cauſe of barrenneſs of the Woman, is, over much dryneſs of the Womb: ſo that the humane Seed pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſheth for want of nutriment, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes as Corn ſown upon ſtones, or ſandy ground.</p>
               <p>A fourth cauſe of womens barren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is, the immoderate heat of the Womb, which ſcorcheth up the Seed of man, as Corn ſown in the drought of Summer; for immoderate heat hurts all the parts of the Body, and no Conception can live, or be nouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed in that woman.</p>
               <p>Many other may be the diſtempers which the Womb is ſubject to, that may render it unfit for Conception, and be the cauſe of barrenneſs, as when unnatural humors, are ingen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred in the Womb, too much flegm, Tympanies, worms, wind, water or any ſuch peccant humour, abounding contrary to nature.</p>
               <pb n="118" facs="tcp:170219:68"/>
               <p>But amongſt all other cauſes, which produce fertility, or barrenneſs to a woman, the monethly Terms are greatly to be reſpected, as hinderers or furtherers thereof; if they come not in due order, it muſt neceſſarily cauſe barrenneſſe of that woman to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low; but of them we have already ſpoken, and given directions how to promote and further the ſame.</p>
               <p>But having ſufficiently ſpoken of the cauſes of barrenneſs in man and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, we ſhall methodically proceed for procreation ſake, to lay down ſuch remedies, as may naturally ſerve to prefer generation, and hinder acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dental barrenneſs in either.</p>
               <p>But if in men the cauſe be, and that in the ſhortneſs of the <hi>penis,</hi> I cannot help that: the women muſt in that caſe help themſelves as well as they can: of any too long there is ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom any complaint.</p>
               <p>A woman may alſo have ſome other accidentall cauſes, which may hinder her conception; as ſudden frights, and anger, fear, grief, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turbations
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:170219:68"/>of the mind, too violent exerciſe or ſtirring after Carnal copu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulation, leaping, dancing, running, or the like.</p>
               <p>If the cauſe of barrenneſs be in the man, through over much hear in his Seed, the woman may eaſily ſee! that in receiving it.</p>
               <p>If the nature of the woman be too hot, and by that cauſe ſhe is unfit for Copulation, it may appear by theſe Signs.</p>
               <p>Such a woman, whoſe cauſe of bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renneſs is by reaſon of too much heat, ſhe hath her Terms or Flowers very little, and they are mixt with ſome yellowneſſe; ſuch a woman is very haſty and Chollerick, quick witted and crafty, thirſty and deſirous after Carnal Copulation, her pulſe very ſwift.</p>
               <p>Some ſay that by theſe ſignes you may know where the fault lies, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the man or the woman: Sprin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kle both Urines of the man and of the woman upon a Lettice leave, and that which dries away firſt is unfruitful.</p>
               <pb n="120" facs="tcp:170219:69"/>
               <p>Alſo take five Wheat corns, ſeven Barley corns, and ſeven Beans; put them all into an earthen pot, and piſſe thereon, and let it ſtand ſeven daies; if they begin to ſprout, the party is fruitful; if they rot, then barren, be it man or woman.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Another way to know whether a woman be fruitful</head>
                  <p>Take Mirth, red Storax, and ſome ſuch like odoriferous things, and make a perfume thereof, which let the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man receive into the neck of the Womb through a tunnel; if the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man feel the ſmoke aſcend through her Body to her Noſe, then ſhe is fruitful.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Another experiment for the ſame.</head>
                  <p>Take Garlick and beat it, and let the woman lie on her Back upon it, and if ſhe feel the ſent thereof to her Noſe; its a ſign of fruitfulneſſe.</p>
                  <p>But I could tell you a more infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble rule, for either the man or woman,
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:170219:69"/>to find out where the fault lies, but they are too apt to learn it without teaching, therefore I paſſe it by.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>If the barrenneſs be proceeding from a hot cauſe, then take theſe directions.</head>
                  <p>Let ſuch beware of hot air and hot dwellings if they can; and that they uſe not too hot cloths about the ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>news, and parts of the Womb.</p>
                  <p>Let them avoid hot meats (I ſpeak now to women) hot Spices, ſtrong Wine, fat meats, warm hearbs uſe not over much watching, lye not much on the Reins and Kidneys, and as much as poſſibly may be, eſchew great labour, anger, heavineſs, and all ſuch motions as diſturb the mind, and uſe moderately cooling things, as thus,</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>To further Conception, and take away barrenneſs proceeding of hot cauſes.</head>
                  <p>Take oftentimes Conſerve of Roſes, cold Lozinges made of Dragagant, the Confections of Triaſantali; and uſe
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:170219:70"/>to ſmell to Camphire, Roſe water and Saunders.</p>
                  <p>It is alſo good to breathe the Baſilica, or Liver Vein, and take out four or five ounces of blood, and then take this purge.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>A Purge against Barrenneſs through heat.</head>
                  <p>Take <hi>Electuarium de Epithymo de ſucco roſarum,</hi> of each two drams and a half: whey of milk four ounces: mix them well together, and take it in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning faſting, ſleep after it about an hour and an half, and faſt four hours after it, and then drink a good draught of Whey about an hour before you eat any thing.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
                  <p>Take water Lilly water four ounces; Mandrogara water, one ounce: Saſſron, half a ſcruple: beat the Safron to powder, and mix it with the waters, and drink them warm in the morning, uſe this eight daies together.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="123" facs="tcp:170219:70"/>
                  <head>Pills againſt Barrenneſs.</head>
                  <p>Take Broom flowers, Smallage, Parſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley ſeed, Comin, Mugwort, Fetherfew, of each half a ſcruple: Aloes, half an ounce; Indy Salt, Saffron, of each half a dram: beat &amp; mix them all well toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, &amp; put to it five ounces of Fether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>few water warm, ſtop it up cloſe, &amp; let it ſtand and dry in a warm place; and thus do two or three times one after another. Then make each dram into 6 Pills, and take one of them every other day before ſupper, all the while the ſaid Potion is uſed, and afterwards when the drink is done, take one of theſe Pills every third or fourth day. And after that Potion proceed with this purging Medecine following.</p>
                  <p>Take Conſerve Benedicta lax. one quarter of an ounce: de Pſillio; three drams; Elect. de Succo roſarum, one dram: mix them together with Fetherfew water, and drink it in the morning betimes.</p>
                  <pb n="124" facs="tcp:170219:71"/>
                  <p>About three daies after the Patient hath taken this purge: let her be let blood four or five ounces in the Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an vein in the right foot. And then take five daies one after another filed Ivory, a dram and a half in Fetherfew water; and during that time, let her ſit in this Bath following, an hour to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether morning and night.</p>
                  <p>Take wild yellow rapes, Daucus, Balſam wood and fruit, Aſh-keys, of each two handfuls; red Behen, white Behen, Broom flowers, of each a handful; Musk, three grains; Amber, Saffron, of each one ſcruple; Boil all in water ſufficiently, but the Musk, Saffron Amber and Broom flowers, put them into the decoction after it is boiled and ſtrained.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>A Confection profitable againſt barrennes.</head>
                  <p>Take Piſtacia, Pingles, Eringos, of each half an ounce; Saffron, one dram: Lignum Aloes, Galingale, Mace, Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riophilata, Balm flowers, red Behen, white Behen, of each four ſcruples; ſhaven Ivory, Caſſia bark, of each two
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:170219:71"/>ſcruples; ſyrup of confected Ginger, twelve ounces; white Sugar, ſix oun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: decoct all theſe well together, in twelve ounces of Balm water, and ſtir it well together; then put to it of Musk and Amber, of each half a ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. Take hereof the quantity of a Nutmeg three times a day, in the morning an hour before noon, and an hour after ſupper,</p>
                  <p>But if the cauſe of Barrenneſs in man or woman, be through ſcarcity or diminution of the natural Seed, then ſuch things are to be taken, as do in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe Seed, and incite and ſtir up Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nery.</p>
                  <p>For this is good, yellow Rape ſeed baked in bread, young fat fleſh not too much ſalted, Saffron, the tailes of Stin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus, and long Pepper, are good prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in Wine.</p>
                  <p>Let ſuch parties eſchew all ſowre, ſharp, doughy, and ſlimy meats, long ſleep after meat, ſurfetting and drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſſe, and as near as poſſibly you can, keep your ſelves from ſorrow, grief, vexation, and care.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="126" facs="tcp:170219:72"/>
                  <head>To encreaſe natural ſeed.</head>
                  <p>Generally theſe things following encreaſe natural ſeed, and ſtir up ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nery, and recover the Seed again, when it is loſt, <hi>viz.</hi> Eggs, Milk, Rice boyled in milk; Sparrows brains, fleſh and bones and all; The Stones and Piſſels of Bulls, Cocks, Bucks, Rams, and Bores.</p>
                  <p>Portages good to encreaſe natural Seed, are ſuch as are made of Beans, Peaſe, and Lupines: caſt away the firſt bitter broth of the Lupines, and mix the reſt with Sugar. French Beans, Wheat ſodden in broth. Anniſeeds, Fennel-ſeed, Muſtard ſeed, Colewort ſeed, and Nettle ſeed.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Roots good to increaſe the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Seed.</head>
                  <p>Oynions ſtewed, Garlick, Leeks, yellow Rapes, freſh Ragwort roots, confected Sugar, confected Eringo roots, confected Ginger, Coſtus roots, Sperage, Thiſtle roots, Radiſh roots,
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:170219:72"/>Zedoary, confected Aſſarabacca.</p>
                  <p>Of fruits, Hazel nuts, Cypreſs nuts, Piſtacia, Almonds, and Marchpane made thereof.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Spices commodious to ſtir up Venery are,</head>
                  <p>In general Cinamon, Cardamome, Galingale, long Pepper, Cloves, Gin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and Saffron.</p>
                  <p>Aſſa foetida taken a dram and a half at a time in good Wine, is very good for this purpoſe, and ſo likewiſe is Dragagant, Borax is alſo fit to be taken in like manner.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Of Compoſitions, theſe Confections fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing are good to increaſe the natural Seed.</head>
                  <p>The Confection Dia Moſcha, Aro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticum roſarum, Diambra, Dianthos, Diagalanga, Tryon pipetion, Dia mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gariton calidum, &amp; Mithridate, and eſpecially the Confection of Diaſaty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rion, but theſe are dear.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="128" facs="tcp:170219:73"/>
                  <head>Lozinges, or a Confection to increaſe the naturall Seed.</head>
                  <p>Take Ginger, one dram and a half; Almonds, Pingles, Piſtacia, of each one ounce; Kernels of Indian Nuts, Syſarum, of each half an ounce; Harts Piſle, five drams: Cinque-foi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e, Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma Chri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>i, one dram and a half: Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingale, Cloves, Cinamon, Muſtard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeed, long Pepper, yellow Rape ſeed, white Behen, of each one dram; Oni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſeed, Radiſh ſeed, Rape ſeed, Aſhen keys, of each two ſcruples: ſides of Stymus, tails of Stymus, three drams; Borrage, one quarter of an ounce; Sugar, two pound; boil them altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in Wine ſufficient to make a Confection or Lozinges thereof; and take about the quantity of a Nutmeg at a time.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
                  <p>Take yellow Rapes, Onions, Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage roots, Muſtard ſeed, Radiſh ſeed, Pingles, Aſh-keyes, Eringo roots,
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:170219:73"/>Satyrion Roots, Coſtus Roots, Gin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, long Pepper, Creſſes ſeeds, of each a like: make all theſe into fine Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and mix them well together, and add to every Ounce of the Powder 3. Ounces of clarified Honey, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with make it into a Confection: take of this Confection, about 3 drams at a time, with a little Sugar, and new milk.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>For the weakneſs, and debility of the yard of a man, uſe this Oyntment.</head>
                  <p>Take Wax, Oyl of Bever-cod, Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jerom gentle, and Oyl of Coſtus, of each a like quantity; make it into an Oyntment, and put to it a little Musk, and therewith annoint the yard, and other members adjacent.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Another Oyntment for the ſame.</head>
                  <p>Take of Horſe Emmers 3 drams, oyl of white Seſamum, oyl of Lillies, of each one Ounce: pound and bruiſe the Ants, and put them to the Oyl, and
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:170219:74"/>let them ſtand in the Sun 6 dayes, then ſtrain out the Oyl, and add to it Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phorbium 1 ſcruple, Pepper, Rue, of each one dram; Muſtard-ſeed half a dram: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>et this again altogether in the Sun, 2 or 3 dayes, then annoint all the Inſtruments of Generation there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
                  <p>Take Oyl of Lillies 2 Ounces, Oyl of Bever Cod 1 Ounce, Euphorbium, Pepper, Muſtard-ſeed, of each 1 dram, Muſcus half a ſcruple, mix them toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther unto an Oyntment, and uſe it as the other.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Remedies againſt barrenneſs in Women, through Cold.</head>
                  <p>Care muſt be taken in this caſe, to cleanſe the womb from all exceſſive moyſture, and not to overcharge the ſtomack with meat, and refrain from much ſleep, and not addict her ſelf to anger, nor ſorrow neither, if ſhe can avoid it, to uſe moderate exerciſe and
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:170219:74"/>ſtirring, unleſs it be immediately af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſhe hath bin helping her Husband to get a Child, or endevouring to do it, then let her reſt from exerciſe, and motion of the body, at leaſt 2 houres after it.</p>
                  <p>Let her abſtain from eating of much fiſh, milk, or freſh cheeſe and from fat fleſh, and Vinegar, theſe are obnox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ious to the womb.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>To cleanſe the womb from moyſture.</head>
                  <p>Take a potion prepared of Oximel, of Squils, or of Oximel compoſitum, and Sirrup of Wormwood, with a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coction of Annis, Fennel, Comin, and Harts Tongue. And afterwards, take 1 dram of Pill benedicta, once in 14. dayes, and faſt 5 houres after it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>A Bath for the ſame.</head>
                  <p>Take Storax, Calamita, Field Mints, Aſphalatus, Annis, Seſeli, Rue, Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſame wood and fruits, Behen red and white, of each half 1 Ounce; boyl all together in water, and make a Bath
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:170219:75"/>thereof, and let the party ſit in it up to the navel.</p>
                  <p>Alſo uſe often to annoynt the parts about the womb, with warm and dry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Oyl, ſuch as Oyl of Spike, Oyl of Elder, and the like.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Another Bath for the ſame, wherein the Woman may either bathe her whole body, or ſit in it up to the middle.</head>
                  <p>Take Mugwort, Sage, of each two handfuls, Calamint, Dittany, of each half a handful, Fennel Roots, Spara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus, Parſley, of each one handful, Bay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berries, Juniper, Annis, Comin, of each two drams, mixe them, and boyl them all in water, and make a Bath thereof, and uſe it, as before is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>A Confection good againſt barrenneſs, cauſed through too much coldneſs, and moyſture in the womb.</head>
                  <p>Take Cinamon, Cardamon, Saffron, Cloves, Mace, long Pepper, Cypers
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:170219:75"/>Roots, Nutmegs, Cummin, Lignum Aloes, Caſſia wood, of each 1 ſcruple; Cucubes, Doronicum, of each four ſcruples; Musk, Amber, Balſom, one dram, fine Sugar 18 Ounces, boyl the Sugar with the reſt, with Malmſey, and Bugloſſe-water, enough to make it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Confection; and take thereof a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout a ſpoonful, going to bed, and half a ſpoonful a little before Supper.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>To dry a moyſt and ſlippery womb.</head>
                  <p>Take Silver Mountain, red Behen, white Behen, Aſh Keyes, ſhaven Ivo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, yellow Rape-ſeed, of each one dram, Cynamon, Mace, Cloves, Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingale, long Pepper, Roſemary flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, Balſom wood, Marjerom gentle, Peny royal, of each 4 ſcruples, Balm, Bugloſs, Citron peels, of each 2 ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples; Pearls 1 ſcruple, Musk 2 grains, white Sugar 24 Oun: ſeeth theſe with Malmſey, &amp; make thereof a Confecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and uſe it as the other.</p>
                  <p>If there be any infirmity in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentive faculty of the womb, ſo that it cannot retain and keep the ſeed inje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted into it, ſo as to come in thereby,
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:170219:76"/>if the ſame be cauſed through over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much coldneſs of that part, as often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times it doth, which the Woman her ſelf may be ſenſible of, whether heat or cold do moſt abound; I ſay, if cold abound, and weaken the retent ivevir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of the womb, then you are to uſe ſuch things as ſtrengthen, comfort, and warm the ſame, ſuch are Amber, Frankincenſe, Maſtick, Cloves, Lignum Aloes, Nutmegs, Sage, and the like.</p>
                  <p>And in this caſe, it is good to boyl Cypers Roots in the water, and often bathe, and waſh the neck of the Matrix therewith.</p>
                  <p>And for this, it is good to make a fume of Maſtick ſtrewed upon Coals, and to receive the ſame into the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trix below.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>An Oyntment for the ſame.</head>
                  <p>Take the juyce of Roſes, of Pome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>granates, Cloves, of each an Ounce, Frankincenſe, Hypociſtis, prepared Coriander, Maſtick, Juyce of Sloes, Iron, Droſſe, of each one dram, ſealed Earth, Starch, of each one Ounce, beat
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:170219:76"/>all theſe together to an Oyntment, and annoint the privy members, and womb often therewith.</p>
                  <p>But if the operation of the reten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive faculty of the womb be impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from performing its natural office through ſome diſtemper of heat, then are ſuch Medicines to be applyed, as are cooling, aſtringent, and corrobo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rating; yet let them be tempered with ſome warm things.</p>
                  <p>The cold things to be uſed for this purpoſe are theſe, burnt Harts-horn, Amber, Juyce of ſloes.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Hypociſtis,</hi> burnt Muſcle ſhells, Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus, Dragons blood, <hi>terra ſigillata,</hi> Pomegranate flowers, and Pills, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corns, and their Cups, Medlars both fruit and bark of the Tree, Services, and Mirtle-ſeed: of any of theſe ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, you may make unguents, Plai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, Confections and Electuaries, or other Medicines, as occaſion ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire.</p>
                  <p>If any yet deſire other Medicines, they may uſe Plaiſters and Peſſaries, and trochis for a fumigation; of which here follows; examples.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="134" facs="tcp:170219:77"/>
                  <head>A Plaiſter to comfort the womb againſt barrenneſs.</head>
                  <p>Take Landanum 1 Ounce, Storax Calamite, half an Ounce, Cynamon, Cloves, Lignum Aloes, of each 1 dram; Species Diambre, Gallia Moſcata, of each half a dram; Oyl of Spikenard, Oyl of Lillies, and Wax a ſufficient quantity to make it into a Plaiſter, or Cerot. This Plaiſter may be applyed to the womb, and quite down to the lower Region of the Abdomen, and worn thereupon a long time.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>For a <hi>Fame,</hi> theſe <hi>Troches</hi> following may be taken.</head>
                  <p>Take of Mugwort a dram, Mirrhe, Benzoi-Storax, Calamint, of each half a dram, Lignum Aloes 1 ſcruple, Musk, Amber, of each 10 grains: beat all theſe together to a Powder, and with Oyl of Spikenard, make Troches of it; put ſome of it upon Coals, and let the Woman receive the fume thereof through a convenient Inſtrument.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="135" facs="tcp:170219:77"/>
                  <head>A Peſſary for the ſame.</head>
                  <p>Take Mugwort, Ditany, Marioram, of each 1 dram, Aniſeeds, Rue, Citron, of each half a dram, Species Galliae Moſchatae one ſcruple, Musk, Amber, Saffron, of each 15 grains, beat them all together into a Maſſe, and make a Peſſary thereof, wrapped up in Linnen, and put it up into the Matrix.</p>
                  <p>And now we have largely declared to you, the external and internal cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, of natural and accidental barren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and ſterility, both in man and woman, and the Phyſical, both exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal and internal means, to be uſed to remedy the ſame, what elſe is to be done, your own natural kindneſs muſt excite you to; which if it be but dull, we have given you ſufficient Rules, whereby you may quicken the ſame. Some other things there are, which the Phyſicians ſay, do prefer fruitful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, by hidden quality, as the ſtones of a Fox, and the like; but they are already declared, and deſcribed in compound Medicines.</p>
                  <pb n="136" facs="tcp:170219:78"/>
                  <p>Phyſitians do likewiſe tell long ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries about the time of the year, what time is beſt for Copulation: all agree, the Spring is the moſt convenient time, and fit for procreation; for then the blood is in its vigour: and in the heat of Summer, it ought to be forborn al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together, if poſſible (but then <hi>Venus</hi> takes moſt pleaſure to be jolly, and to her girles then moſt opportunities offer themſelves.)</p>
                  <p>But the moſt convenient and fit time for a Woman to conceive, is immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately after her purgations ceaſe; for then the womb is cleanſed from ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluous excrements; and the moſt fit houre for conception, is after meat, and before ſleep, that ſhe may ſleep, and reſt after it.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <pb n="137" facs="tcp:170219:78"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Chap. X.</hi> Of monſtrous and unnatural Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions.</head>
               <p>IT followes now in order in the next place, to ſpeak ſomething of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions, contrary to nature, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural Births, which is called a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praved Conception.</p>
               <p>For ſince it is the certain inſtitution and intent of nature, that Women ſhould bring forth perfect man-kind, and nothing elſe, then it followes, that whatſoever elſe is conceived in the womb, beſides man-kind, the ſame is a vitious, and depraved conception, againſt the Rules and Lawes of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
               <p>Which though theſe vitious and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural Conceptions, may be many wayes; yet they may all generally be reduced unto one of theſe heads, to wit, Monſters, Mola, winde and wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, all which we often finde to be conceived, and grow in the womb.</p>
               <pb n="138" facs="tcp:170219:79"/>
               <p>Of Monſters, there is much writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, either hiſtorically, fabulouſly, or philoſophically; but that appertains not to our preſent intent or purpoſe.</p>
               <p>And therefore the Philoſopher in his Book of Generation,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Phyſ.</hi> 82.4. <hi>Gen. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimal.</hi>
                  </note> and the cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes thereof teacheth, that a Monſter is nothing elſe but a peccant vice of deficient nature, whereby nature is impedited, and hindered from effect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her end, as it is in any Art, when the Artiſt fails, by reaſon of ſome de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect in him, that he cannot attain to accompliſh his deſired end.</p>
               <p>And although theſe unnatural Births may happen many wayes, yet all theſe errors of nature may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred to the Diſeaſes proceeding of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil compoſition: as for example, to the Diſeaſe in number, as when a man is born with one eye, one foot, or two heads.</p>
               <p>Of Diſeaſes of magnitude, the ſame the figure of the body demonſtrates to the reſt;<note place="margin">Gal de cauſis morb. <hi>7.</hi>
                  </note> which Doctrine, <hi>Galen</hi> mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly teacheth.</p>
               <p>But the cauſes why Monſters are generated, contrary to the intent of
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:170219:79"/>nature,<note place="margin">Gal. lib. de hiſt. Phil. lib. <hi>5.</hi> plai. Ph. <hi>8.</hi>
                  </note> are not fully agreed upon by all. <hi>Galen,</hi> or rather <hi>Plutarch,</hi> ſayes thus.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Empedocles</hi> teacheth, That Monſters are created, if the ſeed be too much, or too little; too much ſpread abroad, or ſeperated, if it be void, or injected by inordinate motion; or becauſe ſomething is added, detracted, tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſited, or inflamed: or if the womb be diſtorted, the Veſſels corrupted, or the formative vertue be deficient, or do abound: theſe things hinder the natural conception, and due operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of nature.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Chap. XI.</hi> Of the unnatural fleſhy Conception in the womb, called Mola.</head>
               <p>THis unnatural Matter ſometimes happens to grow in the wombs of Women, that have no Copulation with men, and cauſeth the Belly to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe,
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:170219:80"/>and all ſignes to appear, as though they were with Child; their Termes ſtaying, the Breaſts grow hard, they loſe their appetite, or ſtomach to meat: their complexion groweth pale, and ſometimes they may feel a ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring about the Matrix, as if they were with Child; yet nevertheleſs, they bear no Child, which have this <hi>mola</hi> ingendred in them: Of this writes <hi>Aetius,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Aetius lib. ult.</note> and <hi>Avicen,</hi> who ſaith, that it is a certain hard ſubſtance, ſometime found to ſpread it ſelf throughout the whole Matrix.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> teacheth, that this <hi>Mola</hi> is nothing elſe,<note place="margin">Lib. <hi>4.</hi> Gen. Hin. Cap. <hi>7.</hi>
                  </note> but a certain peece of fleſh, conceived and ingendred in the womb of a Woman, and he reciteth a ſtory of a certain Woman, that brought forth a lump of fleſh which they called <hi>Mola.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And hereunto <hi>Galen</hi> alſo plainly conſents,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gal.</hi> 14. <hi>uſu part.</hi> 17.14. <hi>Meth.</hi> 13</note> who affirmeth, that this <hi>Mola</hi> is a peece of unprofitable de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd fleſh, which is ingendred in the Womb of a Woman, without the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulation with a man, as a Hen hath Eggs without a Cock.</p>
               <pb n="141" facs="tcp:170219:80"/>
               <p>But now a Queſtion may ariſe, whether the cauſe of this unnatural <hi>Mola,</hi> proceed from too much heat, or too much cold, or too much blood?</p>
               <p>For <hi>Avicen</hi> teacheth,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Avic. fen.</hi> 21.3. <hi>trait.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 18.</note> that beſides the multitude, or ſuperfluity of blood, there is a vehemency of heat, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the blood is concocted, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the fleſh acquires a form.</p>
               <p>But this, <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> ſeems to contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict, who manifeſtly writeth, that the <hi>Mola</hi> is no otherwiſe bred, then of impure, and imperfect concoction; and that it hath its Original from the defect and imbecillity of natural heat, And <hi>Averroes</hi> confirms, that the cauſe is nothing elſe but debility and weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of nature, corruption of digeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and loſſe of the laſt concoction; and certainly, that rude and deformed fleſh, called <hi>Mola</hi> is ingendred of cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities.</p>
               <p>This, groweth in the womb in two kinds, like a peece of fleſh, putrified without form or figure, reſembling ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a peece of ſpongeous blood, wind &amp; water, then right fleſh which hindereth the expelling of the termes,
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:170219:81"/>and being mixed with the natural ſeed, it groweth ſometimes to a hard ſubſtance.</p>
               <p>It is alſo ingendred of ſuperfluous blood, and the concourſe of tough and unconcocted humours, which make the belly ſwell up, as if the Woman were with Child.</p>
               <p>This is an ill accident, and putrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth and ſpoileth the Matrix, breeding there oftentimes Ulcers and Impoſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>humes, Dropſies, unnatural Fluxes, or ſome ſuch like infirmities, bringing death, if it be not well regarded to be prevented.</p>
               <p>The ſighes whereby they that labour with this unnatural Maſſe, may be known from Women with Child, are generally theſe.</p>
               <p>The firſt is motion; for this burthen moveth not as Children do, becauſe there is neither life nor ſenſe in it.</p>
               <p>But it may move by accident, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the motion of the woman, and the ponderouſneſs thereof, but that is no true motion.</p>
               <p>The Belly of Women which labour with this unnatural Maſſe, is harder
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:170219:81"/>then the Belly of women with Child, and will not ſo eaſily move from one place to another, as theirs that be with Child.</p>
               <p>The Woman that hath this <hi>Mola</hi> is alſo more melancholy, then thoſe that are with Child, and their hands and feet more feeble: this Maſſe alſo ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times falleth from one ſide to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
               <p>A Woman with Child at nine moneths end, is delivered thereof; but they go two, 3, or 4 years, ſometimes all their life-time with this burthen. For the cure of this <hi>Mola, Hippocrates</hi> before all others, preſcribes the moſt perfect method.</p>
               <p>The firſt means to be uſed, is clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and purging of the whole body.</p>
               <p>The ſecond is to mollifie, looſen, and open the Veſſels, and ligaments of the Womb, wherewith the <hi>Mola</hi> is bound and faſtned there.</p>
               <p>The third is to ſtir up, and ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then the expulſive faculty, whereby this burden may the more eaſily be expelled from the Womb.</p>
               <p>All Phyſicians do agree, that this
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:170219:82"/>diſeaſe cannot be cured without great difficulty, and ſometimes not at all; yet nevertheleſs, meanes muſt be uſed, and firſt of all purgation, whereby the Belly may be lenified; and amongſt all other Medicines; <hi>Hiera</hi> obtains the chief place; for its molifying and purging quality, the better if it be mixed with Caſſia, as in this manner.</p>
               <p>Take Species of <hi>Hiera ſimplex,</hi> Caſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia new drawn, of each 1 dram; mix them into a Bolus with Sugar.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>A Sirrup for the ſame.</head>
                  <p>Take of <hi>Oximel ſimplex</hi> one Ounce, decoction of Betony, of Motherwort, Mints, Peny Royal, of each 4 drams, mix them together, and make a Sirrup thereof; but before you take it, take this Bolus and Confection follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>A Bolus.</head>
                  <p>Take Conſerve of Maidenhair, two drams Species of Dia calamint, 1 ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, mix them and make a <hi>Bolus</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of to be taken before the Sirrup.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="145" facs="tcp:170219:82"/>
                  <head>A Confection for the ſame.</head>
                  <p>Take Species Diambre, Diacalam<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> of each half a dram, Sugar 2 Ounces; make a Confection thereof, with White-wine, and take it before the Sirrup.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>An excellent potion for this Diſeaſe.</head>
                  <p>Take Elect Diaphen, Hiera, Diacol, of each half a dram, Mel. Roſ. Sol. 4. drams, decoction of Betony, of Mugwort, of each a ſufficient quanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, to make a potion: let the Patient in this Diſeaſe, abſtain from cold, and moyſt meats, and uſe this potion fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, which mollifies the Maſſe, or Mola, and expels the humors that cauſe, or increaſe it. Take St. <hi>Johns</hi> Wort, Savin, Roſemary, Field Mints, Lovag, Mugwort, Peny Royal, Mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, of each one handful; Fennel, Squi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, Parſley ſeed, Calmus, Galingale, of each 1 dram, Horſ-radiſh Roots, 4 Ounces; boyl them all together in a good quantity of water, to make a
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:170219:83"/>potion, and take thereof every day 3. or 4. Ounces, mixing therewith about a quarter of an Ounce of this Trochis following.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>A Trochis.</head>
                  <p>Take Cynamon, Mirrhe, of each 2. drams and a half, Rue, Savin, Field Mints, Peny Royal, Madder, Sagape<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num, Opopanacum, of each, 1 dram; Cardamum, Juniper-wood, Roſema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, of each, 1 dram &amp; a half: dry them all to powder, &amp; make Troches there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and uſe it, as above is directed.</p>
                  <p>Alſo for this Diſeaſe, this follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is a cheap and ready Medicine.</p>
                  <p>Take 3 Ounces of warm Fetherfew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>water, every morning faſting, for two moneths together, and faſt 4 houres after it. And every fourth day during the time ſhe drinketh the water, let her take one of theſe Pills following.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Pills for the Mola.</head>
                  <p>Take Galbanum, 1 quarter of an Ounce, Flowers of Mugwort, St. <hi>Johns</hi>
                     <pb n="147" facs="tcp:170219:83"/>wort, Aſſarabacca, of each 1 ſcruple, diſſolve the Galbanum in good wine, and make thereof 6 Pills, of a dram, and take one at a time, in 4 dayes, as before is directed.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>A Bath for the ſame.</head>
                  <p>Take Mugwort, Camomile, Dill, Holly-hock Roots, Mallowes, of each one handful; Linſeed, Fenegreek, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſeed, Fennel-ſeed, of each one dram; make a decoction thereof in common water for a Bath, and let the Woman ſit hot in it, up to her breaſts; and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter uſe this Oyntment for the ſame purpoſe.</p>
                  <p>Take juyce of Holli-hocks, 2 Oun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, Gooſgreaſe, Hens greaſe, of each, one Ounce; Oyl of ſweet Almonds, of white Lillies, of each half an ounce, mixe them to an Oyntment, and therewith annoint all the external parts againſt the fire.</p>
                  <p>Inwardly, let her alſo take Dia ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamint, Trochis of Mirrhe, and in a word, whatſoever is good to provoke
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:170219:84"/>the termes, and to drive forth the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundide, and expell a dead Child, the ſame is effectual for this Diſeaſe; of which ſhall be ſpoken in the enſuing diſcourſe, of hard Labours.</p>
                  <p>We have now at large, written of all ſpecial accidents and infirmities, incident to the womb, and parts of generation, and given perfect di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections for remedies for the ſame: yet nevertheleſs, though the humane ſeed may be received and contained, yet a miſchance may follow, or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe a weak and feeble fruit, that it cannot come to perfection; and at laſt, a difficult and hard labour, are many if not moſt of the Daughters of <hi>Eve</hi> ſubject to, whereby oft-times, their lives are in danger thereby, if not quite loſt, with the fruit and all: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore concerning theſe infirmities, and what belongs to fruit-bearing Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and their delivery, is the inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded ſubject of the ſubſequent part of this Book, and firſt, of the debility, or weakneſs of the child in its Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers womb.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <pb n="149" facs="tcp:170219:84"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> XII. Of the weakneſs of Children in the Womb.</head>
               <p>SUch is the frailty of humane na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, that the Child is ſubject to ſickneſs, even in his Mothers womb; no great marvel then, if men are all their lives encumbred with caſualties, when they begin with them, even be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they have a viſible being; the ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Children in the womb, not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing obvious to the eye, is the more difficult to finde out; but the ſignes to know it are theſe,</p>
               <p>If the Woman have her termes much, being with Child, it muſt argue debility of the Child, becauſe his nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhment and ſuſtenance is taken away from him.</p>
               <p>If Milk flow from Women with Child, its evident the Child is weak, and not ſtrong enough to draw his nouriſhment to him.</p>
               <pb n="150" facs="tcp:170219:85"/>
               <p>If a Woman with Child be af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted with a ſtrong and violent looſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, there is great danger of a miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chance.</p>
               <p>But the ſtrength or weakneſs of the Child, depends on heat and cold, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der which are comprehended all acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents whatſoever.</p>
               <p>If the Child be weak through im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moderate heat, and dryeth, then the remedy is to purge the Mother of Choler; for which this following is a convenient Medicine.</p>
               <p>Take Conſerve of Prunes, half an Ounce, three Ounces of whay, of milk, give it her in the morning, and let her faſt 5 houres after it.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
                  <p>Take Caſſia extracted out of the Cane one Ounce, and put to it 4 Oun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Sorrel-water, or Barley-water, and give it in like manner as the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
                  <p>Another ſafe, but ſtronger Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine, both for the Mother and the Child, is this following.</p>
                  <pb n="151" facs="tcp:170219:85"/>
                  <p>Take 2 Ounces of Manna, and 3. or 4. Ounces of Whay, mixed with it, and uſe it as the other.</p>
                  <p>For the ſame, you may alſo ſteep in the ſame quantity of Whay, a dram of Rubarb one night, and ſtrain it out well; or, if you will, take half a dram of Rubarb in powder in ſome whay.</p>
                  <p>Let the Woman uſe ſuch dyet, as is cooling, and moyſtning, as Barley-water, Lettice, and uſe Verjuice, and juyce of Lemons with her meat: En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dive water, &amp; Syrrup of Roſes, &amp; En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dive, &amp; ſuccoury water, are good in this caſe. Forbear all things, which provoke vomiting, or which force U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine or blood.</p>
                  <p>Let the Woman 3 or 4 times every day, cool and quench her thirſt with Barley-water, having half an Ounce of Syrrup of leaves mixt with it.</p>
                  <p>An external Medicine for this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe, if you feel great heat to abound, may be this.</p>
                  <p>Take Citron water, Violet water, of each 6. Ounces, Sorrel-water, 12. Ounces, Red Sanders, burnt Ivory, Sorrel ſeed, of each one ſcruple, Saf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fron,
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:170219:86"/>half a ſcruple, Vinegar 3 ſpoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuls, mix them all together, and wet a Linnen Cloth in it, and lay it on the privities, and on the ſmall of the back.</p>
                  <p>Take alſo one Ounce of Pompeon Peels, Oyl of Roſes, Oyl of Water-Lillies, of each one Ounce and a half, Houſleek one Ounce, temper them all together, and annoint the back and privities therewith 3. or 4. times a day.</p>
                  <p>But if the cauſe of weakneſs, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility of the Child in its Mothers Womb, proceed from cold and moyſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, then are contrary medicines to be uſed; of which theſe following are approved.</p>
                  <p>Take Bugloſſe water, Saffron ſeeds, Agarins, Hermodactils, of each 1 ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, Cynamon, Ginger, Roſes, Cori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander prepared, of each 4 grains, ſteep them one night in the Bugloſſe water, then ſtrain it, and drink it in the morning faſting.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="153" facs="tcp:170219:86"/>
                  <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
                  <p>Take Fetherſew-water, Balm wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, of each one Ounce and a half, <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedicta laxativa</hi> one Ounce, Sugar half an Ounce, mix them, and infuſe them together one night, then ſtrain it out, and uſe it as the other.</p>
                  <p>Have a care to uſe a good order of Dyet, and ſuch things as warm and dry; boyl Sage, Mints, and Roſemary in her Portage, and uſe to drink red Wine with ſteeled water.</p>
                  <p>To mundifie and cleanſe the bad hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours, this Medicine following is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry good.</p>
                  <p>Take juyce of Mints 4 Ounces, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garick one dram, Ginger, Roſes, of each 4 grains; Manna half an Ounce, ſteep the Agarick in the juyce of Mints a dayes, and nights; then put the Manna, Roſes, and Ginger to it, let it ſtand a while, and dry againſt the fire, and make it into Pills, and take them.</p>
                  <p>Uſe this oftentimes; for they gent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:170219:87"/>purge and dry up the warty humors without pain or anguiſh.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>A Plaiſter to remedy the corrupt humours.</head>
                  <p>Take Roſes, Cipers Nuts, burnt I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vory, Sandaraca, of each 1 dram, Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen 3 Ounces; boyl the Roſen in red Vinegar, till the Vinegar be conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, then mix the other things with it, and make 2 Plaiſters of it, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply one to the back, and the other to the womb.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Another excellent good Plaiſter to ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then Women with Child, that do not uſe to go out half their times.</head>
                  <p>Take Oyl of Quinces, Oyl of Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, Oyl of Mints, of each 1 ounce and a half, Comphrey, Blood-ſtone, red Coral, Sandaraca, Date-ſtones burnt, of each 1 dram, mix it with a ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent quantity of Wax, to make a Salve thereof; and with this annoint the Kidneys and Mother.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <pb n="155" facs="tcp:170219:87"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Chap. XIII.</hi> Of Miſchances, and to prevent the ſame.</head>
               <p>IT oftentimes comes to paſſe with women with child, as with the fruit upon a Tree; which being young and tender, hangs on brittle ſtalks, and is eaſily blown off with every wind; nay, when it is come to its full growth, and is ſtronger, ſometimes forcible winds bruiſes, or blowes, cauſe them to fall off; but when they come to their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect time of ripeneſs, they fall of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
               <p>So it is in this occult operation of nature, many accidents ſometimes happen to the Tree, which bring the fruit to an untimely birth; and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes, not without peril of the Womans life, nature being dead in the Child, that it cannot help it ſelf; whereas in thoſe that are alive, &amp; of their full time, nature helps forward the birth, the Infant it ſelf ſtriving to finde a way into the World.</p>
               <pb n="156" facs="tcp:170219:88"/>
               <p>This may be perceived by the breaſts; for if they be ſmall, weak, and ſlack in Women with Child, then is a miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chance to be expected; for then the Child wants nouriſhment, and pines, and dies; alſo impatiency, or vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent motion, many times breaks the ſecundine, and then the fruit falls a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way.</p>
               <p>Signes of a miſchance approaching, are alſo pains of the Back-bone, Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and privities: to prevent which, let the Woman with Child, beware ſharp and bitter meats, and drinks; avoid much anger and violent motion, and exerciſe; uſe oftentimes to drink red Wine, and keep the body ſoluble: To do which, if need require, ſhe may uſe the decoction of Mallowes, Mercu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and ſtew'd Prumes; forbear Cly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, and ſtrong Medicines; but if there be any great obſtruction in the body, then let her eat Caſſia out of the Pipes, or Caſſia new extracted; eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, if the neck of the matrix have any iſſue, or overmuch moyſture, then uſe a little Rubarb in powder, mixed with the Caſſia, which without trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:170219:88"/>or danger, doth cleanſe Flegme, and Choler.</p>
               <p>For to ſtay the ſlipperineſs of the Matrix, take Pomegranate Pills, and pound them to powder groſly, and boyl them in Oyl of Lillies, and inject the ſame into the Matrix.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>A Peſſary excellent good for the ſame.</head>
                  <p>Take Maſtick, Mirrhe, Gallia Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cata, of each half a dram; mix them with one ounce of Gooſ-greaſe, &amp; role it up in Sheeps Wooll, and put it up into the place.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>An Oyntment to ſtrengthen Women with Child.</head>
                  <p>Take Cypreſs Nuts, Galls, Myrtle-ſeed Juyce of Sloes, Hypociſtis, of each half a dram, Blood ſtone, Amber, Dragons blood, Bolus, of each one dram and a half, reffuſe of Iron, half an ounce, innermoſt Peels of Cheſnuts, one ounce: decoct the reffuſe of Iron a good while in Vinegar, then beat them all together in a Morter, to an Oynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, with 3 or 4 whites of Eggs, and annoint the belly therewith, 4 times a day.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="158" facs="tcp:170219:89"/>
                  <head>Another Oyntment for the ſame.</head>
                  <p>Take Oyl of Nuts 4 Ounces, Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes greaſe 1 ounce &amp; a half, Cypres Nuts, Maſtick, of each 1 dram and an half, boyl them together gently, the ſpace of five houres, and therewith annoint the Matrix, Womb, and Reins of the Back.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>A Plaiſter for the ſame.</head>
                  <p>Take Dragagant, Gum, Bdellium, of each 1 quarter of an oun. Juyce of Sloes Frankincenſe, Hypociſtis, Sandaraca, of each one dram, Bolus, Dragons blood, of each 1 quarter of an ounce, wax, half an Ounce, Paper glew 2 ounces: diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve the glew in red Wine-Vinegar, then temper them all together into a Plaiſter, and apply it to the womb and privities.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>For an Ague in Women with Child.</head>
                  <p>Take Barley meal, Juyce of Sloes, and Houſleek, what quantity you ſee convenient, temper it with Vinegar, and lay it upon the belly, uſe it often: this defends the Child from all acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents of an Ague.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="159" facs="tcp:170219:89"/>
                  <head>To prevent miſcarriage through wind.</head>
                  <p>Boil Cominſeed in water, and take three or four ſpoonfuls of that water, with a dram of Mithridate, twice a week.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Chap. XIIII.</hi> To expell and drive out the dead Childe.</head>
               <p>FOr the expulſion or delivery of a child that is dead, the ſame Mede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines that are preſcribed to drive forth the unnaturall excrement, called, Mola, and to provoke the Terms, are good to be uſed.</p>
               <p>But firſt be ſure that the child is dead, and do not go about to expel a live Child inſtead of a dead one, which may be known by theſe ſignes. If the Child be dead in the Womb, then
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:170219:90"/>doth the woman feel great pain in the optick Nerves of her Eys, and behind the Neck, and on the Back-bone, with great pain and anguiſh in her lower parts. And the Burden alwaies falls to that ſide ſhe lies on, becauſe the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaments of the Secundine, have no power to hold it in one place; the thickneſs of the upper part of the Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſinks down, and the woman feels much pain, and cold about the neck of the Matrix.</p>
               <p>Alſo, if one hold a warm hand long upon the Belly, and feel no ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, the Child is dead; theſe are ſigns the Child is dead, before it come to putrefaction.</p>
               <p>But when it beginneth to ſtinke and putrifie, which will be in three daies ſpace after it is dead; the woman will have a ſtinking breath, ſtinking cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption iſſues from the Matrix, and pieces of ſtinking fleſh, will at laſt be expelled from the Womb: then means is to be uſed to clenſe the Womb of the dead Child, and to preſerve and ſtrengthen the heart from the corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of filthy ſents aſcending to it,
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:170219:90"/>which may be done, by this powder following.</p>
               <p>Take white Diplamus, one dram and a half; Citron peels and ſeeds, each half a dram; Pearls prepared, four ſcruples; Coriander prepared, a ſcruple; Roſes, two ſcruples; Sugar, two ounces and a half; make them all to fine powder, and take thereof about a quarter of an ounce at once in drink.</p>
               <p>Juice of Vervaine and Hyſop drunk in Wine, is good to expel the dead Child.</p>
               <p>The innermoſt skins of the Maws of Hens, and Capons waſhed in Wine, and then dryed to powder; and give thereof a dram in Wine, broth, or Roſe water, is good to expell a dead Child, and the Secundine.</p>
               <p>For the ſame, take Betony and Rue, of each a handful; juyce of Salomons ſeal, an ounce; boyl it well in a pint of white Wine, and ſtrain it, and give her to drink.</p>
               <p>Linſeed is very good for the ſame, either to drink the decoction, or Bathe therein.</p>
               <pb n="162" facs="tcp:170219:91"/>
               <p>Alſo, take Mirth the quantity of a Hazle-nut ſtamped, &amp; taken in Wine; or Mugwort water, is good for the ſame.</p>
               <p>For women that are ſtrong; take about a ſpoonful of the juyce of Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, with wine or Honey.</p>
               <p>If a woman chance to miſcarry through a fright, or ſome ſuch acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent: then take a Crab and ſtamp it, and wring out the juyce, and drink it with water of Mugwort.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Pills to expel a dead Child.</head>
                  <p>Take Trochis of Mirth, one ſcruple; Galbanum, half a ſcruple: make five Pills thereof, with Penny-royal wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
                  <p>Take of the fruit of the Savine tree, one quarter of an ounce; Aſſa foetida, Ammoniacum, Madder, of each half a dram; make 11. Pills hereof, and take one at a time three times a day, morning, night and at four of the clock in the afternoone.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="163" facs="tcp:170219:91"/>
                  <head>A Fume to expel the dead Child.</head>
                  <p>Take ſome ſhavings of an Aſſes hoof, or of a Horſes, if you cannot get the other, and make a fume thereof, and let the woman ſit over it.</p>
                  <p>Baſilium is good for the ſame to be uſed in like manner, and ſo is likewiſe the fume of Laudanum, and Galba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>A Bath to expel a dead Child.</head>
                  <p>Take ten handfuls of Mints, and boyl them well in a ſufficient quantity of water, and let the woman ſit there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in up to the middle.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <pb n="164" facs="tcp:170219:92"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Chap. XV.</hi> Of hard Labour, and means to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure eaſie Delivery.</head>
               <p>THat all women ſhould bear chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren with pain and ſorrow, was a puniſhment inflicted on them by God, for the diſobedience of the firſt Mother; for which cauſe they under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go more anguiſh, and peril in bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forth, then any other Creatures.</p>
               <p>Yet nevertheleſs, there may be ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny cauſes, and accidents which render the delivery more dangerous and dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult in ſome then in others; for which our purpoſe is here, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe ſome remedies.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>A moſt excellent Plaiſter to ſtrengthen women with child, to wear all the time they be with child,</head>
                  <p>Take oyl Olive, two pound &amp; four ounces; red Lead, one pound; Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh Sope, twelve ounces; Incorpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:170219:92"/>them altogether in an earthen pot, and when the Sope cometh up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, put it upon a ſmall fire of coals: and continue it an hour and a half, ſtirring it with an Iron or ſtick; then drop a drop of it upon a trencher, if it cleave not, it is enough: ſpread it on cloths, or lay it on a board till it cools, then make it up into Rolls; it will laſt twenty years, the older, the better; and when you have occaſion to uſe it, for this purpoſe, ſpread a Plaiſter of it, and apply it to the Back<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> and when you have tryed it, you will give me thanks for it; It is likewiſe good for the bloody Flux, Running of the Reins, or any weakneſs in the Back, for any bruiſe, to draw out a Thorn out of the fleſh, and eaſeth Cornes, and is good for a ſtrain, and for the Head-ach, being applyed to the Temples.</p>
                  <p>But to proceed, when the woman with child, begins to draw near her time; then let her uſe ſuch meats and drinks as nouriſh well, but uſe no ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe of either; but eſpecially let her take care to keep her Body ſoluble,
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:170219:93"/>for which, and alſo to prepare the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy for an eaſy delivery, this Bath is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry good to be uſed.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>A Bath good for women with Child when they draw near their time, to procure eaſie delivery.</head>
                  <p>Take Holly-hock roots and leaves, two handfuls, Mallows, Betony, of each one handful; Mugwort, Marjo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram, Mints, Camomile, of each half a handful; Linſeed two handfuls; bruiſe the Linſeed groſly, and put that toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the hearbs into two bags, and boyl them well in water, enough to make a Bath for the woman to ſit in up to the Navel when it is warm; and let her ſit upon one bag, and hold the other upon her Navel; And after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, uſe to annoint the Belly, Back, and privities with this Salve follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, being warmed.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>A preparative Salve to cauſe eaſy deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very in Child bearing women.</head>
                  <p>Take oyl of ſweet Almonds, of
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:170219:93"/>Lillies, Violets, of each-half an ounce; Linſeed, Holly-hock roots, Fenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greek, Butter, Hens greaſe of each one quarter of an ounce; Quince kernels, Dragagant, of each an ounce: ſtamp the ſeeds ſmall, and ſlice the roots, and boyl them all together in rain water; then take out the Muſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage, and temper the ſame with the oyl; then let the powned Dragagant and Hens greaſe boyl ſo long, till the Muſcilage, be conſumed: then make thereof a Salve, and annoint there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with as before is directed.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Another Ointment for the ſame.</head>
                  <p>Take oyl of ſweet Almonds, of Lil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, of Violets, each half an ounce: Hens greaſe, Ducks greaſe three drams: mix them together with Wax, as much as is needful to make a Salve, and uſe it as the other.</p>
                  <p>With any of theſe Salves, a woman is to be annointed about the parts be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore mentioned, every day the ſpace of five or ſix weeks before her time.</p>
                  <p>Now when the time of Labour is
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:170219:94"/>come, then uſe any of theſe things which follow, as the cauſe requires; but above all things, this powder fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing is moſt effectual.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>An excellent Powder for women in tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel with Child-bearing.</head>
                  <p>Take Dittany of Crete, Penny-roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, Ariſtolochia round, each half a ſcruple: Cinamon, Saffron, of each twelve grains: Let them be all beaten into a fine powder, and given in Wine or ſome convenient decoction, as the decoction of red Peaſe, of Penny-royal, or of Parſley.</p>
                  <p>For outward Medecines, there be many things uſed to be held to the privities, as, Egrimony with the roots to be held to the Matrix, and immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately after the birth to be thrown away, leſt it draw down the Matrix: alſo Henbane roots, Polypody roots, &amp; Biſtorta, are very good for the ſame.</p>
                  <p>Alſo, take Polypody roots and Mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows of each a handful, and a hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful of Mugwort: bruiſe them ſmall, and boyl them well, and apply it mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derately warm upon the Matrix, and
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:170219:94"/>after the Delivery, immediately take it away.</p>
                  <p>Some uſe to tie a Snakes skin about the Thigh; but what vertue there is in that, they know that have tryed it.</p>
                  <p>Bay-berries beat, and applyed to the Navel, are good to further the Birth; but inwardly this Powder is commended.</p>
                  <p>Take Cinamon, Mirrh, of each half a dram; make them into powder, and give it with a little White-wine,</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
                  <p>Take Cinamon, one dram: Saffron, half a dram: Caſſia wood, Caſſia pipes, of each two ſcruples: ſcrape off the uttermoſt black bark from the Caſſia Pipes, and make it all into fine pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and give it four or five times in the decoction of red Peaſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Pills for the ſame.</head>
                  <p>Take Mirrh, Bever-cod, red Storax, of each half a ſcruple: Cinamon, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin, of each half a ſcruple; make it
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:170219:95"/>into Pills, with the decoction of red Peaſe, and ſo give it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
                  <p>Take Mirth, Coſtus, red Storax, of each half a dram: Ammoniacum, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin, of each half a dram; beat them very ſmall, and give it in the decoction of red Peaſe: uſe it three or four times.</p>
                  <p>If the throws be too weak, or do not continue, let all ſweet ſavours as Musk, or the like, be kept from the woman in labour; for that hinders throwes, and holds back the Birth. But to forward the Birth, make this decoction.</p>
                  <p>Take Betony, three handfulls: Mug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wort, one handful; Camomile Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny-royal, Hyſop; of each one handful: Linſeeds two handfuls: bruiſe the Linſeed groſsly, and cut the hearbs ſmall, and put them all in a bag, and boyl it well in Wine and water: with this decoction foment the Matrix, five or ſix times with a ſpunge, and then annoint the place with the oyl of Wall-flowers; even to the Neck of
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:170219:95"/>the Mother, if it can be done with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniency.</p>
                  <p>But if this help not, then give her a good draught of this Potion following every two hours.</p>
                  <p>Take Mugwort, Penny-royal, Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſop, of each half a handful; Betony one handful: boyl all theſe in a pint and a half of Reniſh Wine till the fourth part be conſumed, ſtrain it our and put to it half a dram of Saffron, and amongſt each draught put half a dram of one of the powders before mentioned.</p>
                  <p>Alſo, this following is very good to quickn the throwes,</p>
                  <p>Take half a dram of beaten Amber, and give it in water of Lillies, or in the decoction of red Peaſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>An excellent Medicine to procure ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie delivery in women.</head>
                  <p>Take Pippins, cut them in thin ſli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and fry them with oyl of ſweet Almonds, and eat thereof in the morning and at four a clock in the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternoon, uſe it conſtantly a matter of
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:170219:96"/>five or ſix weeks before your time, till you are brought to bed: and mix ſome oyl of ſweet Almonds and Sper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma coeti together, and annoint the Belly, and Matrix once every day therewith warm, or oftner if you can conveniently.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
                  <p>Take Hyſop, Vervaine, Betony, of each one handful: ſtamp them ſmall, and ſtrain them in good ſtale Ale, and let the Patient drink a good draught thereof, it gives preſent help.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>To expel the Secundine or after-Birth.</head>
                  <p>The Secundine or after-Birth, is that skin or caule wherein the child is for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med and wrapped up till the time it break forth to the Birth, &amp; doth, or at leaſt ought to come away, immediatly after the Birth of the child.</p>
                  <p>But ſometimes it remains behind, and cauſeth great peril to the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, and many ill accidents, as Agues, ſtinking breath, pain of the Head,
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:170219:96"/>Swooning, and the like, if it be not expelled.</p>
                  <p>It commonly remains behind when the woman hath had very hard labour, and is thereby grown ſo weak and fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that nature hath not ſtrength enough to drive it forth: ſhe muſt therefore have ſome comfortable things given her to ſtrengthen and comfort her heart, as, Dia marga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iton, and Manus Chriſti; 'then let her reſt a little, and if the Secondine do not follow, annoint the Belly and parts adjacent, with oyl of Lillies, and oyl of Elder flowers, and uſe ſuch things as are directed for the delivery of a dead child; as, Corn flowers given in Lilly water: alſo Garlick, half an egg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhell full of the juyce thereof, given in honeyed water, doth expel the dead child, and after-birth as before hath been preſcribed.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>To eaſe the After-throws.</head>
                  <p>Take Spikenard and Squinant, of each one quarter of an ounce: boyl them together in a good quantity of
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:170219:97"/>Mugwort water, till half be conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, and drink thereof two or three times.</p>
                  <p>Alſo to aſſwage the pain, make a Cawdle with Malmſey, or ſome other good Wine, and put therein yolks of Eggs and Cinamon, and ſo give it. For the fame, take Triphes à magna, half an ounce: Saffron half a dram: Mace a ſcruple; and give this at twice, in warm Wine.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>To ſtay the exceſſive flood after the Birth.</head>
                  <p>The Remedies before preſcribed for the aſſwaging of the exceſſive Flux of the Terms in women, be alſo very good for this Diſeaſe, and for all Women in Child-bed; yet neve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe take this Confection follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="175" facs="tcp:170219:97"/>
                  <head>A Confection for an exceſsive flood in Women lying in Child-bed.</head>
                  <p>Take Conſerve of Piony one Ounce, Conſerve of Roſes one ounce, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve of Burrage, Bugios, Balm of each half an ounce, prepared Bolus half a dram, prepared Pearls 1 dram, Cyna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon 1 dram and a half, mix them all together, and make a Confection thereof.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>For the ſame, uſe this Powder following.</head>
                  <p>Take Bolus prepared, Pearls, of each one dram; ſealed Earth 2 ſcruples, Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentil half a dram, Shepheards Purſe 1 ſcruple, Species <hi>de gemmis frigidis</hi> 1 dram and a half, Roſes, Corral, San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, of each one ſcruple, Cynamon 2. ſcruples and a half, Sugar 3 Ounces, mix them all well together, and take it with Hen-broth.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="176" facs="tcp:170219:98"/>
                  <head>Lozinges very effectual for the ſame.</head>
                  <p>Take Blood-ſtone 1 dram and a half, red Coral one dram, Tormentil, Tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chis de Sodio, of each half a dram; ſcraped Ivory, burnt Hartshorn of each 1 ſcruple, Pearls prepared 4 ſcruples, fine Bolus 2. ſcruples, Shepheards purſe, red Sanders, of each a ſcruple, Cynamon 1 dram, Sugar ſix ounces; waſh the Blood-ſtone in Plantain-wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and make a Powder, or Lozinges thereof.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Chap. XVI.</hi> Of the ſuperfluity of Milk; and other accidents happening after the Birth.</head>
               <p>EXceſſive abounding of the milk, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a Woman is delivered, if it flow more than the Child can grow, there oftentimes enſues Impoſthumes, and other Inflammations and diſtempers
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:170219:98"/>in the breaſts; for Remedies where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, uſe theſe preſcriptions following.</p>
               <p>The Patient muſt eat and drink but moderately, and avoid all ſuch things as ingender much blood, &amp; uſe means to dry and take away the ſuperfluous blood, as Rue and wild Rue, with the ſeeds Baſil, and ſtampt together, if one take every day a quarter of an ounce, the ſame is very good to dry up the milk.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>To dry up the milk.</head>
                  <p>Take Roſen a good quantity, and temper it with Cream, and lay it luke-warm over the breaſts.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>For the ſame.</head>
                  <p>Take 8 ounces of Honey, and two pints of water, boyl them well toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and ſcum it, and dip therein a threefold Cloth, and lay it on the breaſts, and when it is cold, renew it again.</p>
                  <pb n="178" facs="tcp:170219:99"/>
                  <p>Alſo for the ſame, take one dram of Saffron, and 8 ounces of Malmſey, wet a Cloth therein, and lay it on the breaſts as aforeſaid.</p>
                  <p>Alſo take Garden Mints, ſtamp them, and mix them with Oyl of Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and uſe it as the other.</p>
                  <p>For a Plaiſter to dry up the milk, take bean meal, oyl of Roſes, and red Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>negar, a ſufficient quantity to make a Plaiſter, and apply it to the breaſts.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>For clotted, or congealed milk in the Breaſts.</head>
                  <p>Let Women keep ſobriety in eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and drinking, and uſe moyſt meats, that may ingender ſubtile milk; Mints, Saffron, and Cynamon, is good to be uſed in their meats.</p>
                  <p>Take grated bread, new milk, and Oyl of Roſes, of each a like quantity, ſeeth them together to a pap, and lay it warm upon the breaſts:</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="179" facs="tcp:170219:99"/>
                  <head>For congealed milk, and pain in the Breſts.</head>
                  <p>Take Cork and burn it to aſhes, and temper it with oyl of Roſes, and a little Vinegar, and therewith annoint the breaſt.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>A Salve to diſſolve congealed milk in the Breaſts.</head>
                  <p>Take Deares Suet 3 quarters of an oun: liquid Styrax 1 oun: Wormwood, Cummin, Dill-ſeeds, of each 1 ounce; oyl of Wormwood, Ducks greaſe, of each 1 ounce and an half, Saffron one ſcruple, make an oyntment or Plaiſter hereof, and apply it to the breaſts.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>For milk congealed with Inflammation in the breaſts.</head>
                  <p>Take a quantity of the muſcilage of Fleawort, Fenegreek, and Purſlain ſeeds, of each a like; and make an oynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment thereof wieh wax, and annoint the breaſts therewith.</p>
                  <pb n="180" facs="tcp:170219:100"/>
                  <p>Alſo for the ſame, take Chickweed, and lay it warm upon the breaſts.</p>
                  <p>Alſo beat oyl of Roſes, and Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar of Roſes together, and lay it on the breaſts.</p>
                  <p>If the Woman hath taken ſome ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme cold, then take this following, eſpecially, if there be an Ague with it, take Camomile, Melilot, Fennel ſeeds, Anniſeeds, Dill ſeeds, Fenegreek Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeds, Southernwood, Ginger, Bazil, beat them together, and with oyl of Camomile, make a Plaiſter of it, and apply it to the breaſts.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>A good Plaiſter to diſſolve hard knots in the breaſt.</head>
                  <p>Take Crums of white bread, Barley meal; Muſtard-ſeeds, Fennel, and Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hocks roſted under the aſhes, of each a like quantity, pound them all well together, and make a Plaiſter thereof, with oyl of Camomile, and apply it warm to the breaſts.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="181" facs="tcp:170219:100"/>
                  <head>For hardneſs, and inflammation in the breaſts through congealed milk, A Pultis.</head>
                  <p>Take flowers of Mallowes, Violets, Celendine, Daiſies, Cinquefoil, of each 1 handful, boyl them together in two quarts of water, till it come to a pint; then ſtrain it, and mingle it with Wheaten meal, to the thickneſs of pap, then put to it Hens greaſe or Hogs Lard, and boyl it again to a Pultis, ſpread it on a Cloth, about the thick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of a finger, and lay it morning and evening, upon an inflamed ſore breaſt.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
                  <p>Take Bean meale, Mints in Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, each 3 quarters of an ounce, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared Coriander, Peaſe meal, of each 1 dram; Roſes half a dram, freſh but<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter 2 ounces, Muſcilage of Linſeed one ounce, Muſcilage of Fenegreek 3 quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of an ounce, Sheeps Suet, Ducks greaſe, of each 1 ounce, oyl of Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentine
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:170219:101"/>half an ounce, Saffron three grains, temper them all together to a ſalve or oyntment, and lay it upon the breaſts.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>For Tumors, or ſwelling of the breaſt.</head>
                  <p>Take Purſlain Plantain, of each one handful, Camomile, Melilot, of each one ounce, Barley meal 4 ounces, ſtamp the Herbs in a morter, to a pap, and then incorporate therewith, oyl of Violets and Roſes, enough to make it a ſalve, and lay it on the ſore breſts.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Another Medicine for ſwelling in the breaſts, much profitable and eaſie to be had.</head>
                  <p>Take a good quantity of Peach leaves, and Rue, and ſtamp them ſmall, and boyl them in water to a Pultis, and lay it on the grieved place, this will ripen the Impoſthume, and eaſe the pain.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="183" facs="tcp:170219:101"/>
                  <head>A Plaiſter for the ſame.</head>
                  <p>Take Plantain, Mallowes, of each one handful, Houſleek 6 handfuls, boyl them together, till they come to be like grout, then ſtrain it, and adde thereunto, Oyl of Roſes 3 ounces, Camomile, Melilot, both beaten, of each an ounce, Barley meal 4 ounces, Bdellium 1 quarter of an ounce, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve the Bdellium in Vineger, and then boyl them all together, to the thickneſs of a Plaiſter, and ſpread it on a Cloth, and apply it to the grieved place.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>For Impoſtumations in the breaſt.</head>
                  <p>Impoſtumations do breed often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times likewiſe in the breaſts, through the congealing of the milk, and ill hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours, ſetling and putrifying there, bringing with them the Canker, Gan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grene, and ſuch like griefs, to the great anguiſh and miſery of the Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, if not to death, by reaſon of the tenderneſs of the place. And many
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:170219:102"/>times it happens, by reaſon of an ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of their termes, which turns our cauſe of the ſuperfluous blood thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: And therefore, if when there happens any ſwelling, or anguiſh in the breaſts in this caſe, if the termes be ſtopt, uſe all means poſſible to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke them ſpeedily, if you mean to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate the ſwelling and pain; and if the ſwelling increaſe, then the Liver vein muſt be opened, or the median. And afterwards take oyl of Roſes, and Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neger, and ſeeth a little Camomile therein; and then dip a Cloth in it, and lay it on the breaſts, four times a day, refreſhing it.</p>
                  <p>If the Impoſtumation in the breaſts be cauſed of ſuperfluity of blood, the ſign to know it is, it cauſeth great pain in the breaſt, redneſs and much beating.</p>
                  <p>If it proceed from Choler, then is the pain more raging, and the breſt redder, and yellowiſh, with greater Agues, and the Inflammation is hot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then that which proceeds of blood.</p>
                  <pb n="185" facs="tcp:170219:102"/>
                  <p>If Flegme be the ingendring cauſe thereof, then the Tumor is but ſmall, the breaſt white, the pain moderate, and no Ague with it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>An excellent Plaiſter to conſume and cleanſe all ſwellings of the breasts; and alſo of other members.</head>
                  <p>Take clarified Honey 6 ounces, Barley meal, 3 ounces and a half, two yolks of Eggs, Mirrhe, Sarcocolla, of each half a dram, Honey of Roſes 4. ounces, oyl of Roſes 3. ounces: pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that which is to be powdered, and boyl the Honey and the meal toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, till it be thick, and then ſtir the yolks of Eggs amongſt it, and the other things; and ſo make a Plaiſter of it, and apply it to the grieved place.</p>
                  <p>When the Tumor or ſwelling comes to maturity, and breaks, then cleanſe it with this Salve.</p>
                  <pb n="86" facs="tcp:170219:103"/>
                  <p>Take Honey, the juyce of Smal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage, yolks of Eggs, and Turpentine, of each a ſufficient quantity, and make a Salve thereof, and ſo apply it.</p>
                  <p>Or elſe uſe this Salve following, with a tent of Lint.</p>
                  <p>Take Wheat-meal, 3 quarters of an ounce, clarified Honey, and juyce of Smallage, of each an ounce, mix them all into a Salve, and uſe them as hath been directed: this is good to be uſed with a tent, to cleanſe any ſore Fiſtula, or Carbuncle.</p>
                  <p>But if in caſe the Tumor, as many times it unhappily doth, grow to a Canker, or Fiſtula, then muſt orher means be uſed, to prevent the eating, or ſpreading thereof: the Patient muſt be purged of melancholy humours, and avoid ſuch things as ingender Choler and melancholy, and to ſeek to prevent the increaſe of the ſame; for which this drink following, is very effectual.</p>
                  <p>Take Time, 1 quarter of an ounce, Polipody, Sene, each 1 dram, Violets, Seeds of Gourds, Cucumbers, Pom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peons, each 1 dram and a half, Cyna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:170219:103"/>Rapeſeed, of each 1 ſcruple, Hops 1 ounce, boyl them all together in 8. ounces of water till half be conſumed, then ſtrain it, and take one ounce of this decoction, in 3 ounces of whay, of Goats milk, and faſt 6 houres after it.</p>
                  <p>Then uſe outwardly this Plaiſter following.</p>
                  <p>Take Fenegreek, Barley meal, of each two Ounces, Mallows 3. hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuls, Houſleek 8 handfuls, Oyl of Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes 6 ounces: bray the Oyl of Roſes in a Leaden Morter, with a Leaden Peſtle, and ſeeth the Herbs in wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y, till they be ſo tender, you may beat them to a pap, and mix the other things amongſt them; and boyl it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain in 6 ounces of Nightſhade-wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, till it be conſumed, and ſo make a Plaiſter of it; and firſt annoint the ſore with Oyl of Roſes, and then lay the Plaiſter thereupon.</p>
                  <p>If the Canker corrode, and ſpread abroad, then take Barley meal 4 oun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, Oyl of Violets, oyl of Roſes, each three ounces, Tutty prepared 2. oun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, Blood-ſtone 1 ounce. Bray the
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:170219:104"/>oyl of Roſes with 4 whites of Eggs; a good while in a Leaden Morter, and likewiſe beat the Blood-ſtone in wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Lillies, then temper them all together, and dip ſmall tents in it, and lay them all on the ſore.</p>
                  <p>Then take one ounce and a half of oyl of Roſes prepared in a Leaden Morter, as before, and two ounces of the juyce of Nightſhade, 1. ounce of ſtarch, and an ounce and an half of Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus: mix and temper them all together; in a Leaden Morter, and therewith of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten annoint the breaſts round about the Canker or Fiſtula.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>A Plaiſter for the Fiſtula.</head>
                  <p>Take Mummey, Bolus, juyce of ſteel, Frankincenſe, Hipociſtis, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick, of each 3 drams, Acorn Cups, Cipers Nuts, Galls, Iſinglaſſe, Draga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant, Gum, of each 1 ounce: diſſolve the Iſinglaſſe in red Wine Vinegar, and mix the other ingredients a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt it to a Plaiſter.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="189" facs="tcp:170219:104"/>
                  <head>For Clefts, or Chops of the Nipples.</head>
                  <p>Take Mutton, or Lambs Suet, as much as you pleaſe, and after it is mol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, and clarified, then waſh it in Roſe-water, and therewith annoint the Nipples. And thus much for the Diſeaſes in the Breaſts.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="chapter">
               <pb n="190" facs="tcp:170219:105"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Chap. XVII.</hi> Shewing means and Remedies for thoſe Nurſes that went milk.</head>
               <p>Having already at large diſcourſed to you the infirmities, happening by reaſon of ſuperfluous; or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gealed milk; and the evil accidents that attend the ſame, with the means of their prevention and Remedy: it is alſo convenient for their ſakes, who would be Nurſes, and cannot for want of milk; to ſhew them ſome means to increaſe it where it is wanting.</p>
               <p>Women given much to fretting, or who are by nature lean and ſickly, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a bad digeſture in ſtomach &amp; Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, cannot breed ſtore of milk, nor good milk: alſo bad meats and drinks, hinder the ingendring of milk, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they ought to be forborn.</p>
               <pb n="191" facs="tcp:170219:105"/>
               <p>And women that would increaſe their milk, let them eat good meats if they can get it, and drink milk where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in Fennel ſeed hath been ſteeped.</p>
               <p>If the woman be of a hot nature, and full of Choler, let her drink Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley water and Almond milk, eat Lec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice with her meat, Burrage, Spin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage, Goats milk, Cowes milk, and Lamb ſodden with Verjuice; And avoid ſorrow and anger as much as may be: and comfort the ſtomach with the Confections of Anniſeeds, Carraway and Cominſeeds: and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe uſe theſe ſeeds ſodden in water.</p>
               <p>Alſo, take Anniſeeds, two drams and a half beaten, and temper them with the broth of Cole<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>orts, and drink it when you go to bed.</p>
               <p>Alſo, take Barley water and boyl therein green Fennel, and Dill, and ſweeten it with Sugar, and drink it at your pleaſure.</p>
               <p>If you would have an outward means, uſe this Plaiſter following.</p>
               <p>Take half an ounce of Deers ſuet, and as much Parſley roots, with the hearbs, an ounce and a half of Barley
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:170219:106"/>meal, three drams of red Storax, and three ounces of oyl of ſweet Almonds: ſeeth the roots and hearbs well, and beat them to pap; and then mingle the other amongſt them, and lay it warm on the Nipples, it increaſeth milk.</p>
               <p>Thus have I Counſelled women of all ſorts, how to free themſelves from all caſualties, the frailty of their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſubjects them to; which when you finde the benefit of, give God the glory, and ſin no more, leſt a worſe thing ſall unto thee.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="appendix">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:170219:106"/>
            <head>AN APPENDIX TOUCHING <hi>The DROPSY.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THis being an infirmity under which many labour, and few are cured thereof partly, nay moſt, by reaſon of their inability; I thought it very neceſſary, having this opportunity put into my hands, to add this ſmall Treatiſe of the Kinds, Cauſe, and Cure of Dropſies.</p>
            <p>This Diſeaſe the Greeks call <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the Latins a water between the fleſh and the skin, and vulg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rly <hi>Hydrops</hi> or <hi>Hydropicus morbus,</hi> the Dropſy or an Hydropical diſeaſe; which name ſeems to have b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>en taken from water which in Greek is called,<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Avicenna</hi> defineth the Dropſy thus: That it is a material ſickneſs,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:170219:107"/>ingendred from a material, outward, and co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d cauſe, and thereby either the whole Body, or many parts and Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers thereof do ſwell. All Authors do not agree about it, ſome call it a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe, and ſome place it among the Symptomes; but they that are afflicted with it, need not care by what name it is called, ſo they were freed from it; therefore I ſhall not ſtay upon the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finition of it, but proceed to directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for the Cure; but be ſure it is a laeſion and depravation of the digeſtive faculty, and unconcoction of the blood; whereby the nutritive faculty is hindred, and corrupted throughout the whole Body, and the natural ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the Liver impedited; and this proceeds from a cold and moiſt humour, that penetrates through the Body, and ſwells the Members, puffs up the Face, ſwells the Feet and Leggs, and the Cods of men: deſtroys the natural complexion, altering it into a whitely colour, cauſeth great appetite to drink, and little or none to eat; ſtoppeth the Terms in women cauſeth retention both of Stool &amp; Excrement:
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:170219:107"/>and ſometimes hard Tumors about the Bowels and other parts.</p>
            <p>This for the deſcription or definition: yet this Diſeaſe hath ſeveral degrees, Kinds or Species.</p>
            <p>One kind of <hi>Dropſy</hi> is called <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarca,</hi> and <hi>Hypoſarca;</hi> another <hi>Aſcites;</hi> and a third <hi>Tympania</hi> or <hi>Tympanites,</hi> or in Engliſh Tympanies.</p>
            <p>Conſerve of Fumitory, is not a miſs to be uſed for cleanſing of the blood in all kind of Dropſies, at the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of them; but to proceed firſt to this kind of Dropſy called <hi>Anaſarca.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is a wateriſh humour that lyeth between the fleſh and the skin, through all the Body cauſing a ſwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and is known by preſſing the fleſh with ones finger, the dint or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion thereof will remain a great while after; the Pulſe is ſlow, the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vie members ſwell, and the party is ſubject to be afflicted with a looſeneſs, or ſcowring, and bad digeſtion of meat, which is the cauſe of it, that it turns into flegm inſtead of blood.</p>
            <p>If it be a woman, it may be cauſed through retention or ſtopping of her
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:170219:108"/>Terms; therefore all means poſſible is to be uſed, to provoke and drive them down.</p>
            <p>Let the Patient be purged with Pills of Rhabarb; and to expel the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, uſe this Confection following.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Confection for the watery Dropſy.</head>
               <p>Take Turbith, half an ounce: Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modactyls, one ounce: wild Saffron ſeeds peeſed, three quarters of an ounce: Ginger, Cinamon Anniſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eds, of each one ſcruple: Violets, Sorrel ſeed, of each one dram: Sugar two ounces: Honey of Roſes, four oun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, boyl the Honey and Sugar toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with Fumitory water until you may ſcum it clear: then mix the reſt with it, and boyl it to a Confection, take hereof half an ounce in a mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
               <p>Take Annis, yellow Rape ſeed, Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca Indiae, of each one ſcruple: Licoris, Rhabarb, of each one dragme: Aſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabacca,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:170219:108"/>half a dram; Conſerve of Marjorom, one ounce; Conſerve of Roſes, three ounces: Syrup of Quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Oximel, a ſufficient quantity to make it into a Confection. Take hereof a dram in a morning.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Pills for the ſame.</head>
               <p>Take Pills Aggregative, two ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples; Ammoniaci, one ſcruple: make it into ſix Pills with Oximel; take two in a morning.</p>
               <p>The maſſe of Pills before mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, are prepared by the Apotheca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, therefore do not ſtartle that they bear no <hi>Engliſh</hi> name; for they are more commonly known by thoſe Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles.</p>
               <p>In this Diſeaſe, uſe abſtinence from meat and drink, as much as may be; forbear drowſineſs and lazineſſe, and addict your ſelf to reaſonable ſweating and exerciſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:170219:109"/>
               <head>Of another kinde of Dropſy called Aſcites.</head>
               <p>This Species of this Diſeaſe ſwelleth only the Belly and Leggs, and the up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per parts dry: and the Belly ſwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth like a Bladder, and ſoundeth like a drum head, or as the Belly of a rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Sheep will do, if you cl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>p your hand thereon; that's not unknown to every Clown, then wonder not at this; And if the ſick perſon ſtir from ſide to ſide, the water may be heard forcibly to ſtir about: the skin is ſtretched out, ſo that it receiveth no dint or impreſſion of ones finger as in the other kind of Dropſy; the Pulſe is ſmall, wanting vigour of heat to cauſe motion, and the original of all is the weakneſs and debility of the Liver, that it cannot exerciſe its natural fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty of concocting the meat and drink into blood, but unnaturally al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereth the moiſture thereof into wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
               <p>This kind of Dropſy may come
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:170219:109"/>ſometimes from overmuch heat of the Liver, as well as cold.</p>
               <p>If it proceed from hot cauſes, the Urine the Patient avoids is little, and that of a very high red colour, ſome ſpots like little ſtones appearing in it; the party ſuffereth intolerable thirſt; and the more he drinks, the more he deſires drink; but it quencheth not his flames, no more then Brimſtone and Oyl will quench fire.</p>
               <p>This Diſeaſe is dangerous, and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes breaks up the root, or at beſt ſtrikes near at it.</p>
               <p>But for means which God hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to be uſed while time is, take theſe following,</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Syrup for the Dropſy through heat of the Liver, and to quench the thirſty deſires of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient in that diſeaſe.</head>
               <p>Take Endive, four handfuls; Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den hair, Harts tongue, of each one handful: Fennel ſeed, Parſley ſeed, of each half an ounce: Spica Nardi, Spica Romani, of each a quarter of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:170219:110"/>an ounce; make a decoction hereof, and then boyl it up to a ſyrrup, with a ſufficient quantity of Sugar.</p>
               <p>The Body of the Patient in this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe, is much ſubject to coſtiveneſs, or binding of the Belly; purging there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore with Clyſters, Pills, and Potions, are requiſite to be uſed in this caſe, and to endeavour to open the obſtructions of the Liver, and ſtrengthen the ſame.</p>
               <p>To purge with Rhabarb or the ſyrup thereof once a week, is very good for this purpoſe; drink Wormwood Beer or Wine, and uſe alſo this gentle purging Potion.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A purging Potion for the dry Dropſy.</head>
               <p>Take the flowers of Burrage, Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets, Fumitory, each half an ounce; Licoris, Jujubes, Currans, Worm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood, each one quarter of an ounce; Prunes, eight or ten: Spikenard, one dram; boyl them altogether in Whey, ſtrain it, and then infuſe therein one night, half an ounce of the ſhells of yellow Mirobalans, ſo ſtrain it for a Potion.</p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:170219:110"/>
               <p>Clyſters are alſo very neceſſary and profitable for this Diſeaſe; and amongſt others, theſe following are very commendable.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Clyſter for the Dropſie.</head>
               <p>Take Bloodwort, Camomil, St. Johns wort, or each one handful; boyl them in well fair water, then take twelve or ſixteen ounces of the decoction and add to it Salt, one dram; three ounces of Sallet oyl, and half a dram of <hi>Hiera picra,</hi> or <hi>Caffia</hi> extracted; mix them together for a Cliſter, and give it warm.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For the ſame another Cliſter more looſening.</head>
               <p>Take Mallows, Holly-hocks, Peers, Camomile, Herb Mercury, of each one handful; boyl theſe herbs well in water, or in broth of Tripes, or other pottage made of freſh fleſh; take 16 ounces of the decoction, and thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to add Sallet oyl, Salt, Hiera picra, or Caſſia, and Benedicta laxativa, of each
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:170219:111"/>half an ounce, wherewith mix the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coction, and give it for a Cliſter very warm.</p>
               <p>If there be any pain or griping in the Belly, which windeneſs too often cauſeth, then uſe with the Herbs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore mentioned, an ounce of Anni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeds, Fennel ſeeds and Carraway-ſeeds, altogether groſly beaten, or the quantity of an ounce of either of them ſevera<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, which you can get.</p>
               <p>Thus for Coſtiveneſs, and Obſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in this Diſeaſe; on the contrary ſometimes the Patient is ſubject to ſcowring, and a red flux with it, for which uſe theſe means following.</p>
               <p>Give to the Patient the Conſerve, &amp; concocted roots of Cicory, Juyce &amp; Marmalade of Quinces, Trochisk and Conſerve of Barberries with Vinegar, and ſuch other things as are binding and cooling in operation.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:170219:111"/>
               <head>For this Dropſy, and all other kinds, and alſo for the Green ſickneſſe too, theſe Pills following, are excellent.</head>
               <p>Take of the Maſſe of the Pill of Hiera with Agarick, one dram and a half: of the Pill of Opopanax, three drams: of the extract of Rhabarb, of Gentian root, of Centory the leſſe, each one dram; Steel prepared, four drams; the root of Aaron prepared, Tartar vitriolated, each two ſcruples; Chymical oyl of Wormwood, one ſcruple: oyl of Cinamon, of Cloves, each ſix drops: Syrup of the Five roots, a ſufficient quantity to make it into Pills; make of every dram hereof ſix Pills; let the Patient take two here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of every morning, and as many at four a clock in the afternoon, and drink after it a draught of Wormwood-Wine or Ale, ſtirring or excerciſing after it the ſpace of an hour.</p>
               <p>To provoke and expel the Urine, is very requiſite in this Diſeaſe; for which theſe things following are very good.</p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:170219:112"/>
               <p>Take Rue, St. Johns wort, Penny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>royal, Sage, Marjoram, Wormwood, Licoris, Anniſeeds, Fennel roots, Elecampane roots, of each one quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of an ounce; boyl them a little in a quart of White-wine, and take thereof three ounces morning and night.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For the ſame.</head>
               <p>Take a head or two of Garlick, and a handful of St Johns wort; boyl them together in a pint of White-wine, till a third part be waſted: ſtrain it, and drink three or four ſpoofuls thereof at a time morning and evening.</p>
               <p>The roots of great Fern boyled in White-wine, and drunk, (the Wine I mean, not the roots) is verygood for this purpoſe.</p>
               <p>This Decoction following, is alſo good for the ſame.</p>
               <p>Take the roots of Nettles, Parſley, Fennel, Elecampane, Licoris, Aſara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bacca,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:170219:112"/>of each one dram; boyl them a little in a quart of White-wine, and drink thereof as of the former.</p>
               <p>Outwardly for this Diſeaſe may be uſed Pultiſſes, Unguents, and Plaiſters; ſuch as dry and expel wind and do ſtrengthen and mollifie the Belly and lower parts, for which purpoſe, this Plaiſter following may effectually be uſed.</p>
               <p>Take Coloquint, Holly-hock ſeeds, Diagridion, Aloes, Mirth, Mallowes roots, Béellion, of each one dram and a half; Ireos, three drams: Mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows ſeeds, wild Cucumbers, Carda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mome, Euphorbium, of each three drams: Boreas, Salgem, of each one quarter of one ounce; mix all theſe and incorporate them well together, with Gooſe greaſe, Ducks greaſe, Calves ſuet and Hoggs ſuet, as much as is ſufficient to make them into a Plaiſter or ſalve, and apply it all over the Belly.</p>
               <p>For the ſame, is good to temper the Salve of Bay-berries with Cowes
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:170219:113"/>or Goats dung, and uſe it as the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For the ſwelling of the privy members in this Diſeaſe, this Salve follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is to be uſed.</head>
               <p>Take Annis, Fennel, and Comin ſeeds, beaten ſmall together, of each one ounce and a half; Bean meale Ebalus, the juyce of Elder leaves, and Wine a ſufficient quantity to make it a Salve or Pultis, and lay it on the Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and privities.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For the ſame.</head>
               <p>Take Barley meale, Cypreſs roots, Sheeps dung, Borax and Bolus, of each a like quantity: beat them together, and make a Plaiſter thereof with Hoggs greaſe or Gooſe greaſe, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply it to the Belly and privities.</p>
               <p>The oyl of Camomile and Rue, mixed together, is a very good Oint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for the dropſy,</p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:170219:113"/>
               <p>Take notice alſo by the way, that Sweating, and Bathing in hot dry Baths, is very effectual for all kind of Dropſies.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the kind of Dropſie, called Tym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies.</head>
               <p>There are three ſorts of Tympanies, the one called <hi>Aqupſa,</hi> or the watery Tympany or Dropſy, of which we have already treated.</p>
               <p>A ſecond called <hi>Ventoſa,</hi> or a Drop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy or Tympany of wind, of which we now proceed to ſpeak, which is cauſed more of wind then water, and thence deriveth its name; and in this Diſeaſe the Belly ſwelleth up very high, and the Navel ſtarteth out; the Belly is very hard and ſoundeth, if one thereon clap his hand.</p>
               <p>There is another Species called <hi>Carnoſa,</hi> by which may be underſtood fatneſſe of the Belly, or as ſome ſay, gorre Bellies; but it is, in plain En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh, a fleſhy Tympany, or fleſhy ſwelling, no way dangerous at all, but Maids Bellies are much ſubject to this
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:170219:114"/>Tympany; and for their Cure the beſt is mother Midwife, and therefore, I ſay no more of it, but leave it to her diſcretion.</p>
               <p>But for the Cure of the <hi>Ventoſa,</hi> or windy Tympany or Dropſy, uſe theſe Rules following.</p>
               <p>Avoid all windy meats, eſchew cold, and keep warm: uſe alſo Swea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, and uſe the Confection <hi>de Baccis Lauri,</hi> be moderate in Dyet and uſe exerciſe.</p>
               <p>Uſe alſo theſe Conſerves, or any of them, as Conſerve of Elder leaves, Betony, Gilly-flowers, Roſemary, Fennel, Annis, Comin or the like.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Suppoſitory for the ſame.</head>
               <p>Take Salgem, Rue, Bever-cod, Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phorbium, Nettle ſeed, of each one dram; mix it with about three oun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of decocted Honey, and thereof make Suppoſitories.</p>
               <p>Uſe to annoint the Belly with hot Oyles, ſuch as are oyl of Dill, oyl of Rue, Coſtus, and Bay-berries.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:170219:114"/>
               <head>A Plaiſter for the ſame effectual.</head>
               <p>Take Goats dung or Sheeps dung dryed twelve ounces, roots of wild Cucumbers, roots of Ebulus, of each two ounces; Barley meal, 12 ounces: ſteeled Vinegar, four ounces; boyl it all well in ſharp Lee, and make there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of a Plaiſter, which apply warm to the Belly, or any part of the Body ſwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with wind, to open the Pores, and draw out the ſame.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Cliſter effectual for the ſame,</head>
               <p>Take Ireos, Hyſop, Smallage, Rue, Barefoot, of each one handful; Annis, Fennel, Ameos, Bay-berries, of each half an ounce: boyl all theſe very well in clean water, then take of this De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coction twelve or ſixteen ounces, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the ſtrength of the Patient, and add to it clarified Honey, and oyl of Rue, of each one ounce and a half; and ſtone Salt, one dram: ſo make it into a Cliſter, and adminiſter it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:170219:115"/>
               <head>A Syrup for the Dropſy.</head>
               <p>Take green roots of Ireos, or in <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh,</hi> Flowerdeluce (and yet that name is not quite <hi>Engliſh</hi> neither) twenty four ounces; cut them in pieces, and infuſe them three days in Well water, as much as will onely cover them, ſtirring them twice a day: then ſtrain that water from them, &amp; reſerve it in a clean pot, &amp; add the like quantity of freſh water to them, doing as you did before; then ſtrain the ſecond water, and mix both together, and boyl it with Sugar a little; and then add thereunto Scabious and Mayden-hair, of each one handful; Sperage roots, Fennel roots, and Ireos roots, of each half a handful; peeled Melon ſeed, Gourd ſeeds, Cucumber ſeeds peeled, Pompeon ſeeds, Purſlane ſeeds Cicory, Endive and Lettice ſeed, of each one quarter of an ounce; Fennel, Annis, Sperage, and Smallage ſeed, of each half a dram; Millet and Winter Cher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, of each three drams; fat dates and figs, of each ſix; Licoris and Mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:170219:115"/>of each five drams; boyl all toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to the waſting of half, and then ſtrain it, and boil up the decoction to a ſyrup with Sugar: of this ſyrup, give about an ounce at a time, and ſometimes more, and to ſtrengthen the Liver, ſteep therein a quarter of an ounce of Rhabarb.</p>
               <p>Alſo for the Dropſy, theſe ſyrups are good to be uſed; as, ſyrup of Worm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood, of the Five roots, of Maiden-hair, and Betony, and Wines com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded with Wormwood, Egremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, Calamint, Cinamon, odoriferous ſeeds, and things of the like nature: Abſtain from all exceſſe, and uſe ſuch meats and drinks as are of a drying, heating, attenuating nature, &amp; eaſy of digeſtion; forbear new ſweet Wine, or drink; and in all things uſe meaſure, for therein conſiſteth the greateſt virtue.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
